<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Policy on Access to Information</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=12453", title: "Policy on Access to Information"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=12453&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2023-06-28",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Policy on Access to Information</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.1</span>This policy takes effect on June 28, 2023.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.2</span>This policy replaces the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a> dated July 13, 2022.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Authorities</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1</span>This policy is issued pursuant  to paragraph 70(1)(c) of the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>. This policy also  contains elements that relate to paragraphs 70(1)(b) and (d), sections 79 and 89,  and paragraph 94(5) of the Act. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.2</span>The President of the Treasury  Board, as designated Minister for the paragraphs of the<em> Access to Information Act </em>referenced in 2.1 above, is responsible  for establishing policies and prescribing forms concerning the operation of the  Act and its Regulations.  </li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Objectives and expected results</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1</span>The objectives of this policy are: 
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1.1</span>Strengthened openness and transparency of government.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1.2</span>Strengthened accountability of government to its citizens and enhanced  democratic participation.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2</span>The expected results of this policy are:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.1</span>Government institutions have appropriate processes and tools to support the administration of the <em>Access to Information Act.</em></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.3</span>Government institutions offer requesters clear and accessible processes  to make access to information requests.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.4</span>Government institutions provide requesters with complete, accurate, and timely responses to requests for government information.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.5</span>Employees understand their obligations under the <em>Access to Information Act.</em></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.6</span>Performance is measured and compliance issues are identified and addressed.  </li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Requirements</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1</span>Heads  of government institutions are responsible for:  


	
	<section><header><h3><span class="mrgn-rght-lg">Delegation of powers, duties and functions under Part 1 and  Part 3 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em></span></h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1</span>Deciding whether to delegate, pursuant to section 95 of the <em>Access to  Information Act</em>, any of the powers, duties or functions under the Act that  are listed in Appendix B: Powers That Can Be Delegated.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2</span>When signing a delegation order, giving careful consideration to the  delegation of any powers, duties or functions pursuant to section 95 of the <em>Access  to Information Act</em> and ensuring that:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.1</span>Powers, duties and functions are:
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.1.1</span>Delegated only to officers and employees of their government  institution, or of another government institution within the same ministerial  portfolio when there is a service-sharing agreement between the two government  institutions; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.1.2</span>Not delegated to consultants, members of a Minister’s exempt staff,  employees of other government institutions with which there is no  service-sharing agreement, or to individuals from the private sector; and   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.1.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.1.3</span>Delegated to positions identified by title, not to individuals  identified by name.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.2</span>Delegates understand that they are  accountable for any decisions they make, but ultimate responsibility remains  with the head of the government institution.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.3</span>Delegates are at the appropriate  level to be able to fulfil the duties of their delegated authorities and are well  informed of their responsibilities.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.4</span>Delegates cannot further delegate  powers, duties and functions that have been delegated to them, although  employees and consultants may perform tasks in support of delegates’ responsibilities.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.5</span>Delegation orders are reviewed when  the circumstances surrounding the delegations have changed. A delegation  order remains in force until it is replaced. </li></ul></li></ul></section></li></ul><section><header><h3>General  Requirements</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2</span>Heads  of government institutions or their delegates are responsible for: 
	  
<section><header><h3>Access to information awareness</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.1</span>Ensuring that employees of the government institution are aware of policies,  procedures and legal responsibilities under the Act.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Contracts and agreements</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.2</span>Establishing measures to  ensure that the government institution meets the requirements of the <em>Access  to Information Act</em> when contracting with private sector entities, or when  establishing agreements or arrangements with public sector institutions.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Service Sharing </h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.3</span>Ensuring  that the requirements of section 96 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> are  respected when entering into a service-sharing agreement.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.4</span>Providing a copy of any new service-sharing agreement,  and any material changes to an existing service-sharing agreement, to the  President of the Treasury Board and to the Information Commissioner, as soon as  possible after entering into the agreement or after any material changes arise.  This responsibility rests with the head of a government institution to which  the services are provided.  </li></ul></section></li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Responding to Requests for Access to Records under Part 1 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em></h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3</span>Heads  of government institutions or their delegates are responsible for:  
	  
	<section><header><h3>Control of Records</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.1</span>Determining,  in a manner consistent with jurisprudence  and considering any TBS guidance, whether records are under the control of the  government institution.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Exercising discretion</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.2</span>Exercising discretion under Part 1 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and associated Regulations in a fair, reasonable and impartial manner with  respect to decisions made in the processing of requests and the resolution of  complaints pursuant to the Act.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.3</span>With the  Information Commissioner’s written approval, exercising the discretion to decline  to act on a request when, in the opinion of the head or delegate, the request  is vexatious, made in bad faith or an abuse of the right to make a request for  access to records, only after considering: 
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.3.1</span>The purpose of the Act, which is to enhance the  accountability and transparency of federal institutions in order to promote an  open and democratic society and to enable public debate on the conduct of those  institutions, and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.3.2</span>The core principle of the Act that government  information should be available to the public, subject to necessary exceptions  that are limited and specific.   </li></ul></li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Duty to assist</h3><h3>Protecting the identity of requesters</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.4</span>Ensuring that requesters'  identities are protected and only used or disclosed when authorized by the <em>Privacy Act</em> and where there is a clear  need-to-know.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Complete, accurate and timely responses</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.5</span>Ensuring every reasonable effort is made to help requesters in connection with the request, in order to provide complete,  accurate, and timely responses.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Access to record in format requested</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.6</span>Ensuring that every reasonable effort is made to provide responses to  requesters in the format requested, in accordance with the regulations.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Language of access </h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.7</span>Providing records in the official  language requested, in accordance with subsection 12(2) of the Act.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Accessible format for requesters </h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.8</span>Providing  a copy of records in an alternative format, in accordance with subsection 12(3)  of the Act, when requested by the requester.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Processing requests</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9</span>Establishing effective procedures and systems to respond to requests  under Part 1 of the Act to ensure that:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.1</span>Requests can be received  through the prescribed platform in accordance with <em>Appendix E: Prescribed Platforms for Receiving and Processing  Access to Information Requests</em> of the<em> Directive on Access to Information  Requests</em>, unless the institution has received an exception  to the use of the platform; and can be received in written format by other  means;  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.2</span>Requests are processed using prescribed platforms in accordance with <em>Appendix E: Prescribed Platforms for  Receiving and Processing Access to Information Requests</em> of the <em>Directive  on Access to Information Requests</em>, when platforms have been prescribed,  unless the institution has received an exception to use of the platform;  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.3</span>Deliberations and decisions concerning requests  received under the Act are documented;  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.4</span>The requested records are  reviewed to determine whether they are subject to Part 1 of the Act; and, if  they are, determining whether any exemptions apply;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.5</span>The principle of severability  is applied;  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.6</span>Any consultations necessary  for the processing of requests made pursuant to the Act are undertaken promptly;  and  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9.7</span>Any transfer of an access to  information request to other government institutions is performed within the  timeline prescribed under the Act.  </li></ul></li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Confidences of the Queen’s Privy  Council</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.10</span>Consulting the institution’s legal counsel, in compliance with <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/access-information-manual.html#cha13_4">established procedures</a>, prior to excluding  confidences of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.11"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.11</span> Upon the request of the Information  Commissioner, acquiring assurances that excluded information is a Confidence of  the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada, in compliance with <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/access-information-manual.html#cha13_4">established procedures</a>.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Acting upon orders of the  Information Commissioner</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.12"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.12</span>Implementing  an order of the Information Commissioner or seeking a review by the Federal  Court of the matter that is the subject of the order within the timelines  prescribed by the Act.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.13"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.13</span>Notifying  TBS when the Information Commissioner provides the institution with an initial  report that sets out any order that the Commissioner intends to make.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Considering other means of making  government information accessible </h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.14"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.14</span>Establishing procedures to review the nature of requests received under Part 1 of the  Act and assessing the feasibility of making frequently requested and disclosed types  of information available by other means.   </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Addressing allegations of an obstruction  of the right of access</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.15"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.15</span>Ensuring that appropriate procedures are in place to address any alleged  obstruction related to the right of access and the Information Commissioner’s  duties and functions under the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, including  conduct described in subsections 67(1) and 67.1(1) of the Act.  </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Monitoring and reporting </h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.16"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.16</span>Monitoring compliance with this policy and its supporting instruments within their  institution.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.17"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.17</span>Investigating when issues regarding policy compliance arise and insuring appropriate  remedial action is taken to address these issues.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.18"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.18</span>Advising the Secretary of the Treasury Board on a  timely basis when significant issues regarding policy compliance arise.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.19"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.19</span>Preparing and tabling an annual report on the administration of the Act in each  House of Parliament in accordance with requirements established by TBS.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.20"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.20</span>Providing the Information Commissioner and TBS with a copy of the annual report.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.21"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.21</span>Providing TBS with a statistical report on the administration of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> within the  institution.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.22"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.22</span>Updating their government institution’s chapter in the prescribed annual index  of information about responsibilities, programs, and information holdings; and  providing TBS with a copy as directed by TBS.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.23"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.23</span>Providing the contact information of the appropriate officer to receive access  requests for publication in the prescribed contact list.  </li></ul></section></li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Proactive  Publication of Information under Part 2 of the <em>Access  to Information Act</em></h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4</span>Heads of institutions are responsible for:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.1</span>Designating the official(s) responsible for supporting the head of the institution’s accountability for requirements under Part 2 of the Act. </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.5</span>Heads of institutions or their designate(s) are responsible for: 
	 <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.5.1</span>Establishing effective procedures and systems, including use of prescribed platforms, to meet the proactive publication requirements under Part 2 of the Act and TBS direction on proactive publication. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.5.2</span>Monitoring compliance with proactive publication requirements under Part 2 of the Act and TBS direction on proactive publication. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.5.3</span>Reporting to TBS on compliance with proactive publication requirements under Part 2 of the Act and TBS direction on proactive publication in accordance with requirements established by TBS. </li></ul></li></ul></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Roles of other government organizations</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1</span>This section identifies other key government organizations in relation to  this policy. In and of itself, this section does not confer any authority.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2</span>Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat is  responsible for supporting the President of Treasury Board in:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.1</span>Issuing direction and guidance to government institutions with respect  to the administration of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and the  interpretation of this policy and its supporting instruments.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.2</span>Approving exceptions to  any requirement in this policy or its supporting instruments.
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.2.1</span>Advising the Office of the Information Commissioner as  required of any exceptions to any requirement in this policy or its supporting  instruments that have been granted.  </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.3</span>Prescribing forms and platforms to be used in the  administration of the Act, as well as the form and content of the annual report to Parliament.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.4</span>Reviewing regularly, or in accordance with the timing of the five-year  review of the Act, the policy, its related directives, mandatory procedures,  standards, guidelines, forms, and prescribed platforms, to assess their  continued effectiveness and accuracy. When substantiated by risk-analysis, TBS  will also ensure an evaluation is conducted.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.5</span>Overseeing compliance with this policy and its supporting instruments  across government institutions, leveraging existing reporting mechanisms as  appropriate.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.6</span> Publishing annually an index that describes  government institutions, their responsibilities, programs and information  holdings.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.7</span>Reviewing  and publishing updates to government institutions' chapters in the annual  index.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.8</span>Reviewing  and publishing updates to the titles and addresses of the officers who receive  access requests at each institution.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.9</span>Reviewing  and publishing statistics collected by institutions under 70 (1)(d).  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.10</span>Working with the Canada School of Public Service to  integrate knowledge elements related to the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and associated policy instruments into training courses, programs and knowledge  assessment instruments.  </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.3</span>The  Information Commissioner is an Agent of Parliament with the duty of ensuring  that rights and obligations set out in the <em>Access  to Information Act</em> are respected.
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.3.1</span>The  Commissioner receives and independently investigates complaints from applicants  or self-initiated complaints on any matter related to obtaining or requesting  access under the Act to records under the control of a government institutions.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.3.2</span>At the end of  an investigation, the Commissioner reports findings and may make orders and  recommendations to government institutions.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.3.3</span>The  Commissioner’s written approval is required for a head of an institution to  decline to act on a request for access.   </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.3.4</span>In addition,  the Commissioner reports to Parliament on activities annually and can report at  any time on any important matter within the scope of the Commissioner's powers,  duties and functions.  </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.4</span>The Privacy Commissioner of Canada is an Agent of  Parliament with the duty of protecting and promoting privacy rights in relation  to personal information. 
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.4.1</span> The Privacy  Commissioner may be consulted on complaints to the Information Commissioner  regarding disclosures of information that an institution has withheld as  personal information.   </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.5</span>The Clerk of the Privy Council Office is  responsible for ensuring the integrity of the Cabinet process and the stewardship of the  documents that support this process. As custodian of confidences of the Queen's  Privy Council for Canada of the current and previous ministries, the Clerk is  responsible for policies on the administration of these confidences and for the  ultimate determination of what constitutes such confidences, and must be  consulted in a manner consistent with the guidance in the <em>Access to  Information Manual</em>.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.6</span>The Department of Justice is responsible for supporting  the Minister of Justice in the role of designated Minister for certain  provisions of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, specifically:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.6.1</span>Designating, by order-in-council, the head of a government institution for the  purposes of the Act.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.6.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.6.2</span>Recommending  extensions of the right of access by Order in Council.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.6.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.6.3</span>Specifying investigative bodies and classes of investigations.  </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.6.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.6.4</span>Amending Schedule I of the Act.  </li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Application</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.1</span>This policy and its  supporting instruments apply to government institutions as defined in section 3  of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, including departments, ministries of  state, any parent Crown corporations and any wholly owned subsidiary of these  corporations.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.2</span>This policy does not apply to the Bank of  Canada.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. Consequences of non-compliance</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.1</span>For those government institutions that do not  comply with this policy and its related instruments, there may be a requirement  to provide additional information relating to the development and  implementation of compliance strategies in their annual report to Parliament or  to TBS directly. This reporting may be in addition to other reporting  requirements.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.2</span>TBS will work collaboratively with heads of  institutions or their delegates to restore compliance.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.3</span>For those government institutions subject to the  Management Accountability Framework (MAF) and to the extent that access to  information is considered in the performance measurement indicators of the MAF,  non-compliance with respect to this policy and its related instruments will be  reported.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.4</span>On the basis of analysis of monitoring and  information received, the designated Minister may make recommendations to the  head of the government institution. This could include prescribing any  additional reporting requirements, as outlined in section 7.1 above.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.1</span>Legislation

<ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SI-83-113/"><em>Access to Information Act Heads of Government Institutions Designation  Order</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-83-507/index.html"><em>Access to Information Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-5/"><em>Canada Evidence Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/I-21/"><em>Interpretation Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/L-7.7/"><em>Library and Archives of Canada Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/"><em>Official Languages Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-83-508/"><em>Privacy Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-31.9/"><em>Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</em></a></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.2</span>Related  policy instruments

<ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18310"><em>Directive on Access to Information Requests</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=30683"><em>Policy on Communications and Federal Identity</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578"><em>Policy on Government  Security</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32621"><em>Policy on People  Management</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy  Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603"><em>Policy on Service and  Digital</em></a></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.3</span>Related guidance 

<ul><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information-privacy-notices.html">Access to Information and Privacy Notices</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/access-information-manual.html">Access to Information Manual</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/delegation-under-access-information-act-privacy-act.html">Delegation under the Access to Information  Act and the Privacy Act</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/access-informatio-policies-guidance/programs-holdings-online-publishing-requirements.html">Info Source Online Publishing Requirements</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/supporting-tool-access-information-personal-information-requests-principles-assisting-requesters.html">Principles for  Assisting Requesters</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha9">9. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla9.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">9.1</span>Members of the public may contact <a href="mailto:questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca" title="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/tbs-sct/cmn/contact-eng.asp#enquiries">Treasury  Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a> regarding any questions about this policy.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla9.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">9.2</span>Employees of federal institutions may contact  their <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/ap/atip-aiprp/coord-eng.asp">Access to Information and Privacy Coordinator</a> regarding any questions about this policy.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla9.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">9.3</span>Access to Information and Privacy  Coordinators may contact the <a href="mailto:ippd-dpiprp@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Access to Information Policy and Performance  Division</a> for information  about this policy.
    </li></ul></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix  A: Definitions</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Note: Certain terms contain excerpts (in quotation marks, with the  reference cited) from the <em>Access to Information Act </em>(the Act). </p><dl><dt><strong>access request</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>demande d'accès</em></span>)</dt><dd>A request for access to a record made under the <em>Access  to Information Act</em>.</dd><dt><strong>annual report</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>rapport annuel</em></span>)</dt><dd>A report submitted by the head of a government  institution to Parliament on the administration of the Act within the  institution during the fiscal year.</dd><dt><strong>complainant</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>plaignant</em></span>)</dt><dd>An individual who makes a complaint to the  Information Commissioner on any of the grounds outlined in subsection 30(1) of  the <em>Access to Information Act</em>.</dd><dt><strong>delegate</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>délégué</em></span>)</dt><dd>An officer or employee of a government  institution, or of another  government institution within the same ministerial portfolio when there is a  service-sharing agreement between the two government institutions, who has been  delegated to exercise or perform the powers, duties and functions of a head of an  institution under the Act.</dd><dt><strong>designated minister</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>ministre désigné</em></span>)</dt><dd>A person who is  designated as the Minister under subsection 3.1(1). For the purposes of this  policy, the designated minister is the President of  the Treasury Board.</dd><dt><strong>excluded information</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>renseignements  exclus</em></span>)</dt><dd>The information to which the Act does not apply  as described in sections 68, 68.1, 68.2, 69 and 69.1.</dd><dt><strong>exemption</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>exception</em></span>)</dt><dd>A mandatory or  discretionary provision under the Act that authorizes the head  of the government institution to refuse to disclose  information in response to a request received under the Act.</dd><dt><strong>government institution</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>institution  fédérale</em></span>)</dt><dd>Any department or ministry of state of the  Government of Canada, or any body or office, listed in Schedule in the Act; any  parent Crown corporation; and any wholly-owned subsidiary of a Crown  corporation, within the meaning of section 83 of the <em>Financial  Administration Act</em>. The term "government institution" does not  include Ministers' Offices..</dd><dt><strong>head</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>responsable</em></span>)</dt><dd>The member of the Queen’s Privy Council for  Canada who presides over a department or ministry of state. In any other case,  it is the person designated by the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SI-83-113/"><em>Access to Information Act Heads of Government Institutions Designation  Order</em></a>. If no such person is designated, the chief  executive officer of the institution, whatever their title, is the head.</dd><dt><strong>Implementation Notice</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>avis de mise en  oeuvre</em></span>)</dt><dd>A notice issued by TBS to provide guidance on the interpretation and  application of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and its related policy,  directives, standards and guidelines.</dd><dt><strong>Info Source </strong>(<span lang="fr"><em>Info Source</em></span>)</dt><dd>The TBS-directed webpage published by each  government institution in which the institution describes their program  responsibilities and information holdings. The descriptions are to contain  sufficient clarity and detail to facilitate the exercise of the right of access  under the <em>Access to Information Act.</em> The webpage also provides contact information for government institutions as  well as summaries of court cases and statistics on access requests. This  webpage must be updated at least once per year.</dd><dt><strong>Information Commissioner</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>commissaire à l'information</em></span>)</dt><dd>An Agent of Parliament appointed by Governor in  Council who is mandated to ensure that rights and obligations set out in  Part I of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> are respected </dd><dt><strong>Privacy Commissioner</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>commissaire à la protection de  la vie privée</em></span>)</dt><dd>An Agent of Parliament appointed by the Governor  in Council who is mandated to  ensure that rights and obligations set out in the <em>Privacy Act</em> are respected. </dd><dt><strong>record</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>document</em></span>)</dt><dd>"any  documentary material regardless of medium or form" (section 3).</dd><dt><strong>requester</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>demandeur</em></span>)</dt><dd>A Canadian citizen, a permanent resident or any  individual or corporation present in Canada who requests access to a record  under Part 1 of the Act.</dd><dt><strong>severability</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>prélèvements</em></span>)</dt><dd>Relates to the principle under the Act in which  the protection of information from disclosure must be limited to the portions  of information or material that the head of the government institution is  authorized or obligated to refuse to disclose under the Act. The principle  applies to records that are the subject of an access request.</dd><dt><strong>statistical report</strong> (<span lang="fr"><em>rapport  statistique</em></span>)</dt><dd>Provides data on the administration of the Act  in the previous fiscal year as described in paragraph 70(1)(d) of the Act. The  statistical report is included in government institutions' annual reports to  Parliament. The forms used for preparing the report are prescribed by the  designated minister, as provided under paragraph 70(1)(b) and subsection 94(5)  of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>.</dd></dl></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix  B: Powers  That Can Be Delegated</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Pursuant to section 95 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, the head  of a government institution may, by order, designate one or more officers or  employees of that institution, or, in the case of a service-sharing agreement,  employees of another government institutions within the same ministerial  portfolio, who are at the appropriate level, to exercise or perform any of the  powers, duties or functions that are to be exercised or performed by the  institutional head under the following provisions of the Act and the <em>Access  to Information Regulations</em>.</p><p><strong><em>Access to Information Act</em></strong></p><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><caption class="text-left"><strong>Part 1</strong></caption><tbody><tr><th scope="row">4(2.1) </th><td>Responsibility of government institutions</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">6.1(1), (1.3) (1.4), (2)</th><td>Reason for declining to act on the request</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">7</th><td>Notice where access requested</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">8(1)</th><td>Transfer of request to another government    institution</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">9</th><td>Extension of time limits</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">10</th><td>Where access is refused</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">11(2) </th><td>Application Fee</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">12(2)(b)</th><td>Language of access</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">12(3)(b)</th><td>Access to record in an alternative format</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">13</th><td>Exemption – Information obtained in    confidence</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">14</th><td>Exemption – Federal-provincial affairs</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">15</th><td>Exemption – International affairs and    defence</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16</th><td>Exemption – Law enforcement and    investigations</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16.1*</th><td>Exemption – Records relating to    investigations, examinations and audits</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16.2*</th><td>Exemption – Records relating to    investigations</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16.3*</th><td>Exemption – Investigations, examinations    and reviews under the <em>Canada Elections Act</em></td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16.4*</th><td>Exemption – Public Sector Integrity    Commissioner</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16.5</th><td>Exemption – <em>Public Servants Disclosure    Protection Act</em></td></tr><tr><th scope="row">16.6*</th><td>Exemption – Secretariat of National    Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">17</th><td>Exemption – Safety of individuals</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">18</th><td>Exemption – Economic interests of Canada</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">18.1</th><td>Exemption – Economic interest of the    Canada Post Corporation, Export Development Canada, the Public Sector Pension    Investment Board and VIA Rail Canada Inc.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">19</th><td>Exemption – Personal information</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">20</th><td>Exemption – Third party information</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">20.1*</th><td>Exemption – Public Sector Pension    Investment Board</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">20.2*</th><td>Exemption – Canada Pension Plan Investment    Board</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">20.4*</th><td>Exemption – National Arts Centre    Corporation</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">21</th><td>Exemption – Advice, etc.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">22</th><td>Exemption – Testing procedures, tests and    audits</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">22.1</th><td>Exemption – Internal audits </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">23</th><td>Exemption – Protected Information – solicitors,    advocates and notaries</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">23.1</th><td>Exemption – Protected Information	– patents    and trade-marks </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">24</th><td>Exemption – Statutory prohibitions</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">25</th><td>Severability</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">26</th><td>Exception – Information to be published</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">27(1), (4)</th><td>Notice to third parties</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">28(1)(b), (2), (4)</th><td>Representations of third party and decision</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">33</th><td>Notice to third parties – Investigations </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">35(2)(b)</th><td>Right to make representations</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">37(4)</th><td>Access to be given to complainant</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">41(2)</th><td>Review by Federal Court – government    institution</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">43(2)</th><td>Service or notice</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">44(2)</th><td>Notice to person who request record </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">52(2), (3)</th><td>Special rules for hearings</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">*Note: The exemptions identified with an asterisk may only be claimed by the institutions named in the provision</td></tr></tbody></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><caption class="text-left"><strong>Part 3</strong></caption><tr><th scope="row">94(1), (4)</th><td>Annual report – government institutions</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">96(3), (4), (5)</th><td>Provision of services related to access to information</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><caption class="text-left"><strong><em>Access  to Information Regulations</em></strong></caption><tr><th scope="row">6(1)</th><td>Transfer of request</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">8</th><td>Providing access to record(s)</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">8.1</th><td>Limitations in respect of format</td></tr></table></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2017, <br/>ISBN: 978-0-660-09520-2</p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>