<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Flying Accidents Compensation</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=13589", title: "Flying Accidents Compensation"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=13589&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "1992-10-01",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Flying Accidents Compensation</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Introduction</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>The Flying Accidents Compensation Regulations, made
pursuant to Section 7 of the Aeronautics Act, provide for
the payment of compensation to employees or their dependants
where injury or death is a direct result of a non-scheduled
flight undertaken by an employee in the course of duty, or in the
case of a civil aviation inspector where injury or death is a
direct result of any flight undertaken for the purpose of
conducting a flight test or monitoring commercial air operations
on that flight.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Authority</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec2.1">2.1 Legislative and regulatory</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Aeronautics Act, RSC 1970;</p><p>Flying Accidents Compensation Regulations, P.C.
1972-2613 of November 9, 1972, as amended by P.C. 1975-76 of
January 16, 1975.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec2.2">2.2 Administration</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Claims made pursuant to the Regulations are adjudicated by the
Pension Commission.</p></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. General provisions</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.1">3.1 Application</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>For the purposes of determining the persons to whom the
Regulations apply, the following definitions are applicable:</p><p>civil aviation inspector means (a) an employee
who is required to conduct flight tests to determine the
competency of flight crew personnel and to inspect commercial air
operations, or, (b) an employee who is required to monitor
in-flight cabin procedures in use in commercial air operations (<span lang="fr" xml:lang="fr"><em>inspecteur de l'aviation civile</em></span>);</p><p>employee means any person who is employed in the
Public Service of Canada or under the direction of any department
of the Public Service of Canada other than a member of the Royal
Canadian Mounted Police who is a person described in
paragraph 27(1)(a) or (b) of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police
Superannuation Act (<span lang="fr" xml:lang="fr"><em>employé</em></span>);</p><p>non-scheduled flight means a flight in an
aircraft that is not a private aircraft and that is not operated
on a scheduled flight (<span lang="fr" xml:lang="fr"><em>vol non régulier</em></span>).</p><p>A number of statutes establishing various public service
corporations and agencies have deemed the directors, officers
and/or employees of the organizations to be employed in the
Public Service for purposes of Section 7 of the Aeoronautics
Act, and therefore subject to the Flying Accidents
Compensation Regulations.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.2">3.2 Compensation</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Compensation payable under the Flying Accident Compensation
Regulations is not subject to taxation.</p><p>Where compensation is payable under the Regulations, the
amount payable is equal to the pension that would have been
awarded to, or in respect of, the employee in accordance with the
rate set out in:</p><ul><li>A of the Pension Act, in
the case of disability, and</li><li>of the Pension Act, in the case of death,</li></ul><p>adjusted in accordance with the cost-of-living index, as
described in Part IV of that Act.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.3">3.3 Funeral expenses</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>In the case of the death of an employee or civil aviation
inspector, under the circumstances prescribed in the legislation,
funeral expenses may be paid in addition to any compensation
payable to dependants.</p><p>The amount payable for funeral expenses is equal to the amount
which would have been payable for such expenses under the Government Employees Compensation Act had the claim been
made under that Act.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.4">3.4 Where person reported as missing</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Treasury Board has indicated that favourable consideration
will be given to requests for authority to make advance payments
to dependants during a period when a person is reported missing
on a non-scheduled flight.</p><p>The amount of the advance is determined by the circumstances
in each case but normally approximates the amounts that would be
payable if the missing person were, in fact, killed. Any such
advances are recovered from salary when the missing person is
found or from authorized payments when death is established.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.5">3.5 Compensation recovery other than under flying accidents compensation regulations</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Where death or injury for which compensation is payable under
the regulations occurs in such circumstances that some person has
a legal liability to pay damages in respect of the injury or
death, any amount paid as damages is taken into consideration
when determining the amount payable under the Flying Accidents
Compensation Regulations.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.6">3.6 Exclusions</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>In some instances, there may be compensation, a gratuity or a
pension payable under other legislation, such as the Government Employees Compensation Act. In such a case, the
claimant may choose the authority under which compensation will
be paid, and payments will only be made under the Flying
Accidents Compensation Regulations where the claimant elects
to accept such payment instead of that payable under the
provisions of any other Act.</p><p>This exclusion does not preclude payment of compensation under
the Regulations in addition to benefits under the Public
Service superannuation Act and any other benefits related to
service in the Public service.</p><p>No compensation is payable for the death or injury of an
employee that was due to a self-inflicted wound or any action by
the employee that endangered the safety of the normal process of
the flight.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3.7">3.7 Procedures for claims</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Claims are adjudicated by the Pension Commission.</p><p>The employing department should inform the employee or
dependants, as the case may be, of the benefits available under
the Flying Accidents Compensation Regulations and those
under the Government Employees Compensation Act, to assist
them in deciding under which authority they wish to elect for
compensation. This information may be obtained from the Pension
Commission and Labour Canada, respectively.</p><p>Where the claimant elects to receive compensation under the Flying Accidents Compensation Regulations, the following
information, where applicable, should be submitted to the Pension
Commission:</p><ul><li>full names and addresses of spouse
and children with dates of birth of the latter;</li><li>official death certificate or a certified copy of it;</li><li>findings of any Court of Inquiry or investigation which was
held as to the cause of the accident, and the circumstances in
connection with it;</li><li>precise duty on which the employee was engaged at the time;</li><li>the case of employees other than civilian aviation inspectors,
a copy of the authorization to undertake air travel on duty other
than in a commercial aircraft on a scheduled flight;</li><li>that the injury or death was a direct result of a flight
undertaken by the employee under due authority and in the course
of a duty, other than a flight in a commercial airline plane on a
scheduled flight;</li><li>travel was by privately-owned airplane, either as pilot or
passenger, assurance that no mileage allowance under the Travel
Regulations was paid or might, if claimed, be paid to any person
in respect of that flight;</li><li>a claim is being made under the Regulations, the applicant
(widow, widower or employee if disabled) must sign an election
claiming for benefits under the Regulations, and stating that it
is understood this will prohibit compensation under any other Act
or Regulation.</li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Reference</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This chapter replaces chapter 5-3 of PMM volume 16.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Enquiries on the benefits payable under the Flying
Accidents Compensation Regulations or the Government
Employees Compensation Act should be directed to the Canadian
Pension Commission and Labour Canada, respectively.</p><p>Enquiries concerning the processing and adjudication of claims
should be directed to:</p><p>The Canadian Pension Commission<br />
P.O. Box 9900<br />
Charlottetown, Prince Edward Island<br />
C1A 8V6</p><p>Enquiries on other than the above should be directed to:</p><p>Benefits Group<br />
General Personnel Policy Development and Compensation
Division<br />
Personnel Policy Branch<br />
Treasury Board Secretariat</p></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2017, <br/>ISBN: 978-0-660-09730-5</p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>