<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Public Service Income Benefit Plan for Survivors of Employees Slain on Duty" documentID="13583" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="s:\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Introduction">
      <p>The Public Service Income Benefit Plan for the survivors of employees slain on duty provides an income guarantee to the spouse and children of employees whose death was caused by an act of violence unlawfully committed by another person or persons, occurring in the course of or arising out of the performance by the employees of their duties.</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Administrative">
      <chapter anchor="2.1" title="Date of approval">
        <p>The provisions of the Public Service Income Benefit Plan for the survivors of employees slain on duty were approved by 
the Treasury Board on March 8, 1990 (TB 813362).</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="2.2" title="Provincial workers' compensation boards">
        <p>The appropriate provincial workers' compensation board will determine whether the death of employees is duty related.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="2.3" title="The administrator">
        <p>The plan is administered by Labour Program whose functions are to adjudicate that an employee was slain on duty, to apply 
the provisions of the Plan, to inform eligible survivors, and to provide monthly payments.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="2.4" title="Departments and agencies">
        <p>Departments and agencies are responsible for providing information to employees concerning this benefit; informing the 
Plan administrator that an employee has been slain on duty; and providing the necessary information required by the Plan 
administrator to adjudicate and administer the provisions of the plan.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="2.5" title="Treasury Board Secretariat">
        <p>The Treasury Board Secretariat is responsible for providing a general advisory service to departments, agencies, and 
Labour Program on the interpretation of the plan's provisions; issuing guidelines concerning contentious issues, monitoring 
the plan's application, and recommending applicable changes to the President of the Treasury Board.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="2.6" title="Public Service Management Insurance Plan Board of Trustees">
        <p>The Public Service Management Insurance Plan Board of Trustees will review claims filed on the request of a surviving spouses or child. It makes a recommendation to the Labour Program, the plan administrator, which reaches a decision in the matter.</p>
        <p>The Public Service Management Insurance Plan Board of Trustees cannot overrule decisions the Labour Program has made.</p>
      </chapter>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="General provisions">
      <chapter anchor="3.1" title="Benefits">
        <p>The Public Service Income Benefit Plan for the survivors of employees slain on duty supplements the income eligible survivors 
receive from various government sources, to guarantee an income level equal to the net salary or the net pension these employees 
would have received if alive.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="3.2" title="Costs">
        <p>The costs of the benefits are borne entirely by the federal government, and no direct contributions are made by employees.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="3.3" title="Tax status">
        <p>Income benefits for the survivors of employees slain on duty are not taxable.</p>
      </chapter>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Specific provisions">
      <chapter anchor="4.1" title="Coverage">
        <p>Employees covered under the Government Employees Compensation Act are covered under this plan, including part-time employees working less than one third the normal weekly hours, and term 
        employees appointed for a period of less than six months.</p>
        <p>Members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, Royal Canadian Mounted Police Reservists, members of the Canadian Armed Forces (Regular and Reserve Forces), and persons locally engaged outside Canada are not covered under this plan. </p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="4.2" title="Eligibility for income benefits">
        <p>The plan administrator adjudicates that employees were slain on duty. Continuing eligibility under this plan is based 
        on the survivors eligibility for compensation under the Government Employees Compensation Act (GECA). When an eligible spouse 
        ceases to receive compensation under the GECA, the terms and conditions of the Pension Act are applied to determine continuing 
        eligibility under the plan. Payments cease when these terms are not met.</p>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="4.3" title="Amount and apportionment of income benefits">
        <p>The specifics are outlined in appendix A, sections 1, 5, 6, and 7.</p>
      </chapter>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Reference">
      <p>This chapter replaces chapter 5-4 of PMM volume 16.</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Enquiries">
      <p>Enquiries concerning the reporting of employees who have been slain on duty and the administration of the plan should be directed to the Federal Workers’ Compensation Service, Labour Program:</p>
      <div class="mrgn-lft-md">
        <p>
          By email: 
          <a href="mailto:ESDC.FWCS.SEAMENINMATESPSIBPS7-RPRFPS7MARINSDETENUS.SFIAT.EDSC@labour-travail.gc.ca">ESDC.FWCS.SEAMENINMATESPSIBPS7-RPRFPS7MARINSDETENUS.SFIAT.EDSC@labour-travail.gc.ca</a>
        </p>
        <p>
          By mail:  
    Federal Workers’ Compensation Service
          <br/>
          
    165 Hôtel-de-Ville, Place du Portage, Phase II, 9th Floor
          <br/>
          
    Gatineau, Québec
          <br/>
           
    K1A 0J2
        </p>
        <p>By phone: Toll free number: 1-855-535-7299</p>
      </div>
      <p>Enquiries concerning the plan's provisions and their interpretation should be directed to:</p>
      <div class="mrgn-lft-md">
        <p>
          Benefits Group
          <br/>
          
        General Personnel Policy Development &amp; Compensation Division
          <br/>
          
        Personnel Policy Branch
          <br/>
          
        Treasury Board Secretariat
          <br/>
          
        Ottawa, Ontario
          <br/>
          
        K1A 0R5
        </p>
      </div>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A - Specific Provisions Regarding Income Benefits">
      <appendix anchor="A.1" title="Interpretation">
        <p>For the purposes of this plan, the following terms shall have the meanings hereinafter specified:</p>
        <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
          <li>
            employee (employé) means a person covered under the Government Employees Compensation Act; but excluding:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
              <li>members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police;</li>
              <li>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Reservists;</li>
              <li>members of the Canadian Armed Forces (Regular and Reserve Forces);</li>
              <li>a person locally engaged outside Canada;</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li>
            maximum age or length of service (âge de la retraite ou nombre maximum d'années de service) means age 65 or such earlier 
date as of which the employee:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
              <li>is at least age 55, and</li>
              <li>has completed 35 years of pensionable service for the purposes of the Public Service Superannuation Act;</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li>
            net pay (revenu net) means the pay of the employee less the total of the amounts which would be deductible from such 
pay, calculated as though the employee were alive, working and claiming, where and if applicable, normal exemptions for 
a spouse and any eligible children, for:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
              <li>contributions under the Public Service Superannuation Act, and the Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act;</li>
              <li>contributions under the Canada Pension Plan or the Quebec Pension Plan,</li>
              <li>contributions under the Employment Insurance Act (S.C. 1996, c. 23), and</li>
              <li>payment of income tax;</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li>net pension (pension nette) means the gross pension of the employee less the amount deductible from such pension for 
income tax purposes, which amount shall be calculated as though the employee were living and in receipt of the pension and, 
if applicable, claiming normal exemptions for a spouse and any eligible children;</li>
          <li>
            pay (revenu) means
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
              <li>at the time of death, the gross annual pensionable pay and pensionable allowances of the employee which are then in force, 
  and</li>
              <li>subsequently, the gross annual pensionable pay and pensionable allowances which would be payable to the employee, including, 
  from the date they become effective, pay increments or merit increases, general revisions, and revisions resulting from 
  an applicable classification conversion which the employee would have received if the employee were performing in a fully 
  satisfactory manner in the occupational group and level which is the equivalent for the position the employee held at 
  the time of death;</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li>pension (pension) means other than for the purposes of paragraph (l), the pension to which the employee would have 
been entitled under the Public Service Superannuation Act, Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act, and the Canada Pension 
Plan or the Quebec Pension Plan if the employee had continued to work until reaching maximum age or service at the group 
and level which the employee held at the time of death and at the rate of pay as defined for the purposes of this plan;</li>
          <li>Plan (régime) means the Public Service Income Benefit Plan for survivors of employees slain on duty;</li>
          <li>Plan administrator (administrateur du régime) means any person in Labour Program designated by the Minister of Labour 
Canada to apply the provisions of the Plan;</li>
          <li>slain on duty (tué dans l'exercice de ses fonctions) means the death of an employee which, in the opinion of the Plan 
administrator, was caused by an act of violence unlawfully committed by another person or persons, occurring in the course 
of or arising out of the performance by the employee of his or her duties;</li>
          <li>
            statutory entitlements (montants statutaires) means the gross amount of any survivor benefit paid by way of a pension, 
annuity, or allowance to or on behalf of the eligible survivors under any of the following:
                
            <ul>
              <li>The Public Service Superannuation Act;</li>
              <li>The Government Employees Compensation Act;</li>
              <li>Canada Pension Plan;</li>
              <li>The Quebec Pension Plan;</li>
              <li>The Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act; and</li>
              <li>a specific Treasury Board authority approving payments under the terms and conditions of the Pension Act in respect of Penitentiary Service and National Parole Service employees slain on duty prior to Treasury Board 1981 decision instituting the Penitentiary Service and National Parole Service Supplementary Income Benefit Plan for Survivors of Employees Slain on Duty. </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.1.1">Regardless of the employee's contributory or non-contributory status, the pensionable pay and pensionable allowances mentioned 
in Section 1(e) are those defined as salary under Part 1 of the Public Service Superannuation Act.</clause>
          <clause anchor="A.1.2">For better certainty, contractors, subcontractors, and any individual working for such persons shall be deemed not 
to be employees within the meaning of the terms of the plan.</clause>
          <clause anchor="A.1.3">The minister responsible for the plan is the President of the Treasury Board.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.2" title="Eligibility">
        <p>Subject to the conditions hereinafter specified, the surviving spouse or child of an employee slain on duty shall 
be eligible for benefits under the plan if and while pensions:</p>
        <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
          <li>are payable under the Government Employees Compensation Act or the Pension Act to or in respect of such spouse or child as the case may be, or</li>
          <li>would be payable under the Government Employees Compensation Act or the Pension Act to or in respect of such spouse or child as the case may be if the amounts payable under the plan were not being paid.</li>
        </ol>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.3" title="Spouse">
        <p>Spouse means an individual to whom the employee was married to at the time of death or with whom the employee was living in a common-law relationship at the time of death.</p>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.4" title="Cessation of eligibility">
        <p> If a person described in section 3 would cease to qualify for a pension under the Pension Act, if he or she were subject 
to that Act, that person shall immediately cease to be eligible for benefits under the plan.</p>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.5" title="Method for calculating certain statutory entitlements">
        <p>For the purposes of determining the amount of the monthly income benefit payable under section 6 or Section 7:</p>
        <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
          <li>A return of contributions under the Public Service Superannuation Act shall not be considered as income under the 
                    Plan.</li>
          <li>Severance pay shall not be considered as income under the plan.</li>
          <li>
            If a lump sum payment has been paid in lieu of a compensation pension under the Government Employees Compensation 
                    Act, it shall be determined as follows:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
              <li>The lump sum payment shall be deemed to have been received by the eligible surviving spouse or children in consecutive, 
  equal monthly installments.</li>
              <li>The rate of monthly installments shall be based on the monthly compensation pension rate previously paid; and 
  where none was paid, it shall be deemed to be the monthly compensation pension rate which would have been payable at the 
  time if that person was subject to the Pension Act.</li>
              <li>The deemed monthly installments shall commence the month following the month the payment of all or a portion 
  of the statutory entitlement ceased under the Government Employees Compensation Act.</li>
              <li>The deemed monthly installments shall cease when the aggregate of monthly installments is equal to the amount 
  of the lump sum payment.</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.6" title="Amount and apportionment of income benefits">
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.6.1">
            Where an employee is slain on duty, the eligible surviving spouse of the employee, subject to sections 6.2 and 6.3, 
shall be entitled to an income benefit, determined as follows:
                    
            <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
              <li>For each month, following the month in which the employee's death occurred, subject to Section 6.1(c), the eligible 
spouse shall be paid an income benefit under the plan in an amount equal to the amount by which the net pay of the employee 
for that month exceeds the total amount of the statutory entitlements payable to or in respect of the spouses and children 
of the employee in respect of that month.</li>
              <li>While the surviving spouse remains eligible for benefits under the plan, payment of the amount determined in paragraph (a) 
shall continue until the end of the month in which the employee would have reached maximum age or length of service.</li>
              <li>For each month, after the month in which the employee would have reached maximum age or length of service, an income 
benefit shall be paid to the eligible spouse, in an amount by which the net pension in respect of that month exceeds the 
total of any statutory entitlements payable to or in respect of the spouses and children of the employee in respect of that 
month.</li>
            </ol>
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.6.2">Where the survivors are two eligible spouses, the income benefit for each spouse, subject to Section 6.3, shall be 
apportioned in the same proportion as the total statutory entitlements which are payable to or in respect of each spouse 
and where applicable, the children domiciled with them, are to the total statutory entitlements referred to in Section 6.1(a) 
or 6.1(c) as the case may be.</clause>
          <clause anchor="A.6.3">Where the survivors are an eligible spouse, and an eligible child who is not domiciled with the eligible spouse, 
the income benefit for the eligible child shall be apportioned in the same proportion as the total statutory entitlements 
which are payable to or on behalf of this eligible child, are to the total statutory entitlements referred to in section 6.1(a) 
or 6.1(c) as the case may be.</clause>
          <clause anchor="A.6.4">Where the survivors are a spouse with a child or children and the spouse subsequently dies or otherwise ceases to 
be eligible, a payment to the eligible child or children shall be made under the provisions of section 7.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.7" title="Eligible children only">
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.7.1">
            Where there is no eligible spouse and the employee is survived by an eligible child or children, the child or children 
shall be entitled to an income benefit determined as follows:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
              <li>
                for each month, following the month in which the employee's death occurred, or in which the spouse died or ceased 
to be eligible;
                
                <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
                  <li>the child shall be paid an income benefit under the plan in an amount such that the total amount of statutory entitlements 
  and the income benefit payable hereunder in respect of that child for that month is equal to 50 percent of the net pay 
  of the employee in respect of that month;</li>
                  <li>where there is more than one eligible child, and subject to section 7.3(b) an income benefit shall be paid under 
  the plan in an amount by which the net pay of the employee in respect of that month exceeds the total amount of statutory 
  entitlements payable to or in respect of the children and in respect of that month, such amount being apportioned equally 
  amongst the eligible children.</li>
                </ol>
              </li>
            </ol>
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.7.2">For as long as the child or children remain eligible for an income benefit under the plan, payment of the amounts 
determined in section 7.1 shall continue until the end of the month in which the employee would have reached maximum age 
or length of service.</clause>
          <clause anchor="A.7.3">
            For each month, after the month in which the employee would have reached maximum age or length of service, an income 
benefit shall be paid to or in respect of the eligible child or children in an amount equal to:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
              <li>in the case of one child, an amount such that the total amount of statutory entitlements and the income benefit payable 
hereunder to or in respect of that child and in respect of that month is equal to 50 percent of the net pension of the employee 
in respect of that month; or</li>
              <li>where there is more than one child, the amount by which the net pension of the employee in respect of that month 
exceeds the total of statutory entitlements payable to or in respect of the children and in respect of that month, such 
amount being apportioned equally amongst the eligible children.</li>
            </ol>
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.7.4">Income benefits payable in respect of any child under the plan shall be paid to the person or agency to whom benefits 
are payable in respect of that child under the Government Employees Compensation Act or where that Act no longer applies, 
are payable under the Terms and Conditions of the Pension Act. Such recipient shall be accountable for the disposition of 
the income benefit in accordance with law.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.8" title="General">
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.8.1">In no case shall the income benefits payable under the plan be in an amount which would cause the total benefits 
payable, including statutory entitlements in respect of the survivors, to exceed the net pay or net pension, as the case 
may be, which the employee would have received.</clause>
          <clause anchor="A.8.2">The plan administrator shall ensure that overpayments are duly recovered.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.9" title="Assignment of payments">
        <p>Payments made under the plan are not assignable.</p>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.10" title="Workers' compensation">
        <p>Payments made under the plan are in the nature of worker's compensation.</p>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.11" title="Payments">
        <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
          <li>Benefits payable under the plan shall be paid monthly in arrears and shall continue until the end of the month 
                    during which the recipient dies or otherwise ceases to be eligible.</li>
          <li>Where monthly payments are twenty dollars or less, the frequency of payments will be on a quarterly, semi-annual, 
or annual basis; whichever is determined by the plan administrator to be the most administratively practicable.</li>
        </ol>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.12" title="Condition">
        <p>As a condition of the payment of benefits under the plan, an eligible spouse, or child, or children or other person 
being paid benefits on behalf of an eligible child or children shall provide or shall authorize the plan administrator to 
obtain such information as is required to properly administer the terms of the plan.</p>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.13" title="Complaint settlement">
        <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
          <li>
            A surviving spouse or child may request, in writing, a review of the plan administrator’s decisions for the following causes:
                
            <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
              <li>To review benefit calculations applicable to their claim.</li>
              <li>To review the application of plan provisions related to their claim.</li>
              <li>To review an eligibility decision made in respect of their claim.</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li>The Public Service Management Insurance Plan Board of Trustee on receipt of a request for a review shall, without delay and in a summary way: review the plan administrator decision and advise the Labour Program, the plan administrator, of their recommendation.</li>
          <li>The plan administrator considers the recommendation of the Public Service Management Insurance Plan Board of Trustees as well as the provisions of the plan and reaches a final decision in the matter.</li>
          <li>Under no circumstances may an administrative review result in a decision that would override legislation and policies of the Government of Canada or prevail over any other plan provision.</li>
        </ol>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
</doc>
