<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Policy on Transfer Payments" documentID="13525" versionID="9" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="1.1">
          This policy takes effect on October 1, 2008.
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="1.1.1">This version of the policy incorporates  updates effective April 1, 2022.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="1.2">
          Transitional considerations:
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="1.2.1">Terms and conditions of transfer payment programs that have been approved before the  effective date of this policy remain in effect until a) their expiry date or b) the date of a decision for continuation or amendment made under this policy, whichever is earlier; and </clause>
            <clause anchor="1.2.2">A funding  agreement entered into before the effective date of this policy remains in effect until its expiry date. However, it may be amended by the department with  the approval of the recipient to reflect the requirements of this policy.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="2.1">
          This policy is issued under subsection 7(1) 
          <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/f-11/">
            <em>Financial  Administration Act</em>
          </a>
          . 
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="Context">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="3.1">Transfer payments represent a large part of the Government of Canada’s  spending. The tangible results of transfer payments touch the lives of  Canadians and others every day in all sectors of society. Transfer payments  include grants, contributions and other transfer payments, including those made  to other orders of government, international organizations and Indigenous peoples.</clause>
        <clause anchor="3.2">Transfer payments are one of  the government’s key instruments in furthering its broad policy objectives and  priorities. Transfer payments enable and engage a wide diversity of skills and  resources outside the federal government.</clause>
        <clause anchor="3.3">Transfer payment programs assist eligible recipients in undertaking their  activities or projects. These activities and projects help achieve the  objectives and outcomes of the transfer payment program and contribute to  departmental results.</clause>
        <clause anchor="3.4">The  government is committed to ensuring that transfer payments are designed,  delivered and managed with integrity, accountability and transparency in a  recipient-focused manner. </clause>
        <clause anchor="3.5">Cabinet  determines when transfer payment programs are the most appropriate policy  instrument to use. Cabinet also determines the objectives and outcomes to be  achieved by transfer payments, within the legislative authorities provided by  Parliament. </clause>
        <clause anchor="3.6">This policy sets out clear  roles and responsibilities for the Treasury Board, the President of the  Treasury Board, the Secretary of the Treasury Board, ministers and deputy heads  in the design, delivery and management of transfer payment programs.</clause>
        <clause anchor="3.7">Additional mandatory  requirements are set out in the directives that deal with grants, contributions  and other transfer payments.</clause>
        <clause anchor="3.8">Treasury Board has delegated  authority to the President of the Treasury Board to issue, amend or rescind any  directive in support of this policy and to approve any exception to the  directives, as necessary.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Objectives and expected results">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="4.1">The  objective of this policy is to ensure that transfer payment programs are  designed and delivered to address government priorities in achieving results  for Canadians; are managed with integrity, transparency and accountability in a  manner that is sensitive to risks; and are citizen- and recipient-focused. </clause>
        <clause anchor="4.2">
          The  expected results of this policy are as follows:
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.2.1">Roles, responsibilities and accountabilities  for the management of transfer payment programs are clearly defined and  understood by all departments;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.2">Transfer payment programs are designed,  delivered and managed in a way that achieves outcomes, contributes to  departmental results, takes account of risk and clearly demonstrates value for  money; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.3">Transfer payment programs are supported by cost-effective  oversight and control systems at both departmental and government-wide levels;  and</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.4">
              Transfer payment programs are accessible,  understandable and useable by applicants and recipients, including the  following:
        
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="4.2.4.1">The administrative requirements on  applicants and recipients, which are required to ensure effective control,  transparency and accountability, are proportionate to the level of risks  specific to the program, the value of funding and the risk profile of  applicants and recipients;</clause>
                <clause anchor="4.2.4.2">Applicants and recipients are engaged in  support of innovation, continuous improvement, and the establishment of fair,  transparent and positive relations with them; and</clause>
                <clause anchor="4.2.4.3">Collaboration  exists within and among departments to harmonize transfer payment programs and  standardize their administration, when appropriate. </clause>
              </clauses>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Requirements">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="5.1">
          The 
          <strong>Treasury Board </strong>
          is  responsible for the following:
	
	
	
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Design</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.1.1">Approving the terms and conditions for new  transfer payment programs, except when a minister is authorized, including by  legislation, to establish those terms and conditions;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.1.2">Approving amendments to terms and conditions  for existing transfer payment programs, except when a minister is authorized  under this policy or by legislation to amend those terms and conditions;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.1.3">Approving funding  agreements when required by Treasury Board or by the directives supporting this  policy, or when recommended by the President of the Treasury Board; </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.1.4">Using periodic spending  reviews, such as resource alignment reviews, to review the continuation,  amendment or termination of transfer payment programs; and</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.1.5">Approving exceptions to  terms and conditions, except when a minister is authorized to approve those  exceptions under paragraphs 5.3.7 and 5.3.8 of this policy.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="5.2">
          The 
          <strong>President of the  Treasury Board</strong>
           is responsible for the following :	
	
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Design</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.2.1">Recommending to the  Treasury Board that a minister has to seek approval from the Treasury Board for  the continuation, amendment or termination of terms and conditions of an  existing transfer payment program;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.2.2">Recommending to the  Treasury Board that a minister has to seek approval from the Treasury Board for  a funding agreement; and</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.2.3">Recommending to the  Treasury Board that a minister has to seek approval from the Treasury Board for  an exception to the terms and conditions of an existing transfer payment  program.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="5.3">
          <strong>Ministers</strong>
           are  responsible for the following:
	
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Design</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.3.1">Approving the continuation or termination of  terms and conditions;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.2">Approving minor amendments of terms and  conditions;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.3">Delegating to the deputy head the approval of  minor amendments of terms and conditions, when appropriate;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.4">
                Approving amendments to the following  elements of terms and conditions:
	 
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.4.1">The eligible activities, initiatives or projects;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.4.2">The class of eligible recipients;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.4.3">The maximum amount payable to a recipient;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.4.4">The stacking limit; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.4.5">Amendments that give effect to a Cabinet  decision or direction;</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.5">Informing the President of the Treasury Board  when taking action under paragraph 5.3.4;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.6">
                Seeking approval from the Treasury Board for  amendments to the following elements of terms and conditions:
	 
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.6.1">The program objectives;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.6.2">The repayment of a repayable contribution;  and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.3.6.3">Up-front multi-year funding;</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.7">Approving, subject to  wording of appropriations, an exception to terms and conditions to provide a  transfer payment to an individual recipient of an amount up to 25 per cent in  excess of the maximum amount authorized by approved terms and conditions; </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.8">Approving, on a  case-by-case basis, an exception to terms and conditions that requires a  recipient to reimburse a repayable contribution when the funding provided is  less than $250,000; and </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.3.9">Setting the strategic direction for risk tolerance  for departmental transfer payment programs.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="5.4">
          <strong>Deputy heads</strong>
           are  responsible for the following:
		
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>General</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.4.1">Ensuring that  transfer payment programs are designed, delivered and managed so they are  accessible, understandable and useable by applicants and recipients; </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.2">Ensuring that  transfer payment programs are designed and delivered to be inclusive and  gender- and diversity-sensitive and respond to government policy objectives and  priorities;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.3">
                Ensuring, when  transfer payment programs support activities that benefit members of both  official language communities, that their design and delivery respect the  obligations of the Government of Canada as set out in Part VII of the 
                <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/">
                  <em>Official  Languages Act</em>
                </a>
                 and that services and benefits are made available in both  official languages in compliance with the 
                <em>Official Languages Act</em>
                ; 
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.4">Ensuring that departmental processes and procedures are in place to support the  design, delivery and management of transfer payments;</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Design</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.4.5">Ensuring that departmental transfer payment  programs are and remain relevant to and effective in meeting departmental results and government objectives;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.6">Engaging applicants and recipients, when appropriate, to achieve  this policy’s objective and expected results through innovative, cost-effective  transfer payment programs that are citizen- and recipient-focused; </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.7">
                 Recommending the continuation, amendment or termination of the terms and  conditions of a transfer payment program based on the findings of the following:
	  
	  
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="5.4.7.1">Relevant evaluations; and/or</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.4.7.2">Relevant resource alignment reviews;</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.8">Ensuring that each  transfer payment program is identified in one or more performance information  profiles when the program is designed, and that the program is maintained and  updated throughout its life cycle to effectively support the evaluation or  review of the relevance and effectiveness of each transfer payment program;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.9">Ensuring, when  appropriate, the harmonization of transfer payment programs within the  department, and ensuring collaboration with other departments; </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.10">Approving minor  amendments to terms and conditions when authorized to do so by the minister  pursuant to paragraph 5.3.3; </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.11">Consulting with the  Secretary of the Treasury Board when a minister proposes to take action under  paragraph 5.3.4; </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Delivery and management</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.4.12">
                Ensuring that the administrative  requirements on recipients and recipient reporting, monitoring and auditing in  particular, are proportionate to the risks specific to the following:
	  
	 
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="5.4.12.1">The transfer payment program;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.4.12.2">The value of funding in relation to  administrative costs; and </clause>
                  <clause anchor="5.4.12.3">The risk profile of applicants and  recipients;</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.13">Ensuring that opportunities are taken to  standardize the administration of transfer payment processes, procedures and  requirements within the department and with other departments, when  appropriate, in order to improve the administration of transfer payment  programs for applicants, recipients and the department;</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Transparency</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.4.14">Ensuring that any  exceptions under paragraphs 5.3.7 and 5.3.8 of this policy that have been  approved by the Treasury Board or the minister are posted on the departmental  website within 30 days of the approval date;</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Monitoring and oversight</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.4.15">
                Ensuring that  transfer payments are not made to a department defined in section 2 of the 
                <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">
                  <em>Financial  Administration Act</em>
                </a>
                , nor made to finance the ongoing operating or  capital requirements of a federal Crown corporation; 
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.16">Monitoring  compliance with this policy and its supporting directives through periodic  audits and other assessments to ensure the effective implementation of this  policy and its supporting directives; and</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.4.17">Investigating and  acting when any issues arise regarding policy compliance and ensuring that  appropriate remedial action is taken to address such issues within the  department.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="5.5">
          The 
          <strong>Secretary of the Treasury Board</strong>
           is responsible for the following:
	 
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Design</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.5.1">Recommending to the  President of the Treasury Board, as a result of consultations under paragraph  5.4.11 of this policy or otherwise, that a minister has to seek approval from  the Treasury Board, by or through the responsible minister, for the  continuation, amendment or termination of terms and conditions for a transfer  payment program;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.5.2">Recommending to the  President of the Treasury Board that a minister has to seek approval from the  Treasury Board for a funding agreement;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.5.3">Recommending to the  President of the Treasury Board that a minister has to seek approval from the  Treasury Board for exceptions to terms and conditions;</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Monitoring and oversight</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.5.4">Monitoring, providing guidance and recommending corrective actions regarding  compliance with this policy and its supporting instruments;</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Leadership</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="5.5.5">Providing leadership  and support in promoting and facilitating collaboration among departments for  government-wide harmonization of transfer payment programs, the standardization  of administrative processes, procedures and requirements, and the sharing of best  practices;</clause>
              <clause anchor="5.5.6">Providing leadership  for the development of the federal practitioner community involved in the  design, delivery and management of transfer payment programs; and </clause>
              <clause anchor="5.5.7">Establishing a  framework for the review of this policy and its supporting directives. </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Roles of other government  organizations">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="6.1">Not applicable.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="Application">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="7.1">
          This policy applies to departments  as defined in section 2 of the 
          <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">
            <em>Financial  Administration Act</em>
          </a>
          , unless excluded by specific acts, regulations or Orders in Council.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="Consequences of non-compliance">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="8.1">
          For an  outline of the consequences of non-compliance, refer to the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17151">
            <em>Framework for the Management of Compliance</em>
          </a>
          , Appendix C: Consequences for  Institutions, and Appendix D: Consequences for Individuals.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="9" title="References">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="9.1">
          <strong>Legislation</strong>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="9.1.1">
              <a href="http://lois-laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">
                <em>Financial Administration Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.2">
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/">
                <em>Official Languages Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.3">
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-17.2/">
                <em>Canada Gender Budgeting Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.4">
              <a href="https://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-0.6/">
                <em>Accessible Canada Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.5">
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-1/">
                <em>Access to Information Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.6">
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/">
                <em>Privacy Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.7">
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-36.65/">
                <em>Conflict of Interest  Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.1.8">
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/l-12.4/">
                <em>Lobbying Act</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="9.2">
          <strong>Related policy instruments</strong>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="9.2.1">
              <a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13616">
                <em>Foundation  Framework for Treasury Board Policies</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.2.2">
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495">
                <em>Policy on Financial Management</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.2.3">
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=31300">
                <em>Policy on Results</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.2.4">
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603">
                <em>Policy on Service and Digital</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.2.5">
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16484">
                <em>Policy on Internal  Audit</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.2.6">
              <a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17151">
                <em>Framework for the Management  of Compliance</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="9.3">
          <strong>Other government publications</strong>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="9.3.1">
              <a href="https://lobbycanada.gc.ca/en/rules/the-lobbyists-code-of-conduct/">
                <em>Lobbyists’ Code of Conduct</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.3.2">
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049">
                <em>Values  and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="9.3.3">
              <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/innovation/greening-government/strategy.html">
                <em>Greening  Government Strategy</em>
              </a>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="10" title="Enquiries">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="10.1">Members  of the public may contact Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries  regarding any questions about this policy.</clause>
        <clause anchor="10.2">Individuals from departments should contact their chief financial officer or  departmental transfer payment centre of expertise regarding any questions about  this policy.</clause>
        <clause anchor="10.3">
          The chief  financial officer or individuals from a departmental transfer payment centre of  expertise may contact 
          <a href="mailto:fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Financial Management  Enquiries</a>
           for interpretation of this policy.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A: Definitions">
      <p>For purposes of this policy and its supporting directives, the following definitions apply:	</p>
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            applicant (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>demandeur</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>An individual or entity that has  applied for a transfer payment.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            contribution (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>contribution</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A transfer payment subject to  performance conditions specified in a funding agreement. A contribution is to  be accounted for and is subject to audit.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            deputy head (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>administrateur général</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The deputy minister, the chief  executive officer or any other officer having this level of responsibility. However,  in respect of a departmental corporation, when the responsibility for making a  decision that this policy attributes to the deputy head lawfully remains with its Board of Directors or equivalent body or person, the term “deputy head” is to be read as standing for “Board of Directors or equivalent”.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            evaluation (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>évaluation</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          In the  Government of Canada, evaluation is the systematic collection and analysis of  information about the outcomes of transfer payment programs. The information is  used to make judgments about a transfer payment program’s relevance, results  and cost-effectiveness, and to find alternative ways to deliver the transfer  payment program or to achieve the same results. Section 42.1 of the 
          <a href="http://lois-laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">
            <em>Financial Administration Act</em>
          </a>
           requires that every department conduct a review every  five years of the relevance and effectiveness of each ongoing non-statutory  program of grants and contributions. This review is a form of evaluation that  would be conducted in a manner appropriate for the risk, complexity and  materiality of the program. 
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            funding agreement (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>entente  de financement</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A written agreement or  documentation constituting an agreement between the Government of Canada and an  applicant or a recipient setting out the obligations or understandings of both  with respect to one or more transfer payments.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            grant (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>subvention</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A transfer payment subject to  pre-established eligibility and other entitlement criteria. A grant is not  subject to being accounted for by a recipient nor normally subject to audit by  the department. The recipient may be required to report on results achieved.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            harmonization of transfer payment  programs (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>harmonisation des programmes de paiements de transfert</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The  alignment and/or integration of two or more transfer payment programs that  contribute to similar objectives. </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            Indigenous  people (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>peuples Autochtones</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          Has the meaning  assigned by the definition aboriginal  peoples of Canada in subsection 35(2) of the
          <em> </em>
          <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/">
            <em>Constitution Act, 1982</em>
          </a>
          .
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            international organization (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>organisme international</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Is an intergovernmental organization of which two or more states are members.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            minister (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>ministre</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          The highest lawful authority for  a department (minister, deputy head or governing body, e.g., Board of  Directors) with respect to a decision to be made under the policy. For  instance, in the case of a department listed under Schedule I of the 
          <a href="https://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">
            <em>Financial Administration Act</em>
          </a>
          ,  the minister is the actual minister, whereas in the case of some departmental  corporations (listed under Schedule II, e.g., the Canadian Polar Commission),  the minister may be its Board of Directors.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            minor amendments (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>modifications  mineures</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          Amendments to terms and  conditions of a transfer payment program:
  
          <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn">
            <li>
              other  than amendments to any of the elements listed below:
  
              <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
                <li>The program objectives</li>
                <li>The eligible activities, initiatives or projects</li>
                <li>The class of eligible recipients</li>
                <li>The maximum amount payable to a recipient</li>
                <li>The repayment of a repayable contribution</li>
                <li>The stacking limit</li>
                <li>Up-front  multi-year funding</li>
              </ol>
            </li>
            <li>that  are, in respect of any of the elements listed above, of a technical nature made  solely for the purpose of correcting errors of wording or adding clarity to  such element.</li>
          </ol>
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            other orders of government (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>autres ordres de gouvernement</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Are Canada’s provincial and territorial governments and provincial and territorial government entities.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            other  transfer payment (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>autre paiement de transfert</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A transfer  payment, other than a grant or contribution, based on legislation or other  arrangement, that may be determined by a formula. Examples of other transfer  payments are transfers to other orders of government, such as equalization  payments or Canada Health and Canada Social Transfer payments. </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            performance  information profile (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>profil de l’information  sur le rendement</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          The document that identifies the performance information for each “program” from the Program  Inventory. See also the definitions in the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=31300">
            <em>Policy on Results</em>
          </a>
          .
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            program (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>programme</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A group of related activities  that are designed and managed to meet a specific public need and are often  treated as a budgetary unit.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            recipient (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>bénéficiaire</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>An individual or entity that  either has been authorized to receive a transfer payment or that has received  that transfer payment.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            recipient‑focused (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>centré sur le bénéficiaire</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A focus on  creating a consistent experience for the recipient of a transfer payment, which  includes consulting with potential applicants and recipient communities, as  well as pursuing opportunities to harmonize and standardize transfer payment  programs. </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            responsible minister (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>ministre  responsable</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The minister who is required, for  the department, to sign submissions to the Treasury Board and Memoranda to Cabinet.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            resource alignment review (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>examen de l’alignement des ressources</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Cyclical or  targeted exercises that consider the alignment with priorities, resources, and  results of government programs in support of management excellence, good  expenditure prioritization and innovation.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            stacking  limit (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>limite sur le cumul de l’aide</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The maximum level of total  Canadian government funding authorized by the terms and conditions for a  transfer payment program for any one activity, initiative or project of a  recipient.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            standardization (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>uniformité</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The  establishment of common processes, systems or procedures for the delivery and  management of transfer payments. </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            terms and conditions (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>modalités</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          
	A document,  approved by the Treasury Board or a minister, that sets out the parameters  under which transfer payments may be made for a given program. In relation to  terms and conditions:
	
	
          <dl class="mrgn-tp-md mrgn-lft-lg">
            <dt>
              <strong>
                continuation (
                <span lang="fr">
                  <em>continuation</em>
                </span>
                )
              </strong>
            </dt>
            <dd>A decision to continue using  terms and conditions with or without minor amendments.</dd>
            <dt>
              <strong>
                amendment (
                <span lang="fr">
                  <em>modification</em>
                </span>
                )
              </strong>
            </dt>
            <dd>A decision to amend or modify  terms and conditions.</dd>
            <dt>
              <strong>
                termination (
                <span lang="fr">
                  <em>résiliation</em>
                </span>
                )
              </strong>
            </dt>
            <dd>A decision to terminate terms  and conditions so that no further funding agreements will be entered into for  that transfer payment program.</dd>
          </dl>
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            total  Canadian government funding (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>total de l’aide financière gouvernementale  canadienne</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The total funding available to a  recipient from federal, provincial, territorial and municipal governments for  any one activity, initiative or project of that recipient.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            transfer  payment (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>paiement de transfert</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A monetary payment, or a transfer  of goods, services or assets made, on the basis of an appropriation, to a third  party, including a Crown corporation, that does not result in the acquisition  by the Government of Canada of any goods, services or assets. Transfer payments  are categorized as grants, contributions and other transfer payments. Transfer  payments do not include investments, loans or loan guarantees.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            transfer  payment program (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>programme de paiements de transfert</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A program or a component of a  program supported by transfer payments.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            up-front multi-year funding (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>financement  pluriannuel initial</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Funding approved and payable to a  recipient to meet expenditures for more than one year when an appropriation for  the full amount has been obtained.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>
            value for money (
            <span lang="fr">
              <em>optimization  des resources</em>
            </span>
            )
          </strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>The extent  to which a transfer payment program demonstrates relevance and performance. Relevance is achieved by addressing a demonstrable need that is appropriate for  the federal government and is responsive to the needs of Canadians. Performance is achieved by using taxpayer resources well, producing transfer payment  program outputs affordably, and achieving outcomes consistent with transfer payment program objectives. </dd>
      </dl>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
</doc>
