<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Guideline on Common Financial Management Business Process 3.3 - Manage Other Payments</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=26954", title: "Guideline on Common Financial Management Business Process 3.3 - Manage Other Payments"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2010-05-30",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Guideline on Common Financial Management Business Process 3.3 - Manage Other Payments</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="chasummary">Executive Summary</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guideline is part of a set of guidelines designed to assist departments<sup><a href="#ftn1" id="ftnref1"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[1]</a></sup> in implementing common financial management business processes.</p><p>This guideline presents the “should be” model for Manage Other Payments, which involves those common<sup><a href="#ftn2" id="ftnref2"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[2]</a></sup> payment transactions not covered by Manage Interdepartmental Settlements (Business Process 2.2), Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1), Manage Travel (Business
    Process 3.2), Pay Administration (Business Process 5.1), and Manage Grants and Contributions (Business Process 6.1). This guideline describes roles, responsibilities and recommended procedures in the context of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA), other legislation, and Government of Canada policy instruments. Familiarity with Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1) is highly
    recommended prior to reading this business process. </p><p>The following categories of common payment transactions are covered in this guideline.</p><p><strong>Other operational payments</strong> result in charges against appropriations and include awards, honoraria, <em>ex gratia</em> payments, repayable loans, employee reimbursements, returns as described in section 20 of the FAA, accountable advances (excluding travel advances, which are covered in Manage Travel (Business Process 3.2)), and imprest funds. These payments do not use a
    purchase order to initiate a transaction and do not follow a formal procurement process.</p><p><strong>Legal payments</strong> also result in charges against appropriations and include settlements, claims against the Crown, and nugatory payments. These transactions are triggered by a court or a tribunal decision rather than by a program requirement. Because these transactions do not involve the acquisition of goods or services, there is no procurement process. A legal opinion and
    documentation, such as the copy of the court or tribunal decision, are required before the payment can be made.</p><p><strong>Payments not impacting appropriations</strong> are made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and include garnishments, other deductions, remittances of taxes collected, payments against imprest funds, repayment of contractor holdbacks, and some types of payments against specified purpose accounts.<sup><a href="#ftn3" id="ftnref3"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[3]</a></sup> Although these transactions do not result in charges against appropriations and there is no acquisition of goods or services, FAA certification and payment authority are still required.</p><p><strong>Periodic payments</strong> are recurring (usually monthly) payments resulting from a multi-year agreement established under Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1), starting with the second and subsequent payments of the agreement. These payments can be a fixed amount (for example, leases and rent) or usage-based (for example, telecommunications, utilities and taxis) and
    result in charges against appropriations. There is no need to identify the requirements or to obtain expenditure initiation authority. Some organizations may conduct a reallocation exercise, to ensure that the costs are properly attributed to responsibility centres.</p><p>As illustrated in Figure 1, Manage Other Payments comprises seven subprocesses (3.3.1 to 3.3.7). These are arranged in four subprocess groups, as follows.</p><p><strong>Manage Requirements</strong> is the start of the Manage Other Payments business process and involves the definition of requirements, prepared by an employee or the responsibility centre manager, and the determination and exercising of expenditure initiation authority. This subprocess group applies to other operational payments and legal payments.</p><p><strong>Control Commitments</strong> involves verifying the availability of a sufficient unencumbered balance and creating and updating commitments according to department-specific policy or procedures. Responsibility centre managers are accountable for monitoring commitments against their budget. Control Commitments connects to two subprocesses groups: Manage Requirements, to create the
    commitment; and Manage Payables, to ensure that sufficient unencumbered funds are available before proceeding with the payment, and to close the commitment once the final request for payment has been issued. This subprocess group applies to other operational payments, legal payments and periodic payments.</p><p><strong>Manage Payables</strong> involves handling invoices, claims, agreements, remittances or deduction requests; performing account verification; and providing certification authority pursuant to section 34 of the FAA. This subprocess group applies to all four categories of payments. Normally, the responsibility centre manager performs account verification and certification. However, for
    some non-pay employee-related payments, these activities may be performed by the compensation role and, for legal payments and payments not impacting appropriations, by financial services.</p><p><strong>Manage Payments</strong> ends the Manage Other Payments business process and involves performing quality assurance activities when applicable, exercising payment authority pursuant to section 33 of the FAA, completing and submitting payment requisitions, and finalizing payments. When quality assurance is performed, the process flow continues to Manage Financial Close (Business Process
    8.2). When quality assurance is not performed, the process flow continues to Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1). Financial services is responsible for managing payment requisitions, certifying payments pursuant to section 33 of the FAA, and recording payments. The Banking and Cash Management Sector of the Receiver General is responsible for issuing payments. This subprocess
    applies to all four categories of payments.</p><p>Because not all subprocesses apply to all categories of payments, the payment categories have different entry points to the Manage Other Payments business process, as illustrated in Figure 1. In addition, the order in which Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.1), Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) and Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4) are
    performed may differ from what is depicted in Figure 1, depending on department-specific policy or procedures.</p><div id="ldr1" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 1. Manage Other Payments – Level 2 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-01-eng.jpg" alt="Manage Other Payments – Level 2 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=1">Text version: Figure 1. Manage Other Payments – Level 2 Process Flow</a></p></div><p>Throughout the Manage Other Payments business process, the vendor master data file may need to be updated; the connection points to Manage Vendor Master Data File (Business Process 7.1) are provided in Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5).</p><p>From time to time, operational expenses are paid with petty cash. The use of petty cash as a payment method and the reconciliation of petty cash are described in <a href="#appE">Appendix E</a>.</p><p>The Level 2 process flow for payments covering the relocation of employees is unique and is described in <a href="#appF">Appendix F</a>.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Date of Issue</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guideline was issued on May 30, 2013.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Context</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guideline is part of a set of guidelines designed to assist departments<sup><a href="#ftn4" id="ftnref4"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[4]</a></sup> in implementing common financial management business processes. This guideline supports the <em>Policy on the Stewardship of Financial Management Systems</em> and the <em>Directive on the Stewardship of
    Financial Management Systems</em>.</p><p>This guideline presents the “should be” model for Manage Other Payments, describing roles, responsibilities and recommended activities from a financial management perspective. Most activities are financial in nature, but some non-financial activities are included in order to provide a comprehensive process description; these activities are identified as outside the scope of Manage
    Other Payments. The recommended activities comply with the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>, other legislation, and Government of Canada policy instruments.</p><p>Recognizing that deputy heads are ultimately responsible for all aspects of financial management systems within their department, standardizing and streamlining financial management system configurations, business processes and data across government provides significant direct and indirect benefits relative to the quality of financial management in the Government of Canada. By establishing a
    common set of rules, standardization reduces the multitude of different systems, business processes and data that undermine the quality and cost of decision-making information. As government-wide standardization increases, efficiency, integrity and interoperability are improved.<sup><a href="#ftn5" id="ftnref5"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[5]</a></sup></p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Introduction</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3_1">3.1 Scope</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>This guideline defines Manage Other Payments, which involves those common<sup><a href="#ftn6" id="ftnref6"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[6]</a></sup> payment transactions not covered by Manage Interdepartmental Settlements (Business Process 2.2), Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1), Manage Travel (Business Process 3.2), Pay Administration
        (Business Process 5.1), and Manage Grants and Contributions (Business Process 6.1).</p><p>The following categories of common payment transactions are covered in this guideline:</p><ul><li><strong>Other operational payments</strong> result in charges against appropriations and include awards, honoraria, <em>ex gratia</em> payments, repayable loans, employee reimbursements, returns as described in section 20 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA), accountable advances (excluding travel advances, which are covered in Manage
                Travel (Business Process 3.2)), and imprest funds. These payments do not use a purchase order to initiate a transaction and do not follow a formal procurement process.</li><li><strong>Legal payments</strong> also result in charges against appropriations and include settlements, claims against the Crown, and nugatory payments. These transactions are triggered by a court or a tribunal decision rather than by a program requirement. Because these transactions do not involve the acquisition of goods or services, there is no
                procurement process. A legal opinion and documentation, such as the copy of the court or tribunal decision, are required before the payment can be made.</li><li><strong>Payments not impacting appropriations</strong> are made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and include garnishments, other deductions, remittances of taxes collected, payments against imprest funds, repayment of contractor holdbacks, and some types of payments against specified purpose accounts.<sup><a href="#ftn7" id="ftnref7"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[7]</a></sup> Although these transactions do not result in charges against appropriations and there is no acquisition of goods or services, FAA certification and payment authority are still required.</li><li><strong>Periodic payments</strong> are recurring (usually monthly) payments resulting from a multi-year agreement established under Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1), starting with the second and subsequent payments of the agreement. These payments can be a fixed amount (for example, leases and rent) or usage-based (for example,
                telecommunications, utilities and taxis) and result in a reduction in appropriations. There is no need to identify the requirements or to obtain expenditure initiation authority. Some organizations may conduct a reallocation exercise, to ensure that the costs are properly attributed to responsibility centres.</li></ul><p>This guideline covers the following subprocess groups:</p><ul><li>Manage Requirements;</li><li>Control Commitments;</li><li>Manage Payables; and</li><li>Manage Payments.</li></ul><p>Some financial management activities described in this guideline are also related to internal controls. The intent is neither to provide a complete listing of controls, nor to produce a control framework; but the process description may provide useful content for the development of a department's control framework.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3_2">3.2 Structure of the Guideline</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The remainder of this guideline is structured as follows: Section 4 provides an overview of the roles that carry out Manage Other Payments. Section 5 presents a detailed description of the Manage Other Payments business process, including subprocess groups, subprocesses, activities and responsible roles. <a href="#appA">Appendix A</a> provides definitions of terminology used in the guideline, and relevant
        abbreviations are listed in <a href="#appB">Appendix B</a>. <a href="#appC">Appendix C</a> describes the methodology used in the guideline, and <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a> elaborates on the roles and responsibilities outlined in Section 4. The process flow for the use and reconciliation of petty cash is described in <a href="#appE">Appendix E</a>. Finally, the process flow for managing payments related to the relocation of employees is
        described in <a href="#appF">Appendix F</a>.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec3_3">3.3 References</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following references apply to this guideline.</p><h4>3.3.1 Acts and Regulations</h4><ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-5.5/"><em>Federal Accountability Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-98-130/"><em>Payments and Settlements Requisitioning Regulations, 1997</em></a></li></ul><h4>3.3.2 Policy Instruments</h4><ul><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15791"><em>Directive on Departmental Bank Accounts</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14220"><em>Directive on Executive Compensation</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15781"><em>Directive on Financial Management of Pay Administration</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17064"><em>Directive on Specified Purpose Accounts</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12407"><em>Directive on the Administration of Required Training</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19855"><em>Directive on the Management of Expenditures on Travel, Hospitality and Conferences</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17590"><em>Directive on the Stewardship of Financial Management Systems</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=3&amp;lang=eng"><em>Foreign Service Directives</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17067"><em>Guideline on Accountable Advances</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17068"><em>Guideline on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15258"><em>Policy on Internal Control</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12405"><em>Policy on Learning, Training and Development</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17589"><em>Policy on the Stewardship of Financial Management Systems</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12409"><em>Standards on Knowledge for Required Training</em></a></li></ul><h4>3.3.3 Other References</h4><ul><li><em><a href="/pubs_pol/hrpubs/TBM_113/iairp-prinefp-eng.asp">Addendum - Initial Appointees Relocation Program</a></em></li><li><a href="http://chrbp-pocrh.tbs-sct.gc.ca/process-eng.aspx"><em>Common Human Resources Business Process</em></a></li><li><a href="/hr-rh/gtla-vgcl/eggca-gdpngc/eggca-gdpngctb-eng.asp"><em>Executive Group (EX) and Governor In Council Appointees (GIC) - Relocation Provisions</em></a></li><li><a href="/maf-crg/index-eng.asp">Management Accountability Framework</a></li><li><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/txt/ccrg-rgcf-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Control Framework</em></a></li><li><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/manuels-manuals/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Manual</em></a></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Roles and Responsibilities</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Figure 2 depicts the roles involved in the Manage Other Payments business process, grouped by stakeholder category.</p><div id="ldr2" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 2. Roles involved in Manage Other Payments</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-02-eng.jpg" alt="Roles involved in Manage Other Payments" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=2">Text version: Figure 2. Roles involved in Manage Other Payments</a></p></div><p>In this guideline, a role is an individual or a group of individuals whose involvement in an activity is described using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted and Informed (RACI) approach. Because of differences among departments, a role may not correspond to a specific position, title or organizational unit. The roles and responsibilities for Manage Other Payments are briefly described in Sections 4.1 to 4.4 and are explained in more detail in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec4_1">4.1 Requirements Framework</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles act in support of legislation, such as the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA) and the <em>Federal Accountability Act</em>, and define policy or processes that must be followed.</p><ul><li>The <strong>Office of the Comptroller General</strong> is the policy authority for financial management and for the management of assets and acquired services.</li><li>The <strong>Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer</strong> is the policy authority for human resources management, but some functions are also performed by the Public Service Commission of Canada.</li><li>The <strong>deputy head</strong> is responsible for providing leadership by demonstrating financial responsibility, transparency, accountability and ethical conduct in financial and resource management. This includes compliance with legislation, regulations, Treasury Board policies and financial authorities.<sup><a href="#ftn8" id="ftnref8"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[8]</a></sup></li><li>The <strong>Receiver General – Accounting, Banking and Compensation Branch</strong> issues directives and guidance to federal departments on government accounting, payment and deposit.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec4_2">4.2 Financial Management</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles act in response to financial management policy and process requirements—for example, from the Office of the Comptroller General and from deputy heads.</p><ul><li>The <strong>corporate finance</strong> role supports the deputy head and the chief financial officer in meeting their financial management accountabilities by developing, communicating and maintaining the departmental financial management framework and by providing leadership and oversight on the proper application and monitoring of financial
                management across the department.<sup><a href="#ftn9" id="ftnref9"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[9]</a></sup></li><li>The <strong>strategic and corporate planning</strong> role coordinates input into the department-specific strategic, integrated, and operational planning processes defined within the department and in support of central agency requirements.</li><li>The <strong>financial services</strong> role carries out the day-to-day transactional financial management operations.</li><li>The <strong>responsibility centre manager</strong> role is responsible and accountable for exercising the following delegated authorities:
                <ul><li>Initiating expenditures;</li><li>Controlling commitments pursuant to section 32 of the FAA;</li><li>Entering into contracts, which is known as transaction authority—this authority is outside the scope of Manage Other Payments and is covered in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5d">Manage Contracts (Subprocess 3.1.5)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1); and</li><li>Performing account verification and certification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec4_3">4.3 Other Functional Roles</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles act in response to policy and process requirements from the Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer, deputy heads, and the Office of the Comptroller General. These roles are not financial in nature but are included in order to provide a comprehensive description.</p><ul><li>The <strong>compensation</strong> role receives requests for pay transactions, confirms that the employee is eligible for the payment, performs any required calculations, and enters the transaction into the Regional Pay System (RPS). This role also performs part of the FAA section 34 certification of pay transactions and for remittance of other
                payroll deductions.</li><li>The <strong>other human resources management functions</strong> role provides critical information (for example, classification decisions, identification of successful candidates in a staffing action, decisions on disciplinary actions, or identification of recipients and amounts for special awards) to responsibility centre managers, compensation and
                employees—information that can result in pay transactions. Note that this role does not administer pay transactions.</li><li>The <strong>asset and materiel management services</strong> role carries out the day-to-day transactional operations for the management of assets and acquired services and for the procurement of goods and services.</li><li>The <strong>employee</strong> role is performed by a federal government person, “who is any person currently paid a salary or remunerated from the Consolidated Revenue Fund.”<sup><a href="#ftn10" id="ftnref10"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[10]</a></sup> Employees can initiate or be the recipient of
                accountable advances and reimbursable expenses.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec4_4">4.4 Central Services</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles provide a central service to other government departments.</p><ul><li>The <strong>Receiver General – Banking and Cash Management Sector</strong> manages the treasury functions of the government, which includes issuing most payments on behalf of the government and controlling the government's bank accounts.</li><li>The <strong>legal services</strong> role is provided by the Department of Justice Canada to federal departments. The Department of Justice Canada is responsible for providing legal opinions and advice, including negotiation advice, and conducting litigation by or against the Crown and against its servants.<sup><a href="#ftn11" id="ftnref11"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[11]</a></sup> Legal services are consulted about payments such as garnishments, <em>ex gratia</em> payments, and claims against the Crown.</li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Process Flows and Descriptions</h2><div class="pol-content"><p><a href="#appC">Appendix C</a> describes the methodology used in this section.</p><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec5_1">5.1 Overview of Manage Other Payments</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>As illustrated in Figure 3, the Manage Other Payments business process comprises seven subprocesses (3.3.1 to 3.3.7). These are arranged in four subprocess groups:</p><ul><li>Manage Requirements;</li><li>Control Commitments;</li><li>Manage Payables; and</li><li>Manage Payments.  </li></ul><p>Because not all subprocesses apply to all categories of payments, the payment categories have different entry points to the Manage Other Payments business process, as illustrated in Figure 3. In addition, the order in which Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.1), Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) and Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4) are
        performed may differ from what is depicted in Figure 3, depending on department-specific policy or procedures.</p><div id="ldr3" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 3. Manage Other Payments – Level 2 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-03-eng.jpg" alt="Manage Other Payments – Level 2 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=3">Text version: Figure 3. Manage Other Payments – Level 2 Process Flow</a></p></div><p>The subprocesses within each subprocess group and the roles and responsibilities relevant to each subprocess are summarized below.</p><p><strong>Manage Requirements</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1):</strong> The responsibility centre manager or an employee identifies the requirements for an expenditure on the basis of the approved plan and budget or an ad hoc requirement, and prepares the justification. This subprocess applies to other operational payments.</li><li><strong>Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2):</strong> The responsibility centre manager ensures that he or she has been delegated the appropriate expenditure initiation authority and exercises the authority or obtains approval.<sup><a href="#ftn12" id="ftnref12"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[12]</a></sup> This subprocess
                applies to other operational payments and legal payments.</li></ul><p><strong>Control Commitments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3):</strong> The responsibility centre manager verifies that a sufficient unencumbered balance is available before proceeding with the payment. This subprocess applies to other operational payments, legal payments and periodic payments.</li><li><strong>Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4):</strong> After the availability of a sufficient unencumbered balance is confirmed, a commitment is created. Commitments are recorded and updated according to department-specific policy or procedures. This subprocess applies to other operational payments, legal payments and periodic payments.</li></ul><p><strong>Manage Payables</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5):</strong> Following receipt of the invoice, claim, agreement or remittance, account verification is performed pursuant to section 34 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA). Certification authority is exercised by the responsibility centre manager,<sup><a href="#ftn13" id="ftnref13"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[13]</a></sup> and a request for payment is prepared and sent to financial services. Account verification is performed by the responsibility centre manager, financial services or compensation, depending on the transaction. This subprocess applies to all four payment categories.</li></ul><p><strong>Manage Payments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6):</strong> Manage Payments starts with the receipt of a request for payment. During the payment process, quality assurance is performed by financial services as part of exercising payment authority pursuant to section 33 of the FAA. This subprocess applies to all four payment categories.</li><li><strong>Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7):</strong> The payment requisition is sent to the Receiver General for payment issuance. The payment requisition files are edited and validated, and the payments are released by the Receiver General. The Receiver General produces a generic return file containing unique payment references for control purposes.
                The payment records are updated in the departmental financial and materiel management system<sup><a href="#ftn14" id="ftnref14"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[14]</a></sup> by financial services, and the Manage Other Payments business process ends. When quality assurance is performed, the process flow continues to Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2).
                When quality assurance is not performed, the process flow continues to Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1). This subprocess applies to all four payment categories.</li></ul><p>Table 1 illustrates the relationship between the subprocesses and the four payment categories covered by this guideline.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 1. Manage Other Payments (Business Process 3.3) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="5"><p id="end1"><strong>Note A:</strong> For periodic payments, Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1) and Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) occur as part of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1).</p></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.1 Determine Requirements</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply<sup>(<a href="#end1"><span class="cn-invisible"> See table 1 </span><strong>Note A</strong></a>)</sup></td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.2 Determine and Exercise <strong>Expenditure Initiation Authority</strong></th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply<sup>(<a href="#end1"><span class="cn-invisible"> See table 1 </span><strong>Note A</strong></a>)</sup></td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.3 Verify Unencumbered Balance<br /><strong>(FAA, section 32)</strong></th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.4 Manage Commitments<br /><strong>(FAA, section 32)</strong></th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.5 Manage Payables<br /><strong>(FAA, section 34)</strong></th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.6 Perform Payment Authority<br /><strong>(FAA, section 33)</strong></th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">3.3.7 Issue Payment<br /><strong>(Receiver General)</strong></th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr></tbody></table></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec5_2">5.2 Manage Requirements Subprocess Group</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Manage Requirements is the start of the Manage Other Payments business process for other operational payments and legal payments, beginning with the approved plan and budget from Manage Planning and Budgeting (Business Process 1.1), an ad hoc requirement, or a copy of the court or tribunal decision. This subprocess group involves the definition of requirements, prepared by an employee or the
        responsibility centre manager, and the determination and exercising of expenditure initiation authority.</p><h4>5.2.1 Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1)</h4><p>As illustrated in Table 2, this subprocess applies to other operational payments.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table  2. Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments<sup><a href="#ftn15" id="ftnref15"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[15]</a></sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Determine Requirements</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Based on the approved plan and budget or an ad hoc requirement, the justification for the other operational payment is prepared by the responsibility centre manager or an employee. Figure 4 depicts the Level 3 subprocess flow for Determine Requirements.</p><div id="ldr4" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 4. Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-04-eng.jpg" alt="Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=4">Text version: Figure 4. Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><h5>5.2.1.1 Activities</h5><p>Consistent with the approved plan and budget from Manage Planning and Budgeting (Business Process 1.1) or an ad hoc requirement, the responsibility centre manager or an employee identifies a need and prepares the justification <strong>(Activity 3.3.1.1 – Identify Needs)</strong>. Other operational payments may be launched by a responsibility centre manager to disburse a monetary employee
        recognition award or a repayable loan established under an agreement. Alternatively, employees may submit a request to obtain an accountable advance or a reimbursement for expenses incurred—for example, for a professional development activity or for parking. Travel advances are outside the scope of this business process and are covered in Manage Travel (Business Process 3.2).</p><p>For some transactions, a consultation and a justification may be required when selecting a vendor <strong>(Activity 3.3.1.2 – Examine and Select Vendor)—</strong>for example, for employee reimbursements when the payee is the employee and the vendor is the third party selected by the employee. Although the payment is a reimbursement to an employee rather than to an external vendor,
        compliance with Treasury Board and departmental policies is still required.</p><p>The content of the justification varies with the type of transaction. The following are examples of the types of documentation required.</p><ul><li><strong>Accountable Advances:</strong>  Employees submit a request conforming to the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a><sup><a href="#ftn16" id="ftnref16"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[16]</a></sup> and other relevant policy instruments.</li><li><strong>Awards:</strong> A monetary award is supported by an awards plan and by a consultation with the other human resources management functions role, ensuring that the recognition is valid and appropriate.</li><li><strong>Reimbursements:</strong> For a reimbursement request related to training, learning or development, the supporting documentation should include an approved Personal Learning Plan. When the reimbursement is for hospitality, the request should be aligned with the annual budget and conform to the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19855"><em>Directive on
                the Management of Expenditures on Travel, Hospitality and Conferences</em></a>. </li><li><strong>Repayable Loans:</strong> The posting assignment notice supports the request for a posting loan under <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/fsd-dse-10/index-eng.php"><em>FSD-10 of the Foreign Service Directives</em></a><em>.</em> Other repayable loans, excluding repayable contributions, are triggered by a loan application received and
                approved by the program area. (Repayable contributions are covered in Manage Grants and Contributions (Business Process 6.1)). The approval of the loan occurs in the appropriate program area, whereas this business process focuses on the loan disbursement. The collection of the loan is covered in Manage Revenues, Receivables and Receipts (Business Process 2.1).</li></ul><h5>5.2.1.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>There are two potential scenarios for the activities of this subprocess. In the first scenario (S1), the employee initiates the transaction, as is the case with accountable advances and reimbursable expenses. In the second scenario (S2), the responsibility centre manager initiates the transaction. In both scenarios, the role initiating the transaction is responsible and accountable.</p><p>Table 3 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 3. Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>EE:</strong></dt><dd>employee</dd><dt><strong>HR:</strong></dt><dd>other human resources management functions</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd><dt><strong>SCP:</strong></dt><dd>strategic and corporate planning</dd></dl></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.1.1 Identify Needs</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Approved plan and budget
                            
                        </li><li>Estimated costs</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: EE</p><p>S2: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: EE</p><p>S2: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, HR, RCM, SCP</p><p>S2: CF, EE, HR, SCP</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.1.2 Examine and Select Vendor</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Dates required
                            
                        </li><li>Estimated costs</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: EE</p><p>S2: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: EE</p><p>S2: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, HR, RCM</p><p>S2: CF</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p></td></tr></tbody></table><h4>5.2.2 Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2)</h4><p>As illustrated in Table 4, this subprocess applies to other operational payments and legal payments.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table  4. Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Responsibility centre managers ensure that they have been delegated the appropriate expenditure initiation authority and exercise or obtain that authority.<sup><a href="#ftn17" id="ftnref17"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[17]</a></sup></p><p>For other operational payments, this subprocess continues from Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1). For legal payments, this subprocess represents the start of the Manage Other Payments business process and is launched when the department receives a copy of the court or tribunal decision. Figure 5 depicts the Level 3 process flow for Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation
        Authority.</p><div id="ldr5" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 5. Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-05-eng.jpg" alt="Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=5">Text version: Figure 5. Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><p>The level of expenditure initiation authority is based on the department's delegation of authorities, according to the delegation documents approved by the minister and the deputy head,<sup><a href="#ftn18" id="ftnref18"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[18]</a></sup> where expenditure initiation authority is defined as “the authority to incur an
        expenditure or to make an obligation to obtain goods or services that will result in the eventual expenditure of funds. This would include the decision…to order supplies or services.”<sup><a href="#ftn19" id="ftnref19"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[19]</a></sup> The creation and maintenance of the delegation of authority instruments is outside the scope of
        Manage Other Payments and is addressed in Manage Delegation of Financial and Spending Authorities (Business Process 7.4). Expenditure initiation authority is distinct from commitment authority, which “is the authority to carry out one or more specific functions related to the control of financial commitments.”<sup><a href="#ftn20" id="ftnref20"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[20]</a></sup> These authorities, together with transaction authority, make up spending authority. Transaction authority is outside the scope of this business process and is covered in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5d">Manage Contracts (Subprocess 3.1.5)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1).</p><h5>5.2.2.1 Activities</h5><p>The responsibility centre manager determines the appropriate expenditure initiation authority by consulting the delegation documents and Treasury Board policies <strong>(Activity 3.3.2.1 – Determine Required Expenditure Initiation Authority)</strong>. When the responsibility centre manager does not possess the required expenditure initiation authority (for example, for <em>ex gratia</em>
        payments or settlements) or when the responsibility centre manager directly or indirectly benefits from the expenditure,<sup><a href="#ftn21" id="ftnref21"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[21]</a></sup> he or she should obtain the signatures of those with delegated expenditure initiation authority <strong>(Activity 3.3.2.2 – Exercise Expenditure Initiation
        Authority or Obtain Approval)</strong>. Supporting documents, such as an agreement, an awards plan or a personal learning plan, are provided to the delegated authority.</p><p>In some situations, the authority to initiate other operational payments may not be obtained, in which case the requirements may be amended or the expenditure initiation process ends. However, departments must usually comply with a court or a tribunal decision, and therefore, expenditure initiation authority for legal payments must be obtained.</p><p>At the same time that expenditure initiation authority is being exercised, the availability of a sufficient unencumbered balance is determined<sup><a href="#ftn22" id="ftnref22"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[22]</a></sup> during Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3). If an unencumbered balance is available, a commitment conforming to
        department-specific policy or procedures is created during Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4).</p><p>The Manage Requirements subprocess group ends when:</p><ul><li>The requirement is defined or the notice to disburse funds for legal payments is received and approved by the appropriate expenditure initiation authority;</li><li>The unencumbered balance is confirmed during Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3); and</li><li>The commitment is recorded during Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4).<sup><a href="#ftn23" id="ftnref23"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[23]</a></sup></li></ul><p>The justification for expenditure initiation approval will vary with the type of transaction. The following are examples of the types of documentation required.</p><p><strong>Other Operational Payments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Accountable advances:</strong> Employees must complete a personal responsibility document, acknowledging responsibility for the advance.<sup><a href="#ftn24" id="ftnref24"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[24]</a></sup></li><li><strong><em>Ex gratia</em> payments:</strong> A legal opinion is required when signing off <em>ex gratia</em> payments<sup><a href="#ftn25" id="ftnref25"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[25]</a></sup><em>Ex gratia</em> payments are approved by the appropriate delegated authority.<sup><a href="#ftn26" id="ftnref26"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[26]</a></sup></li><li><strong>Repayable loans:</strong> Repayable loans are initiated in the program area where the loan agreement is completed. Approval in the form of a signed agreement is provided by the program manager with delegated authority.</li></ul><p><strong>Legal Payments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Settlements:</strong> The documentation could include a settlement or an agreement duly signed by the delegated authority, or a copy of the court or tribunal decision. A legal opinion may be required. The <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a> provides guidance on thresholds and
                requirements—for example, claims over $25,000 require a legal opinion.<sup><a href="#ftn27" id="ftnref27"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[27]</a></sup> Because of the sensitive nature of settlements, the associated data should be kept confidential.</li></ul><h5>5.2.2.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>There are two potential scenarios for Activity 3.3.2.1 – Determine Required Expenditure Initiation Authority. In the first scenario (S1), the employee initiates the transaction, as is the case with reimbursements. In the second scenario (S2), the responsibility centre manager initiates the transaction. In both scenarios, the role initiating the transaction is responsible and
        accountable.</p><p>For Activity 3.3.2.2 – Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority or Obtain Approval, the responsibility centre manager is accountable for obtaining expenditure initiation authorization.</p><p>Table 5 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 5. Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>EE:</strong></dt><dd>employee</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd></dl></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.2.1 Determine Required Expenditure Initiation Authority</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Delegation documents
                            
                        </li><li>Description and type of good or service; and</li><li>Estimated costs</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: EE</p><p>S2: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: EE</p><p>S2: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, RCM</p><p>S2: CF</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.2.2 Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority or Obtain Approval</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>Delegation documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">CF</td><td class="alignTopLeft">EE</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr></tbody></table></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec5_3">5.3 Control Commitments Subprocess Group</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The Control Commitments subprocess group involves verifying the availability of a sufficient unencumbered balance and creating and updating commitments according to department-specific policy or procedures. Control Commitments connects to two subprocess groups: Manage Requirements, to create the commitment; and Manage Payables, to ensure that sufficient unencumbered funds are available to
        proceed with the payment and to close the commitment once the request for payment has been issued.</p><h4>5.3.1 Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3)</h4><p>As illustrated in Table 6, this subprocess applies to other operational payments, legal payments and periodic payments.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table  6. Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Verify Unencumbered Balance</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr></tbody></table><p>The responsibility centre manager ensures that a sufficient unencumbered balance is available before proceeding with the payment .<sup><a href="#ftn28" id="ftnref28"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[28]</a></sup> Figure 6 depicts the Level 3 process flow for Verify Unencumbered Balance.</p><div id="ldr6" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 6. Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-06-eng.jpg" alt="Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=6">Text version: Figure 6. Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><p>The deputy head or other person charged with the administration of a program is responsible for establishing procedures to ensure that commitments are controlled and accounted for and that records pertaining to commitments are maintained.<sup><a href="#ftn29" id="ftnref29"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[29]</a></sup> In addition, departments should have processes in place to verify the availability
        of unencumbered balances at the time of expenditure initiation and prior to entering into a contract.<sup><a href="#ftn30" id="ftnref30"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[30]</a></sup> Commitment authority is delegated in writing to departmental officials by the deputy head.<sup><a href="#ftn31" id="ftnref31"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[31]</a></sup> The delegated official is responsible for ensuring that
        a sufficient unencumbered balance is available before entering into a contract or other arrangement.<sup><a href="#ftn32" id="ftnref32"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[32]</a></sup> The creation and the maintenance of the delegation documents are addressed in Manage Delegation of Financial and Spending Authorities (Business Process 7.4). Commitment control, which includes accounting for those
        commitments, is an ongoing activity throughout the Manage Other Payments business process.</p><h5>5.3.1.1 Activities</h5><p>Before proceeding with the payment, the responsibility centre manager initiating the expenditure ensures that a sufficient unencumbered balance is available by reviewing budget information, including a detailed analysis of outstanding or the previous year's commitments as well as unpaid invoices <strong>(Activity 3.3.3.1 – Determine Unencumbered Balance)</strong>. Ongoing payments, such
        as periodic payments, require that continuing commitments are kept separate for the current fiscal year and for each future year within the most recently approved budget.<sup><a href="#ftn33" id="ftnref33"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[33]</a></sup> The unencumbered balance is reviewed when account verification is performed or when the commitment requires an
        update (Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5)).</p><p>When a sufficient unencumbered balance is available, department-specific functions related to commitment authority are carried out <strong>(Activity 3.3.3.2 – Provide Authorization)</strong>. It is essential to ensure that appropriate evidence exists to substantiate the authorization pursuant to section 32 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>, as stipulated by department-specific
        policy and procedures.<sup><a href="#ftn34" id="ftnref34"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[34]</a></sup></p><p>When the unencumbered balance is insufficient, budgets are reviewed to identify alternative funding<sup><a href="#ftn35" id="ftnref35"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[35]</a></sup> or the Manage Other Payments business process ends. For legal payments, a budget reallocation is required, as described in Manage Forecasting and Budget Review (Business Process
        1.2).</p><p>Further details about this subprocess are provided below for the payment categories to which it applies.</p><p><strong>Other Operational Payments</strong></p><ul><li>There are no additional details.</li></ul><p><strong>Legal Payments</strong></p><ul><li>Given the obligatory nature of the disbursement, funds will need to be reallocated if they are not readily available.</li></ul><p><strong>Periodic Payments</strong></p><ul><li>Anticipated periodic payments must be reflected in the approved plan and budget.</li><li>Annually, the responsibility centre manager ensures that there are sufficient funds for upcoming periodic payments.</li><li>It may be difficult to determine the amount of usage-based invoices because of their ad hoc nature. Typically, the amount is based on estimated expenditures, and the commitment is adjusted as needed once the invoices are processed, during Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5).</li></ul><h5>5.3.1.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>The responsibility centre manager is accountable for his or her commitments.</p><p>Table 7 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 7. Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>EE:</strong></dt><dd>employee</dd><dt><strong>FIN:</strong></dt><dd>financial services</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd></dl><p id="end2"><strong>Note A:</strong> The individual exercising the delegated commitment authority may not be the same individual initiating the expenditure; the latter is therefore informed of the authorization decision.</p></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.3.1 Determine Unencumbered Balance</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Appropriation
                            
                        </li><li>Financial coding</li><li>Financial data (budget, commitments, actuals to date)</li><li>Payable amount</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.3.2 Provide Authorization</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Estimated payable
                            
                        </li><li>Financial coding</li><li>Specimen signature documents</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">CF</td><td class="alignTopLeft">
                        EE, RCM<sup>(<a href="#end2"><span class="cn-invisible"> See table 7 </span><strong>Note A</strong></a>)</sup></td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr></tbody></table><h4>5.3.2 Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4)</h4><p>While the unencumbered balance is being confirmed, the responsibility centre manager or financial services records or updates commitments according to department-specific policy or procedures. Once the unencumbered balance and the appropriate commitment control have been confirmed, section 32 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> has been exercised. Figure 7 depicts the Level 3 process
        flow for Manage Commitments. </p><div id="ldr7" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 7. Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-07-eng.jpg" alt="Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=7">Text version: Figure 7. Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><h5>5.3.2.1 Activities</h5><p>As illustrated in Table 8, this subprocess applies to other operational payments, legal payments and periodic payments.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table  6. Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Manage Commitments</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Does not apply</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr></tbody></table><p>The responsibility centre manager is accountable for ensuring that the commitment, including a continuing commitment that affects future fiscal years, is recorded according to department-specific policy or procedures. The commitment is recorded or updated by asset and materiel management services, financial services or the responsibility centre manager. Throughout the Manage Other Payments
        business process, the commitment is monitored and updated as needed—for example, when the estimated use or value changes <strong>(Activity 3.3.4.1 – Record or Update Commitments)</strong>.</p><p>Following receipt of the final invoice, the commitment is updated and closed out <strong>(Activity 3.3.4.2 – Close Out Commitments)</strong>. The end objective of Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2) and the Control Commitments subprocess group is to ensure that all commitments are managed and that responsibility centre managers do not exceed their
        allocated budgets or appropriations.<sup><a href="#ftn36" id="ftnref36"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[36]</a></sup></p><p>It may be impractical to record individual commitments for payments of low-dollar value. Departments can implement alternative means of accounting for these commitments, provided that their department-specific policy or procedures indicate when it is appropriate to do so and how these commitments are to be accounted for.<sup><a href="#ftn37" id="ftnref37"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[37]</a></sup> Commitments are recorded according to the department's approved budget and serve to quantify the financial implications of the planned requirements.</p><p>Further details about this subprocess are provided below for the payment categories to which it applies.</p><p><strong>Other Operational Payments</strong></p><ul><li>Commitments are recorded according to department-specific policies or procedures.</li></ul><p><strong>Legal Payments</strong></p><ul><li>Commitments are recorded according to department-specific policies or procedures.</li></ul><p><strong>Periodic Payments</strong></p><ul><li>For ongoing, multi-year agreements covering rent, utilities or telecommunications, commitments must be recorded annually.<sup><a href="#ftn38" id="ftnref38"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[38]</a></sup> Department-specific policies or procedures could identify financial services or asset and materiel management services as roles supporting the
                responsibility centre manager in updating the commitments.</li><li>Commitments are updated throughout the year.</li><li>When monitoring or updating an agreement, <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5d">Manage Contracts (Subprocess 3.1.5)</a> and <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5e">Administer Contracts and Deliverables (Subprocess 3.1.6)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1) are launched.</li><li>The department may choose to allocate centralized costs to different responsibility centres or sub-activities for usage-based invoices, either when the commitment is created or when the invoice is received during Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5), according to department-specific policy or procedures.</li></ul><h5>5.3.2.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>The responsibility centre manager is accountable for his or her commitments.</p><p>Table 9 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 9. Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>AMS:</strong></dt><dd>asset and materiel management services</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>FIN:</strong></dt><dd>financial services</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd></dl></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.4.1 Record or Update Commitments</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Commitment authorization
                            
                        </li><li>Estimated payable</li><li>Financial coding</li><li>Financial data (budget, commitments, actuals to date)</li><li>Invoice or claim data</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">AMS, FIN, RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft"> N/A</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.4.2 Close Out Commitments</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Commitment data
                            
                        </li><li>Financial data (budget, commitments, actuals to date)</li><li>Invoice or claim data</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">AMS, FIN, RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr></tbody></table></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec5_4">5.4 Manage Payables Subprocess Group</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>This subprocess group involves handling invoices, claims, agreements, remittances or deduction requests; completing the account verification; and providing certification authority pursuant to section 34 of the <em>Financial Administration</em> Act (FAA). This subprocess group is the starting point for payments not impacting appropriations, which are paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund
        (CRF). Typically the responsibility centre manager performs account verification and provides certification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA. However, for some non-pay employee-related payments, these activities may also be performed by the compensation role or, for legal payments and payments not impacting appropriations, by financial services.</p><h4>5.4.1 Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5)</h4><p>As illustrated in Table 10, this subprocess applies to all payment categories.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table  10. Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Manage Payables</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Upon receipt of invoices, claims, agreements, remittances or deduction requests and the required supporting documents, the following takes place:</p><ul><li>Account verification is performed;</li><li>Certification authority pursuant to section 34 of the FAA is exercised by the responsibility centre manager; and</li><li>A request for payment or settlement is prepared and sent to financial services.</li></ul><p>Figure 8 depicts the Level 3 process flow for Manage Payables.</p><div id="ldr8" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 8. Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-08-eng.jpg" alt="Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=8">Text version: Figure 8. Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><p>Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5) involves receiving, verifying and validating invoices, claims, agreements, remittances or deduction requests and other supporting documents. The agreements and any documents supporting the receipt of goods or the provision of services form part of the account verification process.</p><p>Manage Payables begins when the invoices, claims, agreements, remittances or deduction requests are received by the program area or by financial services. At this time, the date of receipt is recorded; the date of receipt is a key element in calculating interest, which is further described in Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6).</p><p>Account verification provides the necessary evidence to demonstrate that:</p><ul><li>The work has been performed;</li><li>The goods have been supplied or the services have been rendered;</li><li>The relevant agreement terms and conditions have been met;</li><li>The transaction is accurate; and</li><li>All authorities have been complied with.<sup><a href="#ftn39" id="ftnref39"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[39]</a></sup></li></ul><p>Primary responsibility for verifying individual accounts rests with the responsibility centre manager, who has the authority to confirm and certify entitlement pursuant to section 34 of the FAA.<sup><a href="#ftn40" id="ftnref40"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[40]</a></sup> All payments and settlements must be certified pursuant to section 34 of the FAA. Note
        that all payments made out of the CRF are governed by section 26 of the FAA, which states that “no payments shall be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund without the authority of Parliament.”<sup><a href="#ftn41" id="ftnref41"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[41]</a></sup></p><p>To ensure adequate separation of duties, the following functions are kept separate when responsibility is assigned to individuals involved in the expenditures process:<sup><a href="#ftn42" id="ftnref42"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[42]</a></sup>     </p><ul><li>Authority to enter into a contract (transaction authority): This activity is outside the scope of the Manage Other Payments business process and is performed during <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5d">Manage Contracts (Subprocess 3.1.5)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1);</li><li>Certification of the receipt of goods and the provision of services pursuant to section 34 of the FAA (certification authority): These activities are outside the scope of the Manage Other payments business process and are performed during <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5e">Administer Contracts and Deliverables
                (Subprocess 3.1.6)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1);</li><li>Determination of entitlement, verification of accounts, and preparation of requisitions for payment or settlement, pursuant to section 34 of the FAA (certification authority): These activities are performed during Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5); and</li><li>Certification of requisition for payment or settlement, pursuant to section 33 of the FAA (payment authority): This activity is conducted during Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6).</li></ul><p>If the process or other circumstances do not allow such separation of duties, alternative control measures are implemented and documented.</p><p>Furthermore, Section 6.2.2 of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a> requires that persons with delegated authority do not exercise:</p><ul><li>Certification authority and payment authority on the same payment; and</li><li>Spending, certification or payment authority for an expenditure from which they can directly or indirectly benefit—for example, when the payee is the individual with financial signing authority or when the expenditure is incurred for the benefit of that individual.<sup><a href="#ftn43" id="ftnref43"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[43]</a></sup></li></ul><p>Although account verification is normally performed prior to payment, completing account verification following payment is permitted in certain situations, such as acquisition card purchases, provided that the claim for payment is reasonable and meets the criteria outlined in the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Account
        Verification</em></a><em>.</em><sup><a href="#ftn44" id="ftnref44"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[44]</a></sup></p><h5>5.4.1.1 Activities</h5><p>The Manage Payables subprocess involves the following activities<sup><a href="#ftn45" id="ftnref45"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[45]</a></sup> that support verification and certification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA:</p><ul><li>Verifying that the following are complete:
                <ul><li>The supporting documents provide an audit trail and demonstrate the agreed price and other specifications, the receipt of goods or the provision of services, and authorization according to the delegation of signing authorities; and</li><li>The original document (for example, claim, legal document, invoice or advance payment form) requesting that a payment be made is complete <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.1 – Verify That Documentation Is Complete)</strong>;</li></ul></li><li>Confirming that:
                <ul><li>The terms and conditions of the contract or agreement have been met, including price, quantity and quality;</li><li>Work has been performed;</li><li>Goods have been supplied, services have been rendered, or evidence that a liability exists has been provided; and</li><li>The price is reasonable when, because of exceptional circumstances, the price is not specified in the contract or the agreement <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.3 – Confirm That Requirements Are Met)</strong>;</li></ul></li><li>Confirming that the payee is entitled to, or eligible for, the payment. This confirmation includes verifying that the payee is appropriate, particularly for an assignment of the supplier's debt or for an alternate payee <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.4 – Confirm That Payee Is Eligible for Payment)</strong>;</li><li>Ensuring the reasonableness of the amount or price by validating with supporting documents. This validation may include a three-way match <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.5 – Ensure That Amount or Price Is Reasonable)</strong>;</li><li>Ensuring that the payee information is accurate and valid <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.6 – Ensure That Payee Information Is Accurate)</strong>. The payee information should also be verified against the vendor master data file. If the payee information is not accurate and changes are required, Manage Vendor Master Data File (Business Process
                7.1) explains how to make changes to the vendor master data file;</li><li>Verifying that the financial coding is accurate and complete <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.7 – Verify That Financial Coding Is Correct)</strong>;</li><li>Verifying that all relevant statutes, regulations, Orders in Council, policies and directives, and other legal obligations have been complied with <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.8 – Verify That Relevant Regulations Were Followed)</strong>. In addition to the policies identified in Section 3.3,
                “References,” there may be other policy instruments specific to the transaction that should be consulted; and</li><li>Verifying that the transaction is accurate, including that the payment is not a duplicate; that discounts, credits or contract holdbacks have been deducted; that charges not payable have been removed; and that the invoice or the claim total has been calculated correctly<strong>(Activity 3.3.5.10 – Verify the Accuracy of
                Transaction)</strong>.</li></ul><p>The following activities also occur when certifying certain types of other payments:</p><ul><li>Obtaining a legal opinion or ensuring that it has been obtained, when required for settlements, <em>ex gratia</em> payments, and certain types of garnishments or claims against the Crown <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.2 – Obtain Legal Opinion)</strong>. The Department of Justice Canada is responsible for the administration of garnishment
                summonses for family support and other obligations debts against public servants' salaries, in accordance with the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</em></a>. Summonses are served directly to the Department of Justice Canada, which validates and forwards these documents to departments for immediate action;<sup><a href="#ftn46" id="ftnref46"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[46]</a></sup></li><li>Ensuring that the commitment balance is sufficient to proceed with the payment for other operational, legal and periodic payments <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.9 – Verify That Balance is Sufficient)</strong>. If the commitment balance is insufficient, the process flow returns to the Control Commitments subprocess group, to determine whether
                sufficient unencumbered funds are available (Verify Unencumbered Balance (Subprocess 3.3.3)) and to update the commitment as needed (Manage Commitments (Subprocess 3.3.4));</li><li>Ensuring that the liability account balance is sufficient before proceeding with payments not impacting appropriations. If the balance is insufficient, then either the account balance or the payment amount is corrected;</li><li>Ensuring that the responsibility centre manager follows the departmental procedures for determining and validating whether a payment to an employee is taxable for the purposes of the T4 Statement of Remuneration Paid; the T4A Statement of Pension, Retirement, Annuity, and Other Income; or equivalent, as well as notifying the compensation role
                of the determination, as required; and</li><li>Ensuring that the responsibility centre manager follows the departmental procedures for other tax slips specific to periodic and other operational payments—for example, the T1204 Government Service Contract Payments form or equivalent.</li></ul><p>Departments must ensure that suppliers are paid by the due date. Departments that fail to pay by the due date<sup><a href="#ftn47" id="ftnref47"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[47]</a></sup> must pay interest, without demand from the supplier, in accordance with the payment terms specified in the agreement. The <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive
            on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a> does not allow a department to elect a minimum threshold for payment of interest. Certain payments, such as periodic payments, are paid according to a fee schedule or according to the terms of an agreement.<sup><a href="#ftn48" id="ftnref48"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[48]</a></sup> In addition, payments to
        employees are to be paid as soon as possible.<sup><a href="#ftn49" id="ftnref49"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[49]</a></sup> Information on determining the due date is available in the “Payment on Due Date” section of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>.</p><p>The account verification activity performed for periodic payments (for example, rental agreements for shared equipment or taxi invoices) may include a reallocation exercise to attribute the costs to responsibility centres. The reallocation exercise should be based on an appropriate allocation strategy, using actual cost, average cost, or prorated costs by percentage. In these cases, the
        account verification process may be performed centrally or may be decentralized, and certification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA  may be obtained through the participation of various individuals in different responsibility centres, or of different levels in the organizational hierarchy.</p><p>If, at any time during the account verification process, a discrepancy is identified or if the information is incomplete, the responsibility centre manager resolves the discrepancy by tracing the issue to its source <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.11 – Resolve Discrepancies)</strong>. Once the issue is resolved, the account verification resumes or starts over.</p><p>Once the supporting documents have been verified and any discrepancies have been resolved, the account verification is complete and certification authority is exercised pursuant to section 34 of the FAA <strong>(Activity 3.3.5.12 – Exercise Authority or Obtain Approval)</strong>. Certification is usually provided through a signature block on the documentation or a completed account
        verification checklist. The final output of the Manage Payables subprocess is an approved request for payment.</p><p>Account verification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA ensures that there is auditable evidence of verification—that is, the individuals who performed the account verification are identified and there is an audit trail.</p><p>The following are examples of the types of documentation required for the four payment categories when verifying or exercising certification authority:</p><p><strong>Other operational payments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Accountable advances:</strong> An approved request for an accountable advance.</li><li><strong>Awards:</strong> The awards plan and the justification for recognition.</li><li><strong><em>Ex gratia</em> payments:</strong> An agreement and a legal opinion.</li><li><strong>Honoraria:</strong> The approved agreement.</li><li><strong>Reimbursements:</strong> The claim for a reimbursement, including evidence of research and the justification for the selected vendor as well as evidence of the receipt of deliverables, if applicable.</li><li><strong>Repayable loans:</strong> The approved loan agreement.</li></ul><p><strong>Legal payments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Grievances and recourse:</strong> A claim.</li><li><strong>Other settlements:</strong> A copy of the court or tribunal decision for legal payments and other obligations resulting from a legal decision.</li></ul><p><strong>Payments not impacting appropriations</strong></p><ul><li>A remittance, for provincial sales taxes; a deduction request, for voluntary payments; or a garnishee summons. For holdbacks, the responsibility centre manager certifies that the conditions for releasing holdbacks have been met. Information on deduction payments, specifically garnishments, often includes sensitive data that should kept
                confidential. </li></ul><p><strong>Periodic Payments</strong></p><ul><li>Invoices from vendors—for example utility, telecommunication and taxi companies. When the payment is a fixed amount (for example, rent or a lease—a payment schedule outlining the payments for the year should be available; and</li><li>Documentation supporting the receipt of goods or services—for example, signed taxi chit carbons or logs tracking usage.</li></ul><h5>5.4.1.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>There are three scenarios depending on the roles responsible and accountable for the completion of the account verification and the certification of documents, pursuant to section 34 of the FAA:</p><ul><li>In the first scenario (S1), compensation performs account verification for non-pay employee payments, such as garnishments or other deductions.</li><li>In the second scenario (S2), financial services performs account verification for legal payments and payments not impacting appropriations, such as remittances of taxes collected.</li><li>In the third scenario (S3), the responsibility centre manager performs account verification.</li></ul><p>Table 11 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 11. Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>COMP:</strong></dt><dd>compensation</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>EE:</strong></dt><dd>employee</dd><dt><strong>FIN:</strong></dt><dd>financial services</dd><dt><strong>HR:</strong></dt><dd>other human resources management functions</dd><dt><strong>LS:</strong></dt><dd>legal services</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd></dl><p><a href="#endref3" id="end3"><span class="cn-invisible">Return to Table 11 </span><strong>Note A</strong></a>: The authoritative source for most policy instruments is outside the DFMS.</p></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.1 Verify That Documentation Is Complete</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, HR, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, HR, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, EE, FIN, HR</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: FIN, RCM</p><p>S2. RCM</p><p>S3: FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.2 Obtain Legal Opinion</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Legal opinion
                            
                        </li><li>Policy instruments</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, LS, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, LS, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN, LS</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: N/A</p><p>S2: N/A</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.3 Confirm That Requirements Are Met</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Legal opinion (if applicable)
                            
                        </li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, HR, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, HR, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, HR, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.4 Confirm That Payee Is Eligible for Payment</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Alternate payee data (if required)
                            
                        </li><li>Payee data</li><li>Supporting documents</li><li>Vendor data</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, HR, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, HR, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN, HR</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.5 Ensure That Amount or Price Is Reasonable</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, HR, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, HR, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, HR, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.6 Ensure That Payee Information Is Accurate</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Payee data
                            
                        </li><li>Supporting documents</li><li>Vendor data</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.7 Verify That Financial Coding Is Correct</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Chart of accounts
                            
                        </li><li>Cost allocation formula</li><li>Financial coding</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.8 Verify That Relevant Regulations Were Followed</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Evidence of FAA, section 34 certification
                            
                        </li><li>Legal opinion</li><li>Policy instruments<sup>(<a href="#end3" id="endref3"><span class="cn-invisible"> See table 11 </span><strong>Note A</strong></a>)</sup></li><li>Supporting documents </li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, HR, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, HR, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN, HR</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.9 Verify That Balance Is Sufficient</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Financial coding
                            
                        </li><li>Liability account or commitment balance</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.10 Verify the Accuracy of Transaction</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Financial coding
                            
                        </li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.11 Resolve Discrepancies</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Credit memo data (if applicable)
                            
                        </li><li>Payee data</li><li>Supporting documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, EE, FIN, HR</p><p>S2: CF, EE, HR</p><p>S3: CF, EE, FIN, HR</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: FIN</p><p>S2: N/A</p><p>S3: FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.5.12 Exercise Authority or Obtain Approval</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Certification authority
                            
                        </li><li>Delegation documents</li><li>Evidence of expenditure initiation authority (if applicable)</li><li>Evidence of transaction authority (if applicable)</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: COMP</p><p>S2: FIN</p><p>S3: RCM</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: CF, FIN, RCM</p><p>S2: CF, RCM</p><p>S3: CF, FIN</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: RCM</p><p>S2: RCM</p><p>S3: N/A</p></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><p>S1: DFMS</p><p>S2: DFMS</p><p>S3: DFMS</p></td></tr></tbody></table></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="sec5_5">5.5 Manage Payments Subprocess Group</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The Manage Payments subprocess group completes the Manage Other Payments business process and involves performing quality assurance activities when applicable, exercising payment authorization pursuant to section 33 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA), completing and submitting payment requisitions, and finalizing payments. </p><p>In some cases, reimbursements can be disbursed through petty cash; this is further described in <a href="#appE">Appendix E</a>. In other cases, an acquisition card may be used; acquisition card statements are processed as part of the alternate process flow for acquisition cards, as described in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#appE">Appendix E</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process
        3.1).</p><h4>5.5.1 Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6)</h4><p>As illustrated in Table 12, this subprocess applies to all payment categories.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 12. Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Perform Payment Authority</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Perform Payment Authority starts with the receipt of a request for payment. Quality assurance is performed by financial services as part of payment authorization pursuant to section 33 of the FAA. Figure 9 depicts the Level 3 process flow for Perform Payment Authority.</p><div id="ldr9" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 9. Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-09-eng.jpg" alt="Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=9">Text version: Figure 9. Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><h4>5.5.1.1 Activities</h4><p>The request for payment issuance is received by financial services <strong>(Activity 3.3.6.1 – Receive Request for Payment)</strong>. The request for payment includes the justification; claim or invoice data; payment details (date invoice received, deliverables acceptance date, due date and amount payable); payee data; payment type (regular or priority payment); and financial coding
        block.</p><p>As part of this subprocess, the financial officer delegated payment authority pursuant to section 33 of the FAA performs quality assurance <strong>(Activity 3.3.6.2 – Perform Quality Assurance)</strong>. The financial officer exercises payment authority and is responsible for certifying and ensuring that:<sup><a href="#ftn50" id="ftnref50"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[50]</a></sup></p><ul><li>There is auditable evidence demonstrating that account verification has taken place and has been certified by an individual with delegated financial signing authority, pursuant to section 34 of the FAA;</li><li>No payment is made when the payment:
                <ul><li>Is not a lawful charge against the appropriation;</li><li>Will result in an expenditure exceeding the appropriation; or</li><li>Will result in an insufficient balance in the appropriation to meet the commitments charged against it;</li></ul></li><li>When exercising payment authority:
                <ul><li>All high-risk transactions are subjected to a full review; and</li><li>A sample of medium- and low-risk transactions is selected, using a sample selection methodology, and the most important aspects of each transaction are reviewed; and</li></ul></li><li>Certification of payments pursuant to section 33 of the FAA is provided to the Receiver General (Standard Payment System).<sup><a href="#ftn51" id="ftnref51"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[51]</a></sup></li></ul><p>If a discrepancy is identified during this process, for example a duplicate payment, the payment request is returned to the responsibility centre manager for resolution.</p><p>The department is responsible for defining high, medium and low risks based on its risk tolerance. Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1) describes the process of applying the quality assurance requirements of section 33 of the FAA after the payment has been made, which includes the sampling of medium- and low-risk transactions. The financial officer is responsible for
        requesting corrective action when a critical error is identified during the quality assurance process for payment authority.<sup><a href="#ftn52" id="ftnref52"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[52]</a></sup></p><p>The next activity is to determine whether interest is due on the invoice and to calculate interest as appropriate, in accordance with the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>, using the Bank of Canada interest rate in effect for the previous month plus 3 per cent<sup><a href="#ftn53" id="ftnref53"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[53]</a></sup><strong>(Activity 3.3.6.3 – Calculate Interest)</strong>.</p><p>When calculating interest on late payment of an invoice, the date to be used is the latest of the following:</p><ol class="lower-alpha"><li>The original invoice receipt date;</li><li>The supplier's invoice date (to be used as the default if (a) is not captured);</li><li>The deliverables acceptance date; or</li><li>The shipment date (to be used as the default if (c) is not captured).  </li></ol><p>Under the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a><em>,</em> if parts of an invoice are in dispute, the parts that are not in dispute are to be paid within the due date period.<sup><a href="#ftn54" id="ftnref54"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[54]</a></sup> Departmental invoice business processes
        should have the capacity to split supplier invoices into disputed items and non-disputed items, and to have adequate duplicate payment controls that can identify true duplicate payments versus multiple payments on the same supplier invoice.</p><p>To ensure adequate separation of duties, the following functions are kept separate when responsibility is assigned to individuals involved in the expenditures process:<sup><a href="#ftn55" id="ftnref55"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[55]</a></sup></p><ul><li>Authority to enter into a contract (transaction authority): This activity is outside the scope of the Manage Other Payments business process and is performed during <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5d">Manage Contracts (Subprocess 3.1.5)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1);</li><li>Certification of the receipt of goods and the provision of services pursuant to section 34 of the FAA (certification authority): These activities are outside the scope of  the Manage Other Payments business process and are performed during <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=24970&amp;section=text#sec5e">Administer Contracts and Deliverables
                (Subprocess 3.1.6)</a> of Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1);</li><li>Determination of entitlement, verification of accounts, and preparation of requisitions for payment or settlement pursuant to section 34 of the FAA (certification authority): These activities are performed during Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5); and</li><li>Certification of requisition for payment or settlement pursuant to section 33 of the FAA (payment authority): This activity is conducted during Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6).</li></ul><p>If the process or other circumstances do not allow such separation of duties, alternative control measures are implemented and documented.</p><p>Furthermore, Section 6.2.2 of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a> requires that persons with delegated authority do not exercise:</p><ul><li>Certification authority and payment authority on the same payment; and</li><li>Spending, certification or payment authority for an expenditure from which they can directly or indirectly benefit—for example, when the payee is the individual with financial signing authority or when the expenditure is incurred for the benefit of that individual.<sup><a href="#ftn56" id="ftnref56"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[56]</a></sup></li></ul><p>When the financial officer is satisfied that all requirements have been met, the payment requisition is certified pursuant to section 33 of the FAA and electronic authorization and authentication (EAA) is performed <strong>(Activity 3.3.6.4 – Exercise Authority Pursuant to FAA, section 33 (Includes EAA))</strong>.</p><p>The payment requisition is then prepared and submitted to the Receiver General <strong>(Activity 3.3.6.5 – Submit Payment Requisition to Receiver General)</strong> in accordance with the:</p><ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-98-130/index.html"><em>Payments and Settlements Requisitioning Regulations, 1997</em></a>;</li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>; and</li><li><em>Receiver General Manual</em>, Chapter 4 – “Standard Payment System and Departments.” </li></ul><p>The requisitions within the payment file contain full payment details: name, date, amount, delivery address, financial institution routing information, stub detail (if required), and the type of payment. Departments assign a unique requisition number to each batch of payments.<sup><a href="#ftn57" id="ftnref57"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[57]</a></sup></p><p>The <a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Control Framework</em></a> and the <a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/manuels-manuals/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Manual</em></a> provide additional details and steps for ensuring that the payment requisition is properly submitted to the Receiver General. Authorized
        requisitions can be paid using various types of payments. When selecting the type of payment, there are many characteristics to consider.<sup><a href="#ftn58" id="ftnref58"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[58]</a></sup></p><p>Table 13 provides the relevant references as well as key characteristics of the most common types of payments.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 13. Common Types of Payments</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Type of payment</th><th scope="col">Receiver General Control Framework</th><th scope="col">Characteristics</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">Regular payment</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#a7-2">Section 7.2</a></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>Payment file should contain full payment details</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">Priority payment</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#a7-8">Section 7.8</a></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Priority payment indicator
                            
                        </li><li>Time-sensitive deadline</li><li>Pre-registration of payee information</li><li>Advance notice of payment due date</li><li>Adequate internal controls over cheques</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">Direct deposit</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#a7-2">Section 7.2</a></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Payment coding
                            
                        </li><li>Correct banking information</li><li>Recognized vendor</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">Large value transaction system</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#a7-7">Section 7.7</a></td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Pre-registration of payee information
                            
                        </li><li>Advance notice of payment 48 hours before due date</li><li>Due diligence for every payment</li></ul></td></tr></tbody></table><p>Further details about this subprocess are provided below for the payment categories to which it applies:</p><p><strong>Other Operational Payments</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Accountable advances:</strong> Reimbursements made through petty cash and the reconciliation of petty cash are described in <a href="#appE">Appendix E</a>.</li><li><strong>Reimbursements:</strong> Because reimbursements for hospitality are often considered high-risk transactions, quality assurance is performed as part of the certification process pursuant to section 33 of the FAA.</li></ul><p><strong>Legal Payments</strong></p><ul><li>When exercising certification pursuant to section 33 of the FAA, the financial officer ensures that appropriate documentation is obtained from subject-matter experts in compensation or legal services.</li><li>Because legal payments are often considered as high-risk transactions, quality assurance is performed as part of the certification process pursuant to section 33 of the FAA.</li></ul><p><strong>Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</strong></p><ul><li>Because these payments are often certified pursuant to section 34 of the FAA by financial services or corporate finance, the individual who exercises certification pursuant to section 33 of the FAA cannot the same person who exercises certification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA.<sup><a href="#ftn59" id="ftnref59"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[59]</a></sup></li><li>Information on deduction payments, specifically garnishments, often includes sensitive data that should be kept confidential.</li></ul><p><strong>Periodic Payments</strong></p><ul><li>For this payment category, the subprocess is conducted in the same way as Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1).</li></ul><h5>5.5.1.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>Financial services is responsible and accountable for managing payment requisitions and certifying payments pursuant to section 33 of the FAA.</p><p>Table 14 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 14. Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>COMP:</strong></dt><dd>compensation</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>FIN:</strong></dt><dd>financial services</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd><dt><strong>RG-BCM:</strong></dt><dd>Receiver General – Banking and Cash Management Sector</dd></dl></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.6.1 Receive Request for Payment</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Claim or invoice data
                            
                        </li><li>Payee data</li><li>Payment details</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">COMP, RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.6.2 Perform Quality Assurance</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Agreement data
                            
                        </li><li>Claim or invoice data</li><li>Legal opinion (if applicable)</li><li>Delegation document</li><li>Evidence of provision of spending authority</li><li>Payee data</li><li>Payment details</li><li>Policy instruments</li><li>Quality assurance results</li><li>Risk level</li><li>Section 34 of the FAA verification and certification</li><li>Specimen signature documents</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">CF, COMP, RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.6.3 Calculate Interest</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Bank of Canada interest rate
                            
                        </li><li>Claim or invoice data</li><li>Date deliverables received (if applicable)</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">CF</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.6.4 Exercise Authority Pursuant to FAA, section 33 (Includes EAA)</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Appropriation balance
                            
                        </li><li>Approved payment requisition</li><li>Delegation documents</li><li>Liability account balance</li><li>Quality assurance results (if applicable)</li><li>Section 33 certification (signature)</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">CF</td><td class="alignTopLeft">N/A</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.6.5 Submit Payment Requisition to Receiver General</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Electronic authorization and authentication details (FAA, section 33 )
                            
                        </li><li>Payee data</li><li>Payment details</li><li>Payment requisition file</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft"> N/A</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-BCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">DFMS</td></tr></tbody></table><h4>5.5.2 Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7)</h4><p>As illustrated in Table 15, this subprocess applies to all payment categories.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 15. Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7) – Applicability by Payment Category</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subprocess</th><th scope="col">Other Operational Payments</th><th scope="col">Legal Payments</th><th scope="col">Payments Not Impacting Appropriations</th><th scope="col">Periodic Payments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row" class="lightgreyBG alignTopLeft fontSizeNormal">Issue Payment</th><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td><td class="alignTopLeft">Applies</td></tr></tbody></table><p>After payment authorization pursuant to section 33 of the FAA is exercised, the payment requisition is sent to the Receiver General for payment issuance. The payment requisition files are edited and validated, and the payments are released by the Receiver General. The Receiver General produces a generic return file containing unique payment references for control purposes. At this time, the
        payment records should be updated<sup><a href="#ftn60" id="ftnref60"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[60]</a></sup> in the departmental financial and materiel management system. Manage Other Payments (Business Process 3.3) ends, and Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1) or Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2) begins.</p><p>In the unlikely event that an overpayment or a duplicate payment is issued and cashed by the vendor, two options should be considered: obtaining a credit memo to be applied to future invoices within the current fiscal year (section 29.1 of the FAA<sup><a href="#ftn61" id="ftnref61"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[61]</a></sup>) or obtaining a refund from the
        vendor. The credit memo should be processed as described in Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1). The refund should be processed as a receipt, as described in Manage Revenue, Receivables and Receipts (Business Process 2.1).</p><p>Figure 10 depicts the Level 3 process flow for Issue Payment.</p><div id="ldr10" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 10. Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7) – Level 3 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-10-eng.jpg" alt="Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7) – Level 3 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=10">Text version: Figure 10. Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7) – Level 3 Process Flow</a></p></div><h5>5.5.2.1 Activities</h5><p>Public Works and Government Services Canada uses the Standard Payment System (SPS) to issue Receiver General payments in Canadian and foreign currencies <strong>(Activity 3.3.7.1 – Issue Payment)</strong> and to process interdepartmental settlements (IS); the latter is addressed in Manage Interdepartmental Settlements (Business Process 2.2). All program, accounts payable and compensation
        payments are issued by the Receiver General on behalf of federal departments and are drawn from the Consolidated Revenue Fund.<sup><a href="#ftn62" id="ftnref62"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[62]</a></sup> The SPS is an integrated system, with various components and menus that incorporate the entire payment and document process.<sup><a href="#ftn63" id="ftnref63"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[63]</a></sup></p><p>The following summarizes the SPS payment processing steps.<sup><a href="#ftn64" id="ftnref64"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[64]</a></sup></p><p><strong>Edit and Verification:</strong> On receipt of the requisition and payment details, the SPS confirms the authenticity of the electronic signature on the requisition and then edits the input to ensure that the requisition and payment details match and show no signs of tampering.</p><p><strong>Assignment of Payment Reference Numbers:</strong> Each edited payment is assigned a 12-digit payment reference number (PRN) prior to loading into the SPS database. Each PRN is linked to the SPS requisition number assigned by the department.</p><p><strong>Notification to Departments:</strong> Departments receive notification by return file that their payments have been edited and loaded into the SPS. Departments record the payment details (PRN, payment date, etc.) in their own departmental financial management system for control and future reference purposes.</p><p><strong>Online Enquiry and Updates:</strong> Returned payments are recorded in the SPS. Departments are responsible for handling returned payments and may request the cancellation or the issuance of duplicate payments through the SPS. The SPS allows enquiries at all points of the payment life cycle.</p><p>Post-payment processing, including cheque replacement and exceptions, is part of Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2).</p><p>Departments receive notification by return file that their payments have been released by the SPS. Departments process the return payment file <strong>(Activity 3.3.7.2 – Process Return Payment File)</strong> and subsequently finalize and record the payment details (PRN, payment date, etc.) in their departmental financial management system <strong>(Activity 3.3.7.3 – Finalize
        Payment)</strong>. Manage Other Payments (Business Process 3.3) ends, and Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1) or Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2) begins, depending on whether quality assurance is performed.</p><p>Departments are required to regularly reconcile the payment requisitions submitted to the SPS with the payment return or notification file sent by the SPS. Departments are also required to regularly reconcile the control account balances in the departmental financial and materiel management system with the control account totals received daily from the Receiver General – General Ledger
        (RG-GL), based on control data received from the SPS. Control account balance reconciliation is part of Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2).</p><p>At this point in the process, all payments are treated the same by the Receiver General; there are no differences between the payment categories.</p><h5>5.5.2.2 Roles and Responsibilities</h5><p>Financial services are responsible for recording completed payments, and the Banking and Cash Management Sector of the Receiver General is responsible for issuing payments.</p><p>Table 16 provides an overview of roles and responsibilities, using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted, and Informed (RACI) approach. These roles and responsibilities are further described in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 16. Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7) – RACI</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="7"><p><strong>Legend</strong></p><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>COMP:</strong></dt><dd>compensation</dd><dt><strong>DFMS:</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>EE:</strong></dt><dd>employee</dd><dt><strong>FIN:</strong></dt><dd>financial services</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd><dt><strong>RG-BCM:</strong></dt><dd>Receiver General – Banking and Cash Management Sector</dd><dt><strong>RG-SPS:</strong></dt><dd>Receiver General – Standard Payment System</dd></dl></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.7.1 Issue Payment</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Payment details
                            
                        </li><li>Payment return file</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">BCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-BCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-SPS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.7.2 Process Return Payment File</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Payment return file
                            
                        </li><li>Payment Reference Number</li><li>Requisition number</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-BCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft"> N/A</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-SPS</td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft">3.3.7.3 Finalize Payment</td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li>
                            Payment details
                            
                        </li><li>Payment return file</li><li>Payment Reference Number</li><li>Requisition number</li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">FIN</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-BCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">EE, RCM</td><td class="alignTopLeft">RG-SPS</td></tr></tbody></table></div></section></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix A: Definitions</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>The following definitions apply to this guideline and reflect common definitions used in Treasury Board policies, standards, directives, guides and tools.</p><dl><dt><strong>Accountable – RACI:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of the RACI tables, the role that can attest to the truth of the information or a decision and that is accountable for the completion of the activity. There must be exactly one role accountable for each activity.</p></dd><dt><strong>Accountable advance:</strong></dt><dd><p>Accountable advances are: (a) A sum of money advanced to a person from an appropriation; or (b) A sum of money advanced to a person from the sum of money described in paragraph (a) for which the person is accountable and includes imprest funds and working capital advances administered under an imprest system.<sup><a href="#ftn65" id="ftnref65"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[65]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Activity:</strong></dt><dd><p>An elaboration on a subprocess appearing in a Level 3 business process flow. <em>See also</em> Process; Subprocess<em>.</em></p></dd><dt><strong>Authoritative source – RACI:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of the RACI tables, a system that holds the official version of the information generated by the activity or a decision resulting from the activity. The authoritative source can be automated or manual.</p></dd><dt><strong>Awards:</strong></dt><dd><p>Employee recognition through monetary awards. Monetary awards do not include performance pay, gifts and other non-monetary awards such as gift cards.</p></dd><dt><strong>Certification authority:</strong></dt><dd><p>The authority, pursuant to section 34 of the <em>Financial Administration Act,</em> to certify, before payment, contract performance and price, entitlement or eligibility for the payment.<sup><a href="#ftn66" id="ftnref66"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[66]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Commitment accounting:</strong></dt><dd><p>The recording of obligations to make future payments at the time they are planned and before the time that services are rendered and billings are received. Such obligations may represent contractual liabilities, as is the case when purchase orders or contracts for goods or services are issued. Commitments are recorded individually. When it is impractical
        to formally record commitments individually (e.g., low-value transactions), the organization's procedures will be designated to identify these instances and describe how they will be accounted for.<sup><a href="#ftn67" id="ftnref67"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[67]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Commitment authority:</strong></dt><dd><p>The authority that carries out one or more specific functions related to the control of financial commitments as required by the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>.<sup><a href="#ftn68" id="ftnref68"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[68]</a></sup> Commitment authority is delegated in
        writing to departmental officials by the deputy head (or equivalent) for ensuring that there is a sufficient unencumbered balance available before entering into a contract or other arrangement. Note that subsection 32(2) of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> applies.</p></dd><dt><strong>Commitment control:</strong></dt><dd><p>Consists of established procedures that prevent an organization from entering into a contract or any other arrangement that provides for a payment unless there is enough money available in that year's appropriation to discharge the debt that is incurred during that fiscal year.<sup><a href="#ftn69" id="ftnref69"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[69]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Consulted – RACI:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of the RACI tables, a role that is required to provide accurate information or a decision for an activity to be completed. There may or may not be a consulted role, and consultation may or may not be mandatory. When consultation does occur, there is typically a two-way communication between those consulted and the responsible party.</p></dd><dt><strong>Contracted Relocation Service Provider:</strong></dt><dd><p>A private sector company contracted by the federal government to administer the relocation services for employees in accordance with the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>.<sup><a href="#ftn70" id="ftnref70"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[70]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Custodian:</strong></dt><dd><p>The person to whom an accountable advance has been issued or who is responsible for an accountable advance such as petty cash.<sup><a href="#ftn71" id="ftnref71"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[71]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Department financial and materiel management system (DFMS):</strong></dt><dd><p>Is a financial management system (FMS) whose primary objectives are to demonstrate compliance by the government with the financial authorities granted by Parliament, comply with the government's accounting policies, inform the public through departmental financial statements, provide financial and materiel information
        for management and control, provide information for economic analysis and policy formulation, meet central agency reporting requirements and provide a basis for audit.<sup><a href="#ftn72" id="ftnref72"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[72]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>(Employee) Relocation:</strong></dt><dd><p>The authorized move of an employee from one place of duty to another or the authorized move of an employee from the employee's place of residence to the employee's first place of duty upon appointment to a position in the public service.<sup><a href="#ftn73" id="ftnref73"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[73]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Expenditure initiation authority:</strong></dt><dd><p>The authority to incur an expenditure or to make an obligation to obtain goods or services that will result in the eventual expenditure of funds. This includes the decision to hire staff; to order supplies or services; to authorize travel, relocation or hospitality; or to enter into some other arrangement for program purposes.<sup><a href="#ftn74" id="ftnref74"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[74]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Financial authorities:</strong></dt><dd><p>Consist of certification authority and payment authority.</p></dd><dt><strong>Financial management system (FMS):</strong></dt><dd><p>Is any combination of business processes (end-to-end, automated and manual), procedures, controls, data and software applications, all of which are categorized as either a departmental financial and materiel management system (DFMS) or program system or central system that produces financial information and related non-financial
        information.</p><p>Financial management systems are used for any of the following:</p><ul><li>Collecting, processing, maintaining, transmitting and reporting data about financial events and to maintain accountability for the related assets, liabilities and equity;</li><li>Supporting financial management, planning, budgeting and decision-making activities;</li><li>Accumulating and reporting cost information; or</li><li>Supporting the preparation of internal and external reports, such as departmental financial statements and input to the Public Accounts of Canada.<sup><a href="#ftn75" id="ftnref75"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[75]</a></sup></li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Hospitality:</strong></dt><dd><p>Consists of the provision of meals, beverages or refreshments to non-federal government persons at events which are necessary for the effective conduct of government business for courtesy, diplomacy or protocol purposes. In some circumstances, hospitality can also be provided to federal government persons. <sup><a href="#ftn76" id="ftnref76"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[76]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Informed – RACI:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of the RACI tables, a role that is notified of the information or a decision after the decision is made or the activity is completed. There may or may not be an informed role, and informing the role may or may not be mandatory. There is typically a one-way communication from the responsible (or accountable) party to those informed.</p></dd><dt><strong>Legal payments:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of this guideline, payments that result in charges against appropriations—for example, settlements, claims against the Crown, and nugatory payments. These transactions are triggered by a court or a tribunal decision rather than by a program requirement. Because these transactions do not involve the acquisition of goods or services, there is
        no procurement process. A legal opinion and documentation, such as the copy of the court or tribunal decision, are required before the payment can be made.</p></dd><dt><strong>Legal responsibility:</strong></dt><dd><p>Includes responsibilities and authorities flowing from legislation, other instruments such as Orders in Council, regulations, international agreements, policies, directives or standards and, where applicable, delegated authorities related to the management of finance, human resources and procurement and those related to any other instrument identified by
        the employer.<sup><a href="#ftn77" id="ftnref77"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[77]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Level 1:</strong></dt><dd><p>A graphical representation of the Government of Canada financial management business process that applies to all functional domains and cross-functional areas.</p></dd><dt><strong>Level 2:</strong></dt><dd><p>A one-page business process flow describing all or part of a functional domain. This process description is aimed at the executive level.</p></dd><dt><strong>Level 3:</strong></dt><dd><p>A business process flow that provides more detail to a Level 2 subprocess through the identification of activities, while remaining common to all federal departments and system-independent.</p></dd><dt><strong>Other operational payments:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of this guideline, payments that result in charges against appropriations—for example, awards, honoraria, <em>ex gratia</em> payments, repayable loans, employee reimbursements, refunds as described in section 20 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>, payments and accountable advances (excluding travel advances, which are
        covered in Manage Travel (Business Process 3.2)), and imprest funds. These payments do not use a purchase order to initiate a transaction and do not follow a formal procurement process.</p></dd><dt><strong>Payments not impacting appropriations:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of this guideline, payments made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund—for example, garnishments, other deductions, remittances of taxes collected, payments against imprest funds, repayment of contractor holdbacks, and some types of payments against specified purpose accounts. Although these transactions do not result
        in charges against appropriations and there is no acquisition of goods or services, certification and payment authority pursuant to the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> are still required.</p></dd><dt><strong>Periodic payments:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of this guideline, recurring (usually monthly) payments resulting from a multi-year agreement established under Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1), starting with the second and subsequent payments of the agreement. These payments can be a fixed amount (for example, leases and rent) or usage-based (for example, telecommunications,
        utilities and taxis) and result charges against appropriations. There is no need to identify the requirements or to obtain expenditure initiation authority. Some organizations may conduct a reallocation exercise, to ensure that the costs are properly attributed to responsibility centres.</p></dd><dt><strong>Process:</strong></dt><dd><p>A function fully described by a Level 2 business process flow and elaborated at Level 2 through the definition of subprocesses. <em>See also</em> Activity; Subprocess</p></dd><dt><strong>RACI analysis:</strong></dt><dd><p>An analysis that describes the roles and responsibilities of various teams or individuals in delivering or contributing to an activity. The RACI approach divides tasks into four participatory responsibility types (Responsible, Accountable, Consulted and Informed), which are then assigned to different roles in the process.</p></dd><dt><strong>Record of commitments:</strong></dt><dd><p>The deputy head or other person charged with the administration of a program for which there is an appropriation by Parliament or an item included in Estimates then before the House of Commons shall, as the Treasury Board may prescribe, establish procedures and maintain records respecting the control of financial commitments chargeable to each
        appropriation or item.<sup><a href="#ftn78" id="ftnref78"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[78]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Related data – RACI:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of the RACI tables, data sets that are part of the common financial management business process.</p></dd><dt><strong>Relocation Coordinator:</strong></dt><dd><p>An individual or a group of individuals who create the relocation file in cooperation with the contracted relocation service provider (exercising transaction authority), advise the employee on the process that must be followed and ensure that the department meets its obligations as described in the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a><em>.</em><sup><a href="#ftn79" id="ftnref79"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[79]</a></sup> This role is also the point of contact for the contracted relocation service provider. In some departments, this role exercises certification pursuant to section 34 of the <em>Financial
        Administration Act</em>.</p></dd><dt><strong>Responsibility centre manager:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of this guideline, the incumbent of a position who has the required delegated financial, human resources or spending authority.</p></dd><dt><strong>Responsible – RACI:</strong></dt><dd><p>In the context of the RACI tables, a role that records the information or a decision, or that does the work to complete the activity, relying on the information from those consulted or accountable. There can be multiple individuals responsible within a role or multiple roles responsible.</p></dd><dt><strong>“Should be” model:</strong></dt><dd><p>The Government of Canada process that reflects current legislation and policy frameworks.</p></dd><dt><strong>Specified purpose account:</strong></dt><dd><p>Applies to monies received or collected from outside parties and deposited in the Consolidated Revenue Fund pursuant to section 21.(1) of the Financial Administration Act. The money may only be disbursed for the purpose specified in the instrument (i.e., act, trust, treaty, undertaking or contract) under which it is received. There has to be a direct
        link between monies received and monies disbursed, including any interest that may be authorized.<sup><a href="#ftn80" id="ftnref80"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[80]</a></sup></p></dd><dt><strong>Spending authority:</strong></dt><dd><p>Consists of three elements: expenditure initiation authority, commitment authority and transaction authority.</p></dd><dt><strong>Subprocess:</strong></dt><dd><p>An elaboration on a process appearing in a Level 2 business process flow. A subprocess is further elaborated at Level 3 through a definition of activities. <em>See also</em> Activity; Process.</p></dd><dt><strong>Subprocess group:</strong></dt><dd><p>A logical grouping of subprocesses that assist in the explanation of the overall process.</p></dd><dt><strong>Transaction authority:</strong></dt><dd><p>The authority to enter into contracts, including acquisition card purchases.<sup><a href="#ftn81" id="ftnref81"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[81]</a></sup> Transaction authority may be referred to as “contracting authority” in the department's delegation documents.</p></dd></dl></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix B: Abbreviations</h2><div class="pol-content"><dl><dt><strong>CF:</strong></dt><dd>corporate finance</dd><dt><strong>COMP:</strong></dt><dd>compensation</dd><dt><strong>CRF:</strong></dt><dd>Consolidated Revenue Fund</dd><dt><strong>DFMS</strong></dt><dd>departmental financial and materiel management system</dd><dt><strong>EAA:</strong></dt><dd>electronic authorization and authentication</dd><dt><strong>EE:</strong></dt><dd>employee</dd><dt><strong>FAA:</strong></dt><dd><em>Financial Administration Act</em></dd><dt><strong>FIN:</strong></dt><dd>financial services</dd><dt><strong>HR:</strong></dt><dd>other human resources management functions</dd><dt><strong>IS:</strong></dt><dd>interdepartmental settlement</dd><dt><strong>LS:</strong></dt><dd>legal services</dd><dt><strong>N/A:</strong></dt><dd>not applicable</dd><dt><strong>OCG:</strong></dt><dd>Office of the Comptroller General</dd><dt><strong>OCHRO:</strong></dt><dd>Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer</dd><dt><strong>PRN:</strong></dt><dd>payment reference number</dd><dt><strong>RCM:</strong></dt><dd>responsibility centre manager</dd><dt><strong>RG-BCM:</strong></dt><dd>Receiver General – Banking and Cash Management Sector</dd><dt><strong>RG-GL:</strong></dt><dd>Receiver General – General Ledger</dd><dt><strong>RG-SPS:</strong></dt><dd>Receiver General – Standard Payment System</dd><dt><strong>RPS:</strong></dt><dd>Regional Pay System</dd><dt><strong>s.:</strong></dt><dd>section of an Act</dd><dt><strong>SCP:</strong></dt><dd>strategic and corporate planning</dd></dl></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appC">Appendix C: Methods of Analysis Used in This Guideline</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="secC_1">How to Use This Guideline</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>Federal departments.<sup><a href="#ftn82" id="ftnref82"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[82]</a></sup> that have already documented business processes and key controls and control frameworks for their financial management business processes can validate their work by comparing their processes with the appropriate common financial management business process guidelines.</p><p>Federal departments that have not yet documented business processes or key controls and control frameworks for their financial management business processes can accelerate and validate their work by using the guidelines as a starting point for the development of control-focused documentation that is both department- and system-specific.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="secC_2">Methods of Analysis</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>This guideline provides information to the business user (as opposed to the more common objective of supporting a systems development exercise). This guideline describes three levels of detail as defined in the <a href="#appA">Appendix A</a>.</p><h4>Process Model Levels</h4><p>As illustrated in Figure 11, the Level 1 process model represents the highest level and least detailed view of the financial management business process. It provides a graphical representation of financial management in the Government of Canada that applies to all functional domains and cross-functional areas.</p><div id="ldr11" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 11. Level 1 Model of Financial Management</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-11-eng.jpg" alt="Level 1 Model of Financial Management" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=11">Text version: Figure 11. Level 1 Model of Financial Management</a></p></div><p>This Level 1 model provides an overarching context for all financial management in the Government of Canada and can be applied to the following domains, applicable to the common financial management business processes:</p><ul><li>Planning, Budgeting and Forecasting;</li><li>Revenue and Accounts Receivable;</li><li>Expenditures and Accounts Payable;</li><li>Materiel/Finance Interactions;</li><li>Human Resources/Finance Interactions;</li><li>Transfer Payments;</li><li>Common Data;</li><li>Integration; and</li><li>Results and Performance Reporting.</li></ul><p>The Manage Other Capital Assets business process falls within the Materiel/Finance Interactions functional domain.</p><h4>Process Flows</h4><p>Process flows provide a graphical overview of financial management business processes and subprocesses, using the following symbols:</p><h5>Start and End</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-15-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Start of financial management business process." /> Start of financial management business process.</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-16-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: End of financial management business process." /> End of financial management business process.</p><h5>Processes and Activities</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-17-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: A subprocess group (Level 2 grouping of subprocesses)." /> Subprocess group (Level 2 grouping of subprocesses).</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-18-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: A subprocess (Level 2) or activity (Level 3)." /> Subprocess (Level 2) or activity (Level 3).</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-19-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: A process or activity that is outside the common financial management business processes." /> Subprocess (Level 2) or activity (Level 3) that is outside the scope of the common financial management business processes.</p><h5>Gateways</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-20-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Parallel" /><em><strong>Parallel: </strong></em>All of the following subprocesses (Level 2) or activities (Level 3) must be completed.</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-21-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Inclusive or: One or more of the following subprocesses (Level 2) or activities (Level 3) must be selected and completed." /><em><strong>Inclusive "or": </strong></em>One or more of the following subprocesses (Level 2) or activities (Level 3) must be selected and completed.</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-22-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Exclusive or: Only one of the following subprocesses (Level 2) or activities (Level 3) must be selected and completed." /><em><strong>Exclusive "or": </strong></em>Only one of the following subprocesses (Level 2) or activities (Level 3) must be selected and completed.</p><h5>Connectors</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-23-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Connection to a subprocess (Level 2) or an activity (Level 3) appearing on the same page." /> Connection to a subprocess (Level 2) or an activity (Level 3) appearing on the same page.</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-24-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Connection to a subprocess (Level 2) or an activity (Level 3) defined in the common financial management business processes." /> Connection to a subprocess (Level 2) or an activity (Level 3) defined in the common financial management business processes.</p><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-25-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Connection to a process that is outside the scope of the common financial management business processes." /> Connection to a process that is outside the scope of the common financial management business processes.</p><h5>Decisions</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-26-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Decision" />Decision.</p><h5>Inputs and Outputs</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-27-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Key input into, or key output from, a subprocess or an activity." /> Key input into, or key output from, a subprocess or an activity.</p><h5>Other Symbols Used</h5><p><img src="/pol-cont/24970-28-eng.jpg" alt="Symbol found on Figures: Annotation" /> Annotation.</p><h4><abbr title="responsible, accountable, consulted, informed">RACI</abbr> Tables</h4><p>This guideline uses a Responsible, Accountable, Consulted and Informed (RACI) approach to describe how the roles and responsibilities apply to given subprocesses. This approach, depicted in Table 11, identifies related data, the role assignment and the applicable authoritative source.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption class="alignLeft"><strong><em>Table 17. Sample RACI Analysis Table</em></strong></caption><thead><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Activity</th><th scope="col">Related Data</th><th scope="col">Responsible</th><th scope="col">Accountable</th><th scope="col">Consulted</th><th scope="col">Informed</th><th scope="col">Authoritative Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li> </li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td></tr><tr><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"><ul class="index"><li> </li></ul></td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td><td class="alignTopLeft"> </td></tr></tbody></table><ul><li><strong>Activity:</strong> This refers to the number and the title of the activity within the subprocess.</li><li><strong>Related Data:</strong> Data typically created or reviewed as part of the activity, and listed alphabetically.</li><li><strong>Roles and Responsibilities:</strong> In this guideline, a role is an individual or a group of individuals whose involvement in an activity is described using the <abbr title="responsible, accountable, consulted, informed">RACI</abbr> approach. Because of differences among departments, a role may not correspond to a specific position, title or organizational unit. A detailed description of roles and
                    responsibilities for Manage Other Capital Assets is provided in <a href="#appD">Appendix D</a>.
                    
                    <ul><li><strong>Responsible:</strong> A role that records the information or a decision, or that does the work to complete the activity, relying on the information from those consulted or accountable. There can be multiple roles responsible.</li><li><strong>Accountable:</strong> The role that can attest to the truth of the information or a decision and that is accountable for the completion of the activity. There must be exactly one role accountable for each activity.</li><li><strong>Consulted:</strong> A role that is required to provide accurate information or a decision for an activity to be completed. There may or may not be a consulted role, and consultation may or may not be mandatory. When consultation does occur, there is typically a two-way communication between those consulted and the responsible party.</li><li><strong>Informed:</strong> A role that is notified of the information or a decision after the decision is made or the activity is completed. There may or may not be an informed role, and informing the role may or may not be mandatory. There is typically a one-way communication from the responsible or accountable party to those informed.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Authoritative Source:</strong>  A system that holds the official version of the information generated by the activity or a decision resulting from the activity. The authoritative source can be automated or manual.</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> Occasionally, roles and responsibilities can change, depending on the scenario involved. In such cases, an “S(X)” notation is used to show the differences in roles for each scenario.</p></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appD">Appendix D: Detailed Description Roles and Responsibilities</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This appendix describes in detail the roles and responsibilities identified for Manage Other Payments. In this guideline, a role is an individual or a group of individuals whose involvement in an activity is described using the Responsible, Accountable, Consulted and Informed (RACI) approach. Because of differences among departments,<sup><a href="#ftn83" id="ftnref83"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[83]</a></sup> a role may not correspond to a specific position, title or organizational unit. The organizational roles are grouped by stakeholder category, as shown in Figure 12.</p><div id="ldr12" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 12. Roles Involved in Manage Other Payments</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-12-eng.jpg" alt="Roles Involved in Manage Other Payments" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=12">Text version: Figure 12. Roles Involved in Manage Other Payments</a></p></div><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="secD_1">Requirements Framework</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles act in support of legislation, such as the Financial Administration Act and the Federal Accountability Act, and define policy or processes that must be followed.</p><h4>Office of the Comptroller General</h4><p>The Treasury Board Secretariat's Office of the Comptroller General of Canada<sup><a href="#ftn84" id="ftnref84"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[84]</a></sup> (OCG) is responsible for providing functional direction and assurance for financial management, internal audit, investment planning, procurement, project management and the management of real property and material across the federal
            government.</p><p>The Office of the Comptroller General (OCG) supports the Comptroller General of Canada in this by working to ensure sound policies, standards and practices are in place, overseeing performance and compliance across government, and maintaining and building vibrant professional communities through a range of recruitment and development activities.</p><p>Of specific relevance to the Manage Other Payments business process, the OCG plays a lead role in enhancing, integrating, and standardizing business systems, policies, processes, and data to make quality information available for decision making and analysis.<sup><a href="#ftn85" id="ftnref85"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[85]</a></sup>.</p><h4>Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer</h4><p>The Treasury Board Secretariat's Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer (OCHRO)<sup><a href="#ftn86" id="ftnref86"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[86]</a></sup> was established to modernize human resources management across the Government of Canada, contributing to the delivery of quality services to Canadians. The Governance, Planning and Policy Sector
            provides departments with leadership and direction on Government of Canada common human resources business processes, human resources information management, and human resources systems by providing effective human resources standards, processes, infrastructure, and guidance. This includes the following:</p><ul><li>Networking and sharing best practices across the public service;</li><li>Leading the modernization of the classification process;</li><li>Helping to rebuild human resources capacity across government;</li><li>Providing guidance to streamline human resources business processes and systems across government; and</li><li>Developing modern electronic platforms for online learning.</li></ul><p>Regarding the Common Human Resources Business Process initiative, OCHRO will provide documented common end-to-end business processes for human resources business processes, allowing for a consistent definition of these processes for both the Human Resources and Finance communities.<sup><a href="#ftn87" id="ftnref87"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[87]</a></sup></p><h4>Deputy Head</h4><p>The deputy head is responsible for:<sup><a href="#ftn88" id="ftnref88"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[88]</a></sup></p><ul><li>Providing leadership by demonstrating financial responsibility, transparency, accountability and ethical conduct in financial and resources management;</li><li>Managing the department and departmental programs in compliance with legislation, regulations, Treasury Board policies and financial authorities;</li><li>Assuming overall stewardship responsibilities for the integrity of the department's financial management capabilities, and the department's capacity to meet the needs of the department and the government;</li><li>Ensuring the strategic planning process gives due consideration to financial risks,  financial sustainability, governance, resource allocation and performance monitoring; and</li><li>Establishing a sound financial management governance structure that fosters prudent stewardship of public resources in the delivery of the organization's mandate, consistent with the <a href="http://www2.parl.gc.ca/Content/LOP/ResearchPublications/prb0523-e.htm"><em>Management, Resources, and Results Structure</em></a> and the <a href="/maf-crg/index-eng.asp"><em>Management Accountability Framework</em></a><em>.</em></li></ul><p>The deputy head is also responsible for:</p><ul><li>Establishing procedures and maintaining records respecting the control of financial commitments, pursuant to section 32 of the <em>Financial Accountability Act</em>;<sup><a href="#ftn89" id="ftnref89"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[89]</a></sup></li><li>Ensuring the establishment, maintenance, monitoring and review of the departmental system of internal control to mitigate risks in the following broad categories:
                    <ul><li>The effectiveness and efficiency of programs, operations and resource management, including safeguarding of assets;</li><li>The reliability of financial reporting; and</li><li>Compliance with legislation, regulations, policies and delegated authorities;<sup><a href="#ftn90" id="ftnref90"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[90]</a></sup>and</li></ul></li><li>Ensuring that:
                    <ul><li>First-time managers at all levels successfully complete the required training so that they meet the <em>Standards on Knowledge for Required Training</em> prior to delegating authorities;</li><li>Existing managers and executives validate knowledge associated with their legal responsibilities to maintain their delegated authorities; and</li><li>Functional specialists successfully complete training and/or validate knowledge associated with their professional and legal responsibilities.<sup><a href="#ftn91" id="ftnref91"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[91]</a></sup></li></ul></li></ul><p>The deputy head is also responsible for ensuring compliance with other policy instruments as listed in Section 3.3, “References.”</p><h4>Receiver General – Accounting, Banking and Compensation Branch</h4><p>The Receiver General for Canada is a central government service, supporting both the treasury and the accountant functions of the federal government. The mandate of the Receiver General is to safeguard the integrity of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and the accounts of Canada. The <em>Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</em> designates the Minister of Public Works and
            Government Services as the Receiver General for Canada, and the Deputy Minister as the Deputy Receiver General for Canada.<sup><a href="#ftn92" id="ftnref92"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[92]</a></sup></p><p>The authorities carried out by the Receiver General are identified in various sections of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> and entail the following responsibilities: </p><ul><li>Ensuring that all monies owing to the government are deposited into bank accounts managed by the Receiver General;</li><li>Controlling the issue and redemption of all payments out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund;</li><li>Maintaining the accounts of Canada; and</li><li>Preparing annual consolidated audited Public Accounts.</li></ul><p>In addition, the Receiver General manages the Receiver General treasury, accounting and reporting systems, which are accessed by federal departments in fulfilling their accountabilities to the public and Parliament, through payment issuance, revenue collection or accounting and reporting. Directives and guidance related to accounting, payment and deposit issues are provided to federal
            departments through Receiver General Directives, the <em>Receiver General Manual</em>, and Receiver General Information Notices. These functions are performed by the Banking and Cash Management Sector and the Central Accounting and Reporting Sector of the Accounting, Banking and Compensation Branch of Public Works and Government Services Canada.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="secD_2">Financial Management Roles</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles act in response to financial management policy and process requirements—for example, from the Office of the Comptroller General and from deputy heads.</p><h4>Corporate Finance</h4><p>The chief financial officer, with the support of the corporate finance function, provides stewardship with respect to relevant legislation, regulations, policies, directives and standards related to financial management.</p><p>Corporate finance responsibilities of relevance to the Manage Other Payments business process involve:</p><ul><li>Developing, communicating and maintaining the departmental financial management framework and providing leadership and oversight on the proper application and monitoring of financial management across the department;<sup><a href="#ftn93" id="ftnref93"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[93]</a></sup></li><li>Ensuring that robust risk-based account verification procedures are in place, in compliance with the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>;<sup><a href="#ftn94" id="ftnref94"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[94]</a></sup></li><li>Establishing and communicating clear responsibilities for holders of positions with delegated financial authorities, and monitoring adherence to these responsibilities;<sup><a href="#ftn95" id="ftnref95"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[95]</a></sup></li><li>Providing a challenge function on financial management matters and the use of public resources across the department;<sup><a href="#ftn96" id="ftnref96"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[96]</a></sup></li><li>Providing functional guidance, direction and advice to managers across the department on matters of financial management;<sup><a href="#ftn97" id="ftnref97"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[97]</a></sup> and</li><li>Ensuring that financial officers who administer payment requisitions are aware of their responsibilities for processing garnishments in a timely and accurate manner, <em>consistent with</em> the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</em></a> and its regulations,
                    relevant provincial or territorial laws, and the Receiver General's <em>Guidelines on Garnishment</em>, <em>Garnishment of public servant's salaries and monies owing to individuals employed under contracts for services.</em><sup><a href="#ftn98" id="ftnref98"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[98]</a></sup></li></ul><p>The chief financial officer is also responsible for ensuring compliance with other policy instruments as listed in Section 3.3 “References.”</p><h4>Strategic and Corporate Planning</h4><p>The strategic and corporate planning role is responsible for coordinating input into the department-strategic strategic, integrated, and operational planning processes defined by the department, and for supporting central agency requirements, such as those under the Management, Resources, and Results Structure and the Management Accountability Framework, and required parliamentary reports,
            such as the Report on Plans and Priorities and the Departmental Performance Report. Functional ownership will vary, and strategic and corporate planning may be part of either the finance or policy organization in a department.</p><p>The deputy head is responsible for “ensuring that the strategic planning process gives due consideration to financial risks, financial sustainability, governance, resource allocation and performance monitoring.”<sup><a href="#ftn99" id="ftnref99"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[99]</a></sup> The chief financial officer is responsible for
            leading the financial component of the departmental planning process on behalf of the deputy head (unless otherwise delegated).<sup><a href="#ftn100" id="ftnref100"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[100]</a></sup> Senior department managers reporting directly to a deputy head are collectively responsible for overall input into the strategic and integrated planning
            processes.</p><h4>Financial Services</h4><p>The financial services role ensures the day-to-day application and practical implementation of financial controls. This role fulfills financial management responsibilities for departmental transactions (revenues, expenses, assets and liabilities) and vendor and client transactions.</p><p>Within financial services, the finance officer delegated the authority under section 33 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> is responsible for providing assurance on the adequacy of account verification and certification processes pursuant to section 34 of the Act and related financial controls, and for ensuring adherence to the requirements of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-98-130/index.html"><em>Payments and Settlements Requisitioning Regulations,1997</em></a><em>,</em> to ensure accurate and timely payment of transactions.</p><h4>Responsibility Centre Manager</h4><p>In this guideline, a responsibility centre manager role may represent either an individual responsibility centre or a group of responsibility centres, as would be the case for senior managers.</p><p>The role of responsibility centre manager has been delegated the authority to initiate expenditures and to enter into some contracts (transaction authority). The responsibility centre manager is responsible and accountable for recording and managing commitments in accordance with department-specific policy so that the department does not exceed the appropriation.<sup><a href="#ftn101" id="ftnref101"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[101]</a></sup></p><p>In completing the certification and verification requirements of section 34 of the FAA, the responsibility centre manager must ensure the timely performance of account verification and verify the correctness of the payment requested.<sup><a href="#ftn102" id="ftnref102"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[102]</a></sup> Additional details on the responsibility
            centre manager's responsibilities for account verification are provided in Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.1.7).</p><p>In fulfilling training and learning responsibilities and in order to have the necessary knowledge of legal responsibilities to effectively exercise their delegated authorities, managers at all levels should successfully complete the required training so that they meet the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12409"><em>Standards on Knowledge for Required Training</em></a>.<sup><a href="#ftn103" id="ftnref103"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[103]</a></sup> Managers and executives with existing delegated authorities must validate, at least every five years, their knowledge of their legal responsibilities in order to maintain their delegated authorities.<sup><a href="#ftn104" id="ftnref104"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[104]</a></sup></p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="secD_3">Other Functional Roles</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles act in response to financial management policy and process requirements—for example, from the Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer and from deputy heads.</p><h4>Compensation</h4><p>The establishment of pay entitlements and deductions and the calculation of gross pay amounts are compensation functions. The compensation advisor typically receives the pay-related document from the responsibility centre manager. When the employee is able to initiate a pay action directly with the compensation role or when a transaction originates with the Treasury Board (the Employer), the
            compensation advisor ensures that the responsibility centre manager is notified of the transaction. The compensation advisor may also receive “court”<sup><a href="#ftn105" id="ftnref105"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[105]</a></sup> orders that garnishee employees' salaries or that institute payments. The compensation advisor confirms that the
            employee is eligible for the payment, performs any required calculations, and enters the transaction into the Regional Pay System.</p><h4>Other Human Resources Management Functions</h4><p>“Other Human Resources Management functions” involve classification, staffing, labour relations, official languages, training, and performance appraisal, including awards and recognition. These functions provide managers, the compensation role and employees with important information (for example, classification decisions, identification of successful candidates in a staffing
            action, decisions on disciplinary actions, or identification of recipients and amounts for special awards) that can lead to pay transactions. Note that these functions do not directly initiate pay transactions.</p><p>The heads of human resources are also responsible for ensuring that human resources personnel involved in the garnishment process are aware of their responsibilities and process garnishments in a timely and accurate manner consistent with the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/index.html"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</em></a> and its regulations,
            relevant provincial or territorial laws, and the Office of Chief Human Resources Officer's <em>Guidelines for the Processing of Garnishments</em>.<sup><a href="#ftn106" id="ftnref106"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[106]</a></sup></p><h4>Asset and Materiel Management Services</h4><p>The Asset and materiel management services role provides contracting and materiel services for a department. The Government of Canada's definition of asset and materiel management services<sup><a href="#ftn107" id="ftnref107"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[107]</a></sup> identifies three categories of services in departments and agencies. These services
            normally occur as a result of a financial transaction (purchases, inventory, asset accounting) and may be directly associated with an employee or a position. Administrative officers and staff provide the following:</p><ul><li><strong>Real property services:</strong> to ensure that real property is managed in a sustainable and financially responsible manner throughout its life cycle, to support the cost-effective and efficient delivery of government programs. Real property is defined as any right, interest or benefit in land, which includes mines, minerals and
                    improvements on, above or below the surface of the land.</li><li><strong>Materiel services:</strong> to ensure that materiel can be managed by departments in a sustainable and financially responsible manner to support the cost-effective and efficient delivery of government programs. Materiel is defined as all movable assets, excluding money and records, acquired by Her Majesty in right of Canada. Materiel
                    management entails all activities necessary to acquire, hold, use and dispose of materiel, including the notion of achieving the greatest possible efficiency throughout the life cycle of materiel assets; and</li><li><strong>Acquisition services</strong> (formerly Procurement Services): to acquire a good or service to fulfill a properly completed request (including a complete and accurate definition of requirements and certification that funds are available) until entering into or amending a contract.</li></ul><p>Under the Manage Other Payments business process, asset and materiel management services is responsible for exercising control commitments (on behalf of the manager), if delegated to do so.</p><h4>Employee</h4><p>The employee role is performed by a federal government person “who is any person currently paid a salary or remunerated from the Consolidated Revenue Fund.”<sup><a href="#ftn108" id="ftnref108"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[108]</a></sup> Employees can initiate or be the recipient of accountable advances and reimbursable expenses.</p><p>Government of Canada employees initiate or are the recipients of compensation actions and are required to:</p><ul><li>Provide accurate personal data (for example, social insurance number, address, banking details, and life events, such as marriage and birth) to support compensation actions; and</li><li>Accept or initiate changes to their conditions of employment, which are reflected in changes to their compensation package. This activity includes:
                    <ul><li>Timely reporting of leave, with or without pay, and extra duty (for example, overtime);</li><li>Management of work schedule (for example, flexible and variable hours); and</li><li>Reporting of discrepancies to the compensation role.</li></ul></li></ul><p>Employees are expected to be knowledgeable about relevant policies and collective agreements or terms and conditions affecting their employment as well as the relocation of employees. They are also expected to follow rules and regulations pertaining to the procurement of goods and services. Employees are responsible for ensuring compliance with other policy instruments as listed in Section 3.3
            “References.”</p><p>A small number of transactions, such as those related to learning and development and accountable advances, can be initiated by employees directly, sometimes without the knowledge of the responsibility centre manager. When the transaction affects the responsibility centre manager's budget, the compensation advisor needs to ensure that the responsibility centre manager is notified of the
            transaction.</p><p>A definition of “employee” is also provided in <a href="#appF">Appendix F</a>: Process Flow for Manage Payments for Employee Relocation.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><h3 id="secD_4">Central Services</h3><div class="pol-content"><p>The following organizational roles provide a central service to most federal government departments.</p><h4>Receiver General—Banking and Cash Management Sector</h4><p>The Receiver General for Canada is a central government service, supporting both the treasury and the accountant functions of the federal government. The Banking and Cash Management Sector specifically is responsible to:</p><ul><li>Control the Receiver General accounts at the Bank of Canada;</li><li>Negotiate and implement banking arrangements for payments and revenues;  </li><li>Maintain the float model for federal government cash flows;</li><li>Manage the issuance, redemption and validation of all Receiver General payments;</li><li>Manage the Standard Payment System  and the Government Banking System;</li><li>Publish the bank rate established by the Bank of Canada; and</li><li>Calculate the payment on due date interest rate.<sup><a href="#ftn109" id="ftnref109"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[109]</a></sup></li></ul><h4>Legal Services</h4><p>Legal services are provided by the Department of Justice Canada. The Department of Justice Canada is responsible for providing legal opinions and advice, including negotiation advice, and conducting litigation by or against the Crown and against its servants.<sup><a href="#ftn110" id="ftnref110"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[110]</a></sup></p><p>The Department of Justice Canada provides legal services to government on a “portfolio” basis. There are six portfolios encompassing the entire range of federal departments: Government-at-Large and the Justice Portfolio, Aboriginal Affairs Portfolio, Business and Regulatory Law Portfolio, Central Agencies Portfolio, Public Safety, Defence and Immigration Portfolio, and the Tax Law
            Portfolio. Services are delivered through a mix of co-located departmental legal services units, specialized branches located within the Department of Justice Canada, and a network of six regional offices located across the country.<sup><a href="#ftn111" id="ftnref111"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[111]</a></sup></p><p>The Department of Justice Canada is responsible for the administration of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</em></a>. The Garnishment Registries are served the relevant garnishment documents required under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and
            Pension Diversion Act</em></a> to garnishee against salaries of public servants and fees owing to personal services contractors. The Garnishment Registries are responsible for validating and forwarding the documents to the appropriate department for action in accordance with the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion
            Act</em></a> and Regulations.<sup><a href="#ftn112" id="ftnref112"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[112]</a></sup></p><p>The responsibilities of the Minister of Justice and Attorney General of Canada are set out in the <em>Department of Justice Act</em> and 49 other Acts of Parliament. The Department of Justice fulfills three distinct roles within the Government of Canada, acting as a:</p><ul><li>Policy department with broad responsibilities for overseeing all federal matters relating to the administration of justice;</li><li>Provider of a range of legal advisory, litigation and legislative services to government departments; and</li><li>Central agency responsible for supporting the Minister in advising Cabinet on all legal matters, including the constitutionality of government initiatives and activities.<sup><a href="#ftn113" id="ftnref113"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[113]</a></sup></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appE">Appendix E: Process Flow for the Use and Reconciliation of Petty Cash</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This appendix provides supplementary information on using and reconciling petty cash and should be read in conjunction with the remainder of the Manage Other Payments business process. Rules and regulations pertaining to the procurement of goods and services apply to expenditures reimbursed with petty cash.</p><p>Petty cash funds are a type of standing advance known as “an accountable advance issued in a specified amount for an indeterminate period and replenished to that specific amount each time an accounting for expenditures is made.”<sup><a href="#ftn114" id="ftnref114"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[114]</a></sup> Petty cash is used to make low-value
        payments only when it is more cost-effective than other payment methods. An acquisition card is the preferred alternative unless a card is not available or its use is not suitable.<sup><a href="#ftn115" id="ftnref115"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[115]</a></sup></p><h3>Role and Responsibilities</h3><p>The custodian has sole responsibility for the petty cash fund. The custodian is the person to whom an accountable advance has been issued or who is responsible for an accountable advance,<sup><a href="#ftn116" id="ftnref116"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[116]</a></sup> which is documented through an accounting and acknowledgement of responsibilities for the
        fund.<sup><a href="#ftn117" id="ftnref117"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[117]</a></sup></p><p>Under section 6.7 of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a><em>,</em> the petty cash custodian is:</p><ul><li>Personally responsible and accountable for advances issued to establish a petty cash fund. Any loss or shortage may be recovered from the petty cash custodian. Note that subsection 76(4) or section 78 of the <em>Financial Accountability Act</em> applies; and</li><li>Responsible for reconciling the petty cash fund even when a petty cash fund is not used frequently. The custodian should reconcile the fund once a week or at least once a month, to verify that it balances and that no theft has taken place, and should report on the reconciliations to his or her supervisor.</li></ul><p>The <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a> provides additional details on:</p><ul><li>The establishment of the petty cash fund;<sup><a href="#ftn118" id="ftnref118"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[118]</a></sup></li><li>The safeguarding of petty cash by the custodian;<sup><a href="#ftn119" id="ftnref119"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[119]</a></sup></li><li>Reconciliation of petty cash, ensuring that custodians are personally responsible and accountable for advances that have been issued to them;<sup><a href="#ftn120" id="ftnref120"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[120]</a></sup> and</li><li>An adequate separation of duties of employees who deal with petty cash and change funds and other advances.<sup><a href="#ftn121" id="ftnref121"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[121]</a></sup></li></ul><h3>Process Flow</h3><p>Figure 13 depicts the Level 2 process flow for the Use and Reconciliation of Petty Cash.</p><div id="ldr13" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 13. Use and Reconciliation of Petty Cash – Level 2 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-13-eng.jpg" alt="Use and Reconciliation of Petty Cash – Level 2 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=13">Text version: Figure 13. Use and Reconciliation of Petty Cash – Level 2 Process Flow</a></p></div><h3>Manage Requirements Subprocess Group</h3><p><strong>Determine Requirements (Subprocess 3.3.1):  </strong>Typically, a petty cash disbursement is ad hoc and low value. Nevertheless, the requirements should be defined and approval should be obtained.</p><p><strong>Determine and Exercise Expenditure Initiation Authority (Subprocess 3.3.2):</strong> The responsibility centre manager ensures that he or she has been delegated the appropriate expenditure initiation authority and exercises the authority or obtains approval.<sup><a href="#ftn122" id="ftnref122"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[122]</a></sup></p><p><strong>Pay Supplier for Deliverables (Subprocess 3.3.8)</strong>: Once the goods are received or the service is rendered, the responsible individual pays and requests a reimbursement through petty cash, submitting appropriate documentation—for example, a receipt or voucher covering the expenditure.<sup><a href="#ftn123" id="ftnref123"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[123]</a></sup></p><h3>Manage Petty Cash Reconciliation Subprocess Group</h3><p>Evidence of account verification and certification pursuant to section 34 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA) are indicated on the invoice or receipt for reimbursements handled through petty cash disbursement, according to department-specific procedures. When processing reimbursements through petty cash, there are two possible streams:</p><ul><li>When a voucher or receipt is received, the responsibility centre manager performs account verification and provides certification pursuant to section 34 of the FAA <strong>(Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5))</strong> before the custodian reimburses the employee <strong>(Reimburse With Petty Cash (Subprocess 3.3.9))</strong>. When the petty
                cash fund requires replenishment, the custodian reconciles the petty cash fund and prepares a summary of receipts certified under section 34 of the FAA; or</li><li>The custodian reimburses the employee through the petty cash fund <strong>(Reimburse With Petty Cash (Subprocess 3.3.9))</strong>. When replenishment of the fund is necessary, the custodian reconciles the petty cash fund and prepares a summary of receipts for the responsibility centre manager with the delegated authority. The responsibility
                centre manager performs account verification and provides section 34 certification on the summary of receipts rather than on an individual basis <strong>(Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5))</strong>.</li></ul><p>With either stream, the end result of the reconciliation is the summary of receipts, that is, a collection of supporting receipts and invoices which are voided in a manner to prevent reuse<sup><a href="#ftn124" id="ftnref124"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[124]</a></sup> and are certified pursuant to section 34 of the FAA. The reconciliation should be done
        regularly by the petty cash custodian. When the funds are depleted, the summary of receipts is processed for payment, replenishing the petty cash fund.  </p><h3>Manage Payments Subprocess Group</h3><p><strong>Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6):</strong> A request for payment is prepared by the custodian, who sends the request and any supporting documents to financial services for processing, including payment authority pursuant to section 33 of the FAA.<sup><a href="#ftn125" id="ftnref125"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[125]</a></sup></p><p><strong>Issue payment (Subprocess 3.3.7):</strong> The payment requisition is sent to the Receiver General for payment issuance. The payment requisition files are edited and validated, and payments are released by the Receiver General. The Receiver General produces a generic return file containing unique payment references for control purposes. The payment records are updated in the
        departmental financial and materiel management system<sup><a href="#ftn126" id="ftnref126"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[126]</a></sup> by financial services, and the Manage Other Payments business process ends. When quality assurance is performed, the process flow continues to Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2). When quality assurance is not performed, the process flow continues to
        Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1).</p><p>As part of the period-end activities described in Manage Financial Close (Business Process 8.2), it may be determined that petty cash is no longer needed. In that case, it is necessary to proceed with reconciliation, and the process flow continues to Manage Revenue, Receivables and Receipts (Business Process 2.1), to deposit the funds and close the petty cash fund. The <em>Directive on
        Receipt, Deposit and Recording of Money</em> applies to the return of funds to the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appF">Appendix F: Process Flow for Manage Payments for Employee Relocation</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This appendix provides supplementary information and should be read in conjunction with the remainder of the Manage Other Payments business process, the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, the <a href="/hr-rh/gtla-vgcl/eggca-gdpngc/eggca-gdpngc-eng.asp"><em>Executive Group (EX) and Governor In
        Council Appointees (GIC) - Relocation Provisions</em></a> and the <a href="/pubs_pol/hrpubs/TBM_113/iairp-prinefp-eng.asp"><em>Addendum - Initial Appointees Relocation Program</em></a>.</p><p>The <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a> applies to:</p><ul><li>All departments and other portions of the public service of Canada listed in Schedules I and IV of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em> (FAA); and</li><li>Any employer listed in Schedule V of the FAA that is a member of the NJC and that has opted to follow the directive.<sup><a href="#ftn127" id="ftnref127"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[127]</a></sup></li></ul><p>The <em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em> describes the government's Integrated Relocation Program, which is “the framework governing the relocation of employees of all federal government departments, the Canadian Forces (CF) and the Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP).”<sup><a href="#ftn128" id="ftnref128"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[128]</a></sup>  The
        CF and the RCMP use many of the provisions of the directive, including some specific to their memberships, and both organizations publish a departmental relocation policy.<sup><a href="#ftn129" id="ftnref129"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[129]</a></sup></p><h3>Roles and Responsibilities</h3><p>The following are the key roles involved in Manage Payments for Employee Relocation.</p><p>The <strong>deputy head</strong> provides leadership by demonstrating financial responsibility, transparency, accountability and ethical conduct in financial and resource management. This includes compliance with legislation, regulations, Treasury Board policies and financial authorities.<sup><a href="#ftn130" id="ftnref130"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[130]</a></sup></p><p>The <strong>contracted relocation service provider (CRSP)</strong> is the private sector company contracted by the federal government to deliver the Integrated Relocation Program.<sup><a href="#ftn131" id="ftnref131"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[131]</a></sup> This role is responsible for providing the services specified in the contract and in the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a><em>,</em> which includes establishing contact with the employee within 48 hours and providing the employee with advance funds as required.</p><p>The <strong>departmental national coordinator</strong> acts as the department's internal policy coordinator for the Integrated Relocation Program and issues approvals specific to the directive. This role serves as the liaison between the employer and the contracted relocation service provider and is the sole departmental liaison with the Treasury Board Secretariat's program authority for the
        Integrated Relocation Program.</p><p>The <strong>relocation coordinator</strong> is an individual or a group of individuals who, in cooperation with the contracted relocation service provider, are responsible for initiating the relocation file (by exercising transaction authority), advising the employee on the procedures that should be followed, and ensuring that the department meets its obligations as described in the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council Relocation (NJC) Directive</em></a><em>.</em> The relocation coordinator also serves as the departmental contact for the contracted relocation service provider, and in some departments, exercises certification authority pursuant to section 34 of the FAA.</p><p>The <strong>responsibility centre manager</strong> exercises expenditure initiation authority, commitment control pursuant to section 32 of the FAA, and certification authority pursuant to section 34 of the FAA for relocation-related payments, and is responsible for the account verification.</p><p>The <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a> defines “<strong>employee</strong>” as a person who is employed in the federal public service performing continuing full-time duties of a position and whose salary is paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund (employees performing continuing
        full-time duties on a seasonal basis are also included). <sup><a href="#ftn132" id="ftnref132"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[132]</a></sup> “Employee” also means a deputy minister, or any other person appointed by the Governor in Council to a position classified within the occupational groups comprising the Senior Management, Program and Administrative and Foreign Service, Scientific and
        Professional, and Technical categories.<sup><a href="#ftn133" id="ftnref133"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[133]</a></sup></p><p>The employee is expected to read the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a> and, when applicable, the <a href="/hr-rh/gtla-vgcl/eggca-gdpngc/eggca-gdpngc-eng.asp"><em>Executive Group (EX) and Governor In Council Appointees (GIC) - Relocation Provisions</em></a>, and to consult with the contracted
        relocation service provider before engaging in any relocation-related activities.<sup><a href="#ftn134" id="ftnref134"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[134]</a></sup> Further details on the employee's responsibilities are outlined in the directive.</p><p>The <strong>Central Removal Service</strong> of Public Works and Government Services Canada arranges with removal services contractors to transport and store the household goods of relocating employees. The services are provided for federal government employees relocating within Canada and the continental United States of America, including Alaska, except from isolated posts where professional
        packing services are not available.</p><p>In accordance with the Integrated Relocation Program, the following departments must use the Central Removal Service:</p><ul><li>All departments, agencies and corporations listed in Schedules I, I.1 and II of the FAA, except National Defence and the Royal Canadian Mounted Police; and</li><li>All branches of the government designated as departments for the purpose of the FAA, with the exception of Royal Commissions.<sup><a href="#ftn135" id="ftnref135"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[135]</a></sup></li></ul><h3>Process Flow</h3><p>Manage Payments for Employee Relocation does not follow Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1), and transactions related to employee relocation do not conform to any of the four payment categories described in Section 3.1 of this guideline. Because of its unique nature, Manage Payments for Employee Relocation is described in this appendix.</p><p>Figure 14 depicts the Level 2 process flow for Manage Payments for Employee Relocation.</p><div id="ldr14" class="alignCenter"><p><em><strong>Figure 1. Manage Payments for Employee Relocation – Level 2 Process Flow</strong></em></p><p><img src="/pol-cont/26954-14-eng.jpg" alt="Manage Payments for Employee Relocation – Level 2 Process Flow" /></p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26954&amp;section=longdesc&amp;ld=14">Text version: Figure 14. Manage Payments for Employee Relocation – Level 2 Process Flow</a></p></div><p>Manage Payments for Employee Relocation begins with an approved letter of offer or equivalent identifying the requirement for the employee to relocate for the position. The document can also take the form of a posting notice, a secondment, or another type of agreement requiring relocation. The possibility of relocation should be considered when initiating a staffing action and obtaining
        approval for the letter of offer. This activity is covered in the <em>Common Human Resource Business Process,</em><a href="http://chrbp-pocrh.tbs-sct.gc.ca/processMap-eng.aspx?processID=3.0&amp;path=">3.0 “Staffing and Employee Integration</a>.”</p><p><strong>Open Relocation File With Contracted Relocation Service Provider (CRSP)(Subprocess 3.3.10):</strong> The employee provides a copy of the signed letter of offer to the relocation coordinator. The relocation coordinator provides written authorization to the CRSP to provide contracted relocation services to the employee referred,<sup><a href="#ftn136" id="ftnref136"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[136]</a></sup> thereby initiating the file and exercising transaction authority, the third element of spending authority. Once the file is created, the employee provides additional data directly to the contracted relocation service provider so that a financial worksheet can be prepared.</p><p>The contracted relocation service provider is responsible for conducting all relocation activities (for example, accountable advances, travel, house hunting, temporary accommodations) and for preparing and submitting related expense claims. The contracted relocation service provider is also responsible for ensuring that all activities conform to the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=6&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a> as well as to the other references noted in this appendix. The policy instruments identify when further approval is required from the responsibility centre manager, the departmental relocation coordinator or the national departmental coordinator. The activities
        conducted by the contracted relocation service provider are outside the scope of the Manage Other Payments business process. Until the relocation file is closed, the supporting documents remain with the contracted relocation services provider. The file, including the original receipts, is sent to the department only when the file is closed.</p><p><strong>Manage Payables (Subprocess 3.3.5):</strong> Invoices are sent to departments by the Central Removal Service of Public Works and Government Services Canada or the contracted relocation service provider or, as is the case for National Defence (DND) and the RCMP, the moving company. In the case of DND and the RCMP, the invoice is verified and certified pursuant to section 34 of the FAA by
        the responsibility centre manager or the departmental relocation coordinator.</p><p>For removal of household goods, the contracted relocation service provider provides the departmental relocation coordinator with the required documentation. The departmental relocation coordinator then notifies the Central Removal Service. The Central Removal Service invoices the department directly, and the invoice is paid through interdepartmental settlement. These activities are performed
        during Manage Interdepartmental Settlements (Business Process 2.2).</p><p>Air or train travel booked with travel authority numbers (TANs) and charged to the departmental travel expense account is processed during Manage Travel (Business Process 3.2).</p><p>The contracted relocation service provider invoices the department directly for services rendered. Invoicing is typically done in three instalments: the first two invoices are pre-billings and the third invoice is the final bill. The final bill includes all relocation costs incurred less advances received. A summary of relocation costs with documentation is attached to the invoice.</p><p>Account verification and certification of the invoice pursuant to section 34 of the FAA is performed by the responsibility centre manager or by the departmental relocation coordinator, when the authority has been delegated. When the responsibility centre manager performs account verification, he or she may consult with the departmental relocation coordinator regarding the directive and the
        specifics of the relocation. When advances exceed the actual cost of the relocation, a refund cheque from the contracted relocation service provider is attached to the summary. The cheque is recorded as a cash receipt. These activities are performed during Manage Revenue, Receivables and Receipts (Business Process 2.1). </p><p>Occasionally, an employee is overpaid and the overpayment needs to be recovered. The employee is invoiced, and the overpayment is collected. These activities are also performed during Manage Revenue, Receivables and Receipts (Business Process 2.1).</p><p><strong>Perform Payment Authority (Subprocess 3.3.6):</strong> This subprocess starts with the receipt of a request for payment. Quality assurance may be performed by financial services as part of the payment authorization process pursuant to section 33 of the FAA. Typically, a relocation invoice is considered as a high-risk transaction.</p><p><strong>Issue Payment (Subprocess 3.3.7):</strong> After payment is authorized pursuant to section 33 of the FAA, the payment requisition is sent to the Receiver General for payment issuance. The payment requisition files are edited and validated, and the payments are released by the Receiver General. The Receiver General produces a generic return file containing unique payment references for
        control purposes. The payment records are updated in the departmental financial and materiel management system<sup><a href="#ftn137" id="ftnref137"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span>[137]</a></sup> by financial services, signalling the end of Manage Other Payments (Business Process 3.3) and the start of Manage Post-Payment Verification (Business Process 8.1) or Manage Financial Close (Business Process
        8.2), depending on whether quality assurance is performed.</p></div></section></div><aside class="wb-fnote" role="note"><h2 id="fn">Footnotes</h2><dl><dt>Footnote ftn1</dt><dd id="ftn1"><p>
         This guideline applies to “departments” as defined in section 2 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref1"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>1<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn2</dt><dd id="ftn2"><p>
    	Payments that are made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and are department-specific rather than government-wide—for example, debt repayment or other transfer payments made by the Department of Finance Canada or Human Resources and Skills Development Canada—are not covered by any of the common financial management
        business processes. Nevertheless, department-specific payments are governed by section 26 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>, which states that “no payments shall be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund without the authority of Parliament.”
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref2"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>2<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn3</dt><dd id="ftn3"><p>
    	Under the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17064"><em>Directive on Specified Purpose Accounts</em></a>, “all amounts credited to [specified purpose accounts], whatever the source, are managed as public money. Accordingly, all regulations, policies and directives relating to the control of receipts and
        expenditures apply to funds received, credited and paid out for a special purpose or a specified purpose.” The type of transaction determines which common financial business process should be followed.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref3"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>3<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn4</dt><dd id="ftn4"><p>
         This guideline applies to “departments” as defined in section 2 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref4"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>4<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn5</dt><dd id="ftn5"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17590&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Directive on the Stewardship of Financial Management Systems</em></a>, Section 3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref5"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>5<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn6</dt><dd id="ftn6"><p>
    	Payments that are made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and that are department-specific rather than government-wide—for example, debt repayment or other transfer payments made by the Department of Finance Canada or Human Resources and Skills Development Canada—are not covered by any of the common financial
        management business processes. Nevertheless, department-specific payments are governed by section 26 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>, which states that “no payments shall be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund without the authority of Parliament.”
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref6"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>6<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn7</dt><dd id="ftn7"><p>
    	Under the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17064"><em>Directive on Specified Purpose Accounts</em></a>, “all amounts credited to [specified purpose accounts], whatever the source, are managed as public money. Accordingly, all regulations, policies and directives relating to the control of receipts and
        expenditures apply to funds received, credited and paid out for a special purpose or a specified purpose.” The type of transaction determines which common financial business process should be followed.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref7"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>7<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn8</dt><dd id="ftn8"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Sections 5.1.1 and 5.1.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref8"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>8<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn9</dt><dd id="ftn9"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref9"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>9<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn10</dt><dd id="ftn10"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19855&amp;section=text#appB"><em>Directive on the Management of Expenditures on Travel, Hospitality and Conferences</em></a>, Appendix B – Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref10"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>10<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn11</dt><dd id="ftn11"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782&amp;section=text#cha8"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a>, Section 8.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref11"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>11<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn12</dt><dd id="ftn12"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref12"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>12<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn13</dt><dd id="ftn13"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref13"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>13<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn14</dt><dd id="ftn14"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/manuels-manuals/chap4/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Manual –</em> Chapter 4: “Standard Payment System (SPS) and Departments”</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref14"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>14<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn15</dt><dd id="ftn15"><p>
         Although periodic payments are included in the approved plan and budget, the activities associated with the definition of requirements and expenditure initiation authority are conducted in the year that the contract is signed; these activities are performed during Manage Procure to Payment (Business Process 3.1).
        Consequently, periodic payments proceed directly to the Control Commitments subprocess group.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref15"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>15<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn16</dt><dd id="ftn16"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17067&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Guideline on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 5.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref16"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>16<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn17</dt><dd id="ftn17"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref17"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>17<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn18</dt><dd id="ftn18"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref18"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>18<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn19</dt><dd id="ftn19"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Appendix - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref19"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>19<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn20</dt><dd id="ftn20"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Appendix - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref20"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>20<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn21</dt><dd id="ftn21"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Section 6.2.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref21"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>21<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn22</dt><dd id="ftn22"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Sections 3.4 and  6.2.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref22"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>22<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn23</dt><dd id="ftn23"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.5
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref23"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>23<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn24</dt><dd id="ftn24"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/page-2.html#docCont"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a>, paragraph 6(4)(<em>a</em>)
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref24"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>24<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn25</dt><dd id="ftn25"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782&amp;section=text#cha6"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a>, Section 6.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref25"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>25<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn26</dt><dd id="ftn26"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a>, Section 3.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref26"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>26<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn27</dt><dd id="ftn27"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782&amp;section=text#cha6"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref27"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>27<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn28</dt><dd id="ftn28"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.1.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref28"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>28<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn29</dt><dd id="ftn29"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control,</em></a> Sections 3.5 and 6.2.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref29"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>29<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn30</dt><dd id="ftn30"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref30"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>30<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn31</dt><dd id="ftn31"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref31"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>31<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn32</dt><dd id="ftn32"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref32"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>32<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn33</dt><dd id="ftn33"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.8
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref33"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>33<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn34</dt><dd id="ftn34"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.9
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref34"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>34<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn35</dt><dd id="ftn35"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref35"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>35<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn36</dt><dd id="ftn36"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec5.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 5.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref36"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>36<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn37</dt><dd id="ftn37"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.6
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref37"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>37<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn38</dt><dd id="ftn38"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.8
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref38"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>38<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn39</dt><dd id="ftn39"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 3.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref39"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>39<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn40</dt><dd id="ftn40"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref40"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>40<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn41</dt><dd id="ftn41"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/page-18.html#docCont"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>, section 26
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref41"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>41<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn42</dt><dd id="ftn42"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Section 6.3.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref42"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>42<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn43</dt><dd id="ftn43"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Section 6.2.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref43"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>43<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn44</dt><dd id="ftn44"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.3.4
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref44"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>44<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn45</dt><dd id="ftn45"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref45"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>45<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn46</dt><dd id="ftn46"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2/page-2.html#docCont"><em>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</em></a>, subsection 7(1)
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref46"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>46<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn47</dt><dd id="ftn47"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>, Section 6.3.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref47"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>47<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn48</dt><dd id="ftn48"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>, Section 6.3.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref48"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>48<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn49</dt><dd id="ftn49"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>, Section 6.3.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref49"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>49<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn50</dt><dd id="ftn50"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref50"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>50<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn51</dt><dd id="ftn51"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>, Section 6.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref51"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>51<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn52</dt><dd id="ftn52"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.3.7
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref52"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>52<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn53</dt><dd id="ftn53"><p><a href="http://www.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/recgen/txt/taux-rates-eng.html"><em>Payment on Due Date (PODD) Interest Rate</em></a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref53"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>53<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn54</dt><dd id="ftn54"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15784&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Payment Requisitioning and Cheque Control</em></a>, Section 6.3.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref54"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>54<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn55</dt><dd id="ftn55"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Section 6.3.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref55"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>55<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn56</dt><dd id="ftn56"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Section 6.2.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref56"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>56<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn57</dt><dd id="ftn57"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#a7-2"><em>Receiver General Control Framework</em></a>, section 7.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref57"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>57<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn58</dt><dd id="ftn58"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/mp-pm/index-eng.html">Payment Methods, Receiver General for Canada</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref58"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>58<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn59</dt><dd id="ftn59"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Section 6.2.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref59"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>59<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn60</dt><dd id="ftn60"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Control Framework</em></a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref60"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>60<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn61</dt><dd id="ftn61"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/f-11/page-17.html"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>, section 29.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref61"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>61<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn62</dt><dd id="ftn62"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#7"><em>Receiver General Control Framework</em></a>, Chapter 7
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref62"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>62<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn63</dt><dd id="ftn63"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/manuels-manuals/chap4/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Manual</em></a>, Chapter 4: “Standard Payment System (SPS) and Departments”
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref63"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>63<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn64</dt><dd id="ftn64"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/cc-cf/07-eng.html#7"><em>Receiver General Control Framework</em></a>, Chapter 7
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref64"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>64<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn65</dt><dd id="ftn65"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/page-1.html#h-2"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a>, section 2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref65"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>65<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn66</dt><dd id="ftn66"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Appendix A – Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref66"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>66<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn67</dt><dd id="ftn67"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.6
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref67"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>67<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn68</dt><dd id="ftn68"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Appendix - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref68"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>68<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn69</dt><dd id="ftn69"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Appendix - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref69"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>69<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn70</dt><dd id="ftn70"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref70"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>70<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn71</dt><dd id="ftn71"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/page-1.html#h-2"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a><em>,</em> section 2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref71"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>71<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn72</dt><dd id="ftn72"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17590&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on the Stewardship of Financial Management Systems</em></a>, Appendix – Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref72"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>72<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn73</dt><dd id="ftn73"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref73"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>73<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn74</dt><dd id="ftn74"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Appendix - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref74"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>74<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn75</dt><dd id="ftn75"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17590&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on the Stewardship of Financial Management Systems</em></a>, Appendix – Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref75"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>75<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn76</dt><dd id="ftn76"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19855&amp;section=text#appB"><em>Directive on the Management of Expenditures on Travel, Hospitality and Conferences</em></a>, Appendix B - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref76"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>76<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn77</dt><dd id="ftn77"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12405&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Policy on Learning, Training, and Development</em></a>, Appendix A - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref77"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>77<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn78</dt><dd id="ftn78"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/page-20.html#docCont"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>, subsection 32(2)
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref78"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>78<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn79</dt><dd id="ftn79"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=105&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_1"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Sections 2.1 and 2.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref79"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>79<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn80</dt><dd id="ftn80"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17064&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Specified Purposes Accounts</em></a>, Appendix A - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref80"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>80<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn81</dt><dd id="ftn81"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17060&amp;section=text#appA"><em>Directive on Delegation of Financial Authorities for Disbursements</em></a>, Appendix - Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref81"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>81<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn82</dt><dd id="ftn82"><p>
         This guideline applies to “departments” as defined in section 2 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref82"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>82<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn83</dt><dd id="ftn83"><p>
         This guideline applies to “departments” as defined in section 2 of the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>.
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref83"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>83<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn84</dt><dd id="ftn84"><p><a href="/ocg-bcg/abu-ans/abu-ans-eng.asp">Office of the Comptroller General of Canada's website</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref84"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>84<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn85</dt><dd id="ftn85"><p><a href="/ocg-bcg/abu-ans/structure-eng.asp">Office of the Comptroller General's of Canada website</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref85"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>85<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn86</dt><dd id="ftn86"><p><a href="/chro-dprh/index-eng.asp">Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer's website</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref86"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>86<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn87</dt><dd id="ftn87"><p><a href="http://www.ochro-bdprh.tbs-sct.gc.ca/chrbp-pocrh/">Common Human Resources Business Process initiative</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref87"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>87<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn88</dt><dd id="ftn88"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref88"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>88<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn89</dt><dd id="ftn89"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 3.5
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref89"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>89<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn90</dt><dd id="ftn90"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15258&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Policy on Internal Control</em></a>, Section 6.1.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref90"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>90<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn91</dt><dd id="ftn91"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12405&amp;section=text#cha6"><em>Policy on Learning, Training and Development</em></a>, Section 6.1.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref91"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>91<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn92</dt><dd id="ftn92"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-38.2/page-1.html#docCont"><em>Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</em></a>, sections 3 and 4
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref92"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>92<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn93</dt><dd id="ftn93"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref93"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>93<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn94</dt><dd id="ftn94"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.4
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref94"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>94<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn95</dt><dd id="ftn95"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.9
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref95"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>95<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn96</dt><dd id="ftn96"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.10
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref96"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>96<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn97</dt><dd id="ftn97"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.13
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref97"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>97<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn98</dt><dd id="ftn98"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15781&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Financial Management of Pay Administration</em></a>, Section 6.3.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref98"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>98<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn99</dt><dd id="ftn99"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.1.4
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref99"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>99<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn100</dt><dd id="ftn100"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Section 5.4.5
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref100"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>100<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn101</dt><dd id="ftn101"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref101"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>101<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn102</dt><dd id="ftn102"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref102"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>102<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn103</dt><dd id="ftn103"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12409&amp;section=text#cha3"><em>Standards on Knowledge for Required Training</em></a>, Section 3.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref103"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>103<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn104</dt><dd id="ftn104"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12407&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Directive on the Administration of Required Training</em></a>, Section 5. 1.5
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref104"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>104<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn105</dt><dd id="ftn105"><p>
         “Court” refers to any external body that is legally mandated to order the withholding of an employee's salary (for example, a Family Court or the Canada Revenue Agency) or payments to employees (for example, the Canadian Human Rights Commission).
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref105"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>105<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn106</dt><dd id="ftn106"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15781&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Financial Management of Pay Administration</em></a>, Section 6.3.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref106"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>106<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn107</dt><dd id="ftn107"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tbs-sct.gc.ca/mrrs-sgrr/about-apropos/instructions-consignes/profil-eng.asp#Toc231015417">Profile of Government of Canada Internal Services</a>, Section 3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref107"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>107<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn108</dt><dd id="ftn108"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19855&amp;section=text#appB"><em>Directive on the Management of Expenditures on Travel, Hospitality and Conferences</em></a>, Appendix B – Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref108"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>108<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn109</dt><dd id="ftn109"><p>
         Publiservice, Receiver General website
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref109"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>109<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn110</dt><dd id="ftn110"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15782&amp;section=text#cha8"><em>Directive on Claims and</em> Ex Gratia <em>Payments</em></a>, Section 8.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref110"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>110<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn111</dt><dd id="ftn111"><p><em><a href="http://www.justice.gc.ca/eng/abt-apd/index.html">Department of Justice</a> Canada</em> website
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref111"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>111<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn112</dt><dd id="ftn112"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15781&amp;section=text#cha8"><em>Directive on Financial Management of Pay Administration</em></a>, Section 8.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref112"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>112<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn113</dt><dd id="ftn113"><p><em><a href="http://www.justice.gc.ca/eng/abt-apd/index.html">Department of Justice</a> Canada</em> website
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref113"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>113<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn114</dt><dd id="ftn114"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/page-1.html#h-2"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a>, section 2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref114"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>114<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn115</dt><dd id="ftn115"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.1.4
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref115"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>115<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn116</dt><dd id="ftn116"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/page-1.html#h-2"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a>, section 2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref116"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>116<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn117</dt><dd id="ftn117"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref117"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>117<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn118</dt><dd id="ftn118"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.1"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref118"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>118<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn119</dt><dd id="ftn119"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref119"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>119<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn120</dt><dd id="ftn120"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.7"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.7
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref120"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>120<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn121</dt><dd id="ftn121"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.4"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.4
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref121"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>121<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn122</dt><dd id="ftn122"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17061&amp;section=text#sec6.2"><em>Directive on Expenditure Initiation and Commitment Control</em></a>, Section 6.2.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref122"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>122<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn123</dt><dd id="ftn123"><p><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-438/page-2.html#docCont"><em>Accountable Advances Regulations</em></a>, paragraph 6(3)(<em>b</em>)
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref123"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>123<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn124</dt><dd id="ftn124"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15789&amp;section=text#sec6.6"><em>Directive on Accountable Advances</em></a>, Section 6.6
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref124"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>124<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn125</dt><dd id="ftn125"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15790&amp;section=text#sec6.3"><em>Directive on Account Verification</em></a>, Section 6.3
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref125"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>125<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn126</dt><dd id="ftn126"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/manuels-manuals/chap4/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Manual</em>—Chapter 4: “Standard Payment System (SPS) and Departments”</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref126"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>126<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn127</dt><dd id="ftn127"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=104&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_4"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Section 1.4.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref127"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>127<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn128</dt><dd id="ftn128"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref128"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>128<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn129</dt><dd id="ftn129"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=104&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_4"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Section 1.4.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref129"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>129<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn130</dt><dd id="ftn130"><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14005&amp;section=text#cha5"><em>Policy on Financial Management Governance</em></a>, Sections 5.1.1 and 5.1.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref130"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>130<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn131</dt><dd id="ftn131"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref131"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>131<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn132</dt><dd id="ftn132"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref132"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>132<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn133</dt><dd id="ftn133"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=103&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_3"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Definitions
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref133"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>133<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn134</dt><dd id="ftn134"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=105&amp;hl=1&amp;lang=eng#tc-tm_2_2"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Section 2.2.2
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref134"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>134<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn135</dt><dd id="ftn135"><p><a href="http://publiservice.gc.ca/services/icpsss-spicsn/crs/intro-e.html">Central Removal Service</a> website
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref135"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>135<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn136</dt><dd id="ftn136"><p><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?sid=105&amp;lang=eng"><em>National Joint Council (NJC) Relocation Directive</em></a>, Section 2.1.1
    </p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref136"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>136<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote ftn137</dt><dd id="ftn137"><p><a href="http://publiservice.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/rg/manuels-manuals/chap4/index-eng.html"><em>Receiver General Manual</em>—Chapter 4: “Standard Payment System (SPS) and Departments”</a></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#ftnref137"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>137<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd></dl></aside><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small"></p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>