<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Appendix A: Examples of Acceptable Network and Device Use (Non-Exhaustive List)</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=32707", title: "Appendix A: Examples of Acceptable Network and Device Use (Non-Exhaustive List)"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=32707&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2022-05-03",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Appendix A: Examples of Acceptable Network and Device Use (Non-Exhaustive List)</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="chaAppendix A">Appendix A. Examples of Acceptable Network and  Device Use (non-exhaustive list)</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.1">A.1 Effective Date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.1</span>These take effect on April 1, 2020.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.2</span>These replace Appendix B: Acceptable Use  (non-exhaustive list of examples) of the Policy on Acceptable Network and  Device Use (October 1, 2013).</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.1">A.1 Examples</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.1</span>These examples provide details in support  of requirement 4.4.3.15.1 of the Directive on Service and Digital.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2</span>Open  access to the Internet, including Government of Canada and external Web 2.0  tools and services, can assist authorized individuals to conduct the business  of government more efficiently and effectively. The acceptable use of  Government of Canada electronic networks, devices and internal and external Web  2.0 tools and services support public servants in their work duties, enhance  collaboration and networking with their peers, augment professional development  opportunities and enable limited and reasonable personal use during work hours.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3</span>As  well, informing users of expected behaviours when using networks, devices and  Government of Canada and external Web 2.0 tools and services will help them to  protect against potential confidentiality or privacy breaches and to comply  with the Policy on Government Security, the Policy on Communications and  Federal Identity, the Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector, and other  related Treasury Board policies and departmental codes of conduct and policies.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.4</span>The  following are non-exhaustive lists of examples of acceptable use of internal  and external Web 2.0 tools and services that could be conducted via Government  of Canada electronic networks and devices.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5</span>Work-related and Professional Development  Activities
     <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.1</span>Conduct consultations within the federal government via  internal wikis and forums to support the development of policies and programs;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.2</span>Share knowledge and  information intra- or inter-departmentally to support planning and  decision-making or facilitate project collaboration;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.3</span>Perform research  through  accessing online reports, presentations, and data-sets;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.4</span>Watch online broadcasts  of work-related content, such as a parliamentary committee meeting via ParlVU;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.5</span>Remain up-to-date with  official announcements published on social media platforms by federal  departments and agencies, provincial or municipal governments, or international  jurisdictions or organizations;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.6</span>Document corporate  knowledge on Government of Canada wikis to facilitate employee orientation and  knowledge transfer;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.7</span>Participate in a video  or audio conference with colleagues or clients from other organizations or  jurisdictions through tools such as Skype or Google Hangouts;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.8</span>Develop and share code  repositories in collaboration with departments, other jurisdictions and private  sector organizations via code sharing tools such as GitHub;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.9</span>Leverage expertise from  across government by creating or participating in online communities of  interest on topics of shared professional interest such as #w2p (Web  2.0Practitioners community);</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.10</span>Access  or share  unclassified information through cloud-based tools such as Slide-Share;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.11"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.11</span>Collaborate on joint  initiatives and projects, via open discussions or closed groups as appropriate,  with other departments and levels of government through the use of wikis,  professional networking applications, internal tools such as GCdocs or external  cloud-based tools such as Google Docs;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.12"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.12</span>Maintain an up-to-date  profile on professional networking sites such as Linkedin;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.13"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.13</span>Follow thought leaders  and government officials on blogs or micro-blog such as Twitter;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.14"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.14</span>Tweet, re-tweet or share  links to professional activities and events, or interesting and relevant  articles;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.15"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.15</span>Read, contribute to, or  edit articles in work-related wikis, online forums or discussion groups;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.16"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.16</span>Discuss professional  issues or participate in professional associations via online forums or social  networking sites;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.17"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.17</span>Participate in online  professional training activities (e.g. webcasts, online learning products via  CSPS, podcasts);</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.18"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.18</span>Find a colleague or  client's contact information or directions to a meeting;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.19"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.19</span>Make arrangements for work-related travel, including booking  tickets and searching for information about accommodations via Government of  Canada or third-party travel review services; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.5.20"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.5.20</span>Complete an online job  application or participate in an online interview.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6</span>Examples of limited personal use that is  conducted on personal time, that is not for financial gain, that does not incur any additional costs for the  department, and that does not interfere with the conduct of business include:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.1</span>Search for information online;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.2</span>Keep up-to-date with  news and current events;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.3</span>Subscribe to Web feeds  (such as RSS) ; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.4</span>Get directions for a  trip or search for addresses and contact information;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.5</span>Make personal travel  arrangements;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.6</span>Post or read  ratings/reviews of products or services or make online purchases;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.7</span>Check the weather  forecast;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.8</span>Confirm bus schedule  information;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.9</span>Pay bills or conduct  personal banking online;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.10</span>Read or contribute to  online forums, blogs, discussion groups, or wikis on topics of personal  interest;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.11"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.11</span>Update a personal blog,  micro-blog, social networking page, or Web page that is for non-commercial  purposes or does not otherwise constitute Unacceptable Use as per Appendix D;  and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.6.12"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.6.12</span>Visit social networking  sites to connect with family and friends.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small"></p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>