<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Directive on Access to Information Requests" documentID="18310" versionID="11" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="s:\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date"><clauses><clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on July 13, 2022.</clause><clause anchor="1.2">This directive replaces the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32732"><em>Interim Directive on the  Administration of the Access to Information Act</em></a> dated May 5, 2016.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities"><clauses><clause anchor="2.1">This directive is issued pursuant to section 70(1)(c)  of the <em>Access  to Information Act</em> and as specified in section 2.2 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a>. </clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="Objectives and expected results"><clauses><clause anchor="3.1">In addition to the objectives indicated in section 3  of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy  on Access to Information</em></a> the  objective of this directive is to establish consistent practices and procedures  for processing requests for access to government records made under the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a> and for  publishing summaries of completed requests.</clause><clause anchor="3.2">The expected results indicated in section 3 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a> apply to this directive.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="Requirements"><clauses><clause anchor="4.1">Heads of government institutions, or their delegates,  are responsible for:
	  
	 <section><header><h3>Exercising discretion </h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.1">Exercising  discretion under Part 1 of the Act in a fair, reasonable and impartial manner  after:
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.1.1">Considering  the purpose of the Act, which is to enhance the accountability and transparency  of federal institutions in order to promote an open and democratic society and  to enable public debate on the conduct of those institutions;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.1.2">Considering  the core principle of the Act that government information should be available  to the public, subject to limited and specific exceptions;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.1.3">Considering  all relevant factors for and against disclosure, the relevant provisions of the  Act, as well as applicable jurisprudence;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.1.4">Consulting  with other government institutions and third parties, where necessary, as provided  in the Act; and</clause><clause anchor="4.1.1.5">Reviewing  the information contained in records.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Access to information training</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.2">Ensuring  that employees of government institutions and officials who have functional or  delegated responsibility for the administration of the Act receive training in  accordance with Appendix B: Mandatory Procedures for Access to Information  Training.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.3">Documenting  the completion of training in accordance with Appendix B: Mandatory Procedures  for Access to Information Training.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Eligibility of the requester</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.4">Establishing  procedures to:
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.4.1">Confirm  that the requester is a Canadian citizen, permanent resident, an individual present  in Canada, or an authorized representative of a corporation present in Canada and  therefore has the right to make a request under Part 1 of the Act.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.4.2">Confirm  the identity of the requester when the requester seeks access to records  involving their personal information; or that consent  to disclose personal information was obtained by a requester making an access  to information request on behalf of another individual. </clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Informal processing</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.5">Determining  whether it is appropriate to respond to a request on an informal basis,  recognizing that the Act is intended to complement existing procedures for  obtaining government information and is not intended to limit the type of  information that is otherwise available to the public. </clause><clause anchor="4.1.6">Proceeding  with treating a request informally only upon receipt of written consent from  the requester who has been informed that only formal requests are subject to  the provisions of Part 1 of the <em>Access to  Information Act, </em>including  legislative timelines and the right to complain.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Acknowledging requests</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.7">Providing  the requester with:
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.7.1">Acknowledgement  of receipt of the request; </clause><clause anchor="4.1.7.2">Receipt  of the application fee;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.7.3">The  legislative due date for the response; </clause><clause anchor="4.1.7.4">The  contact information of the appropriate officer or office within the institution  where questions and further clarifications may be addressed; </clause><clause anchor="4.1.7.5">Notification  of the right to complain to the Information Commissioner; and,</clause><clause anchor="4.1.7.6">A copy of the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/supporting-tool-access-information-personal-information-requests-principles-assisting-requesters.html"><em>Principles for Assisting Requesters</em></a>, or a link to the Principles  online.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Duty to assist</h3><h3><span class="mrgn-rght-lg">Protecting the identity of requesters</span></h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.8">Limiting  the use or disclosure of information that could directly or indirectly lead to  the identification of a requester to a need to know basis or when authorized by  the <em>Privacy Act.</em></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Interpretation and clarification of  requests</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.9">Adopting  a broad interpretation of an access request and communicating promptly with the  requester when necessary to clarify the request. </clause><clause anchor="4.1.10">Assisting the requester in clarifying a request where  it would result in the requester receiving more complete, accurate, or timely  access.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.11">Documenting the wording of a clarified request as  agreed to by the requester, and the date of the revision when a request has been  clarified or its wording altered.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Access to record in format requested</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.12">Providing the records in the format requested by the requester, including  machine-readable and reusable formats, when privacy, confidentiality and  security considerations would not be compromised and when it would not be  unreasonable to do so.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Onsite examination</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.13">When  a copy of the record cannot be made available, providing an appropriate  location and time convenient both for the institution and the requester, for  the requester to examine the record.
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.13.1">The  location must meet government security requirements and be reasonably  accessible to the requester.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.13.2">If  personal information is involved, privacy requirements must also be considered.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Language of access</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.14">Providing the requested records in  the language in which they exist, or if the requester has requested access in a  particular official language, providing the requested records if the records  already exist in that language.
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.14.1"> Should the requester seek the  records in the official language different from which they currently exist, preparing  and providing a translation of records if the head of the institution considers  translation of the record to be in the public interest.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Accessible format for requesters</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.15">Providing  the requested record in an accessible format requested by the requester if the  record already exists in that format or, converting the record to the requested  format if it is necessary to enable the requester to exercise their right of  access, and reasonable to do so.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Processing requests</h3><h3><span class="mrgn-rght-lg">Use of prescribed platforms</span></h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.16">Receiving  requests using the prescribed platforms listed in Appendix E: Prescribed  Platforms for Receiving and Processing Access to Information Requests.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.17">Processing  requests using the prescribed platforms, listed in Appendix E: Prescribed  Platforms for Receiving and Processing Access to Information Requests, when  platforms have been prescribed.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Tracking system </h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.18">Establishing  and maintaining an internal management system to track: 
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.18.1">The  processing of access requests;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.18.2">Consultation  requests; </clause><clause anchor="4.1.18.3">Complaints; </clause><clause anchor="4.1.18.4">Reports,  recommendations, and orders by the Information Commissioner; and</clause><clause anchor="4.1.18.5">Reviews  by the courts.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Documentation</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.19">Documenting the processing of requests by placing on  file all documents that support decisions under Part 1 of the  Act, including communications where factors considered when exercising  discretion are discussed,  recommendations are given, rationales are provided and decisions are made. </clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Control of records </h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.20">Determining, in a manner consistent with jurisprudence  and considering any Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat (TBS) guidance,  whether the records are under the control of the government institution. </clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Declining to act on a request</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.21">Making  every reasonable effort to assist the requester in accordance with section  4(2.1) of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and 4.1.9 and 4.1.10 of this Directive before seeking the Information  Commissioner’s approval to decline to act on a request.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.22">Exercising  the discretion to decline to act on a request under Part 1 of the Act in  accordance with section 4.1.1 of this Directive.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.23">Seeking  the written approval of the Information Commissioner in the form and with the  supporting documentation required by the Information Commissioner. 
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.23.1">Giving  written notice to the requester of the suspension of the time period for responding  to the request and the reasons for the suspension, at the same time as the  institution communicates with the Information Commissioner to obtain the  Commissioner’s approval to decline to act on the request.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.23.2">If  the Information Commissioner does not give approval for the institution to  decline to act on a request, notifying the requester in writing of the  Information Commissioner’s decision and the resumption of the time period for  responding to the request.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.23.3">If  the Information Commissioner gives approval for the institution to decline to  act on a request, notifying the requester in writing of the decision to decline  to act on the request and the reasons for doing so. </clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Extension of the time limit</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.24">Assessing,  without undue delay, each access request received under Part 1 of the Act to  determine if an extension is needed for processing the request.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.25">Notifying  the requester of the extension within 30 days of the receipt of the request.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.26">Notifying  the requester of their right to complain to the Information Commissioner in  respect to extension of the time limit.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.27">Reporting on the number of and reasons for  extensions in the institution’s annual report to Parliament. </clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Length of extension</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.28">Ensuring that  any extension taken is as short as possible and can be reasonably justified.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.29">Establishing  a process that would ensure justifications for extensions are documented and  supported by evidence.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Notice of extension to Information Commissioner</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.30">Notifying  the Information Commissioner if the extension is for more than 30 days, in  accordance with subsection 9(2) of the Act. </clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Limiting the need for inter-institutional consultations</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.31">Undertaking  inter-institutional consultation only when:
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.31.1">The  processing institution requires more information for the proper exercise of  discretion to withhold information; or</clause><clause anchor="4.1.31.2">The  processing institution intends to disclose potentially sensitive information.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="4.1.32">Ensuring  that consultation requests from other federal government institutions are  processed with the same priority as access to information requests.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Exceptions to disclosure</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.33">Applying the exclusion and exemption provisions  of the Act in accordance with:
    <ul><li>the principle that government information  should be available to the public, subject to limited and specific exceptions; </li><li>the purpose of the Act; and </li><li>relevant jurisprudence and TBS guidance. </li></ul><p>Appendix C: Classification of Exemptions lists the exemptions and  indicates whether they are based on a class test or an injury test, and whether  they are discretionary or mandatory in nature.</p></clause><clause anchor="4.1.34">Citing  exemptions and exclusions invoked on records, provided under Part 1 of the Act,  on each page, unless doing so would reveal the exempted information or cause  the injury upon which the exemption is based to materialize.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.35">Clearly  identifying the redacted material in a manner that is evident on the individual  record.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.36">Recognizing  that lack of relevance is not a ground for exemption, ensuring that  non-relevant information contained in a record is disclosed unless an exemption  applies or consent is obtained from the requester to not disclose non-relevant  information.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Giving access</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.37">Providing  written notice to the requester of whether access is being granted.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.38">Providing  access to the records or part thereof or notifying the  requester if access is refused. </clause><clause anchor="4.1.39">Providing,  as appropriate, general information of a contextual nature in response to an  access request to help the requester understand the record in cases where the  record itself may provide misleading information and the access to information  analyst has been informed by the office of primary interest that the  information contained in the record may be misleading. 
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.39.1">For  greater certainty, government institutions are not obligated to explain all  records or complex information being disclosed when responding to an access  request.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="4.1.40">Notifying  requesters of their right to complain to the Information Commissioner in  respect of matters relating to requesting and obtaining access to records under  Part 1 of the Act.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Waiver or refund of fees</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.41">Exercising  discretion concerning the waiver or refund of the application fee in accordance  with section 4.1.1.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.42">Refunding  the application fee if the request is processed as an informal request or if  the Information Commissioner gives  their approval for the institution to decline to act on the request.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Timely disclosure of records</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.43">Ensuring that any internal process  relating to the disclosure of records under Part 1 of the Act does not delay  the processing of the request. </clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Considering other means of making government information  accessible</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.44">Regularly  reviewing the nature of requests received under Part 1 of the Act and assessing  the feasibility of making frequently requested types of information available  by other means.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Allegations of an obstruction of the right of access</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.45">Establishing  internal procedures to address alleged or suspected obstructions related to the  right of access under Part 1 of the Act and the Information Commissioner’s  duties and functions, which are outlined in sections 67 (1) and 67.1(1) of the  Act. Procedures should outline measures for:
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.45.1">Documenting  and reporting any suspected falsification, concealment,  mutilation or improper destruction of records as described in section  67.1(1) or any obstruction of the Information Commissioner’s duties and  functions as defined in 67(1) immediately to the head of the government  institution;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.45.2">Investigating  any allegation of falsification, concealment, mutilation or improper  destruction of records; or any obstruction of the Information  Commissioner’s duties and functions as described in 67(1); and</clause><clause anchor="4.1.45.3">Reporting  a suspected contravention to the institutions’ security officials for their referral  to law enforcement agencies as appropriate.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Publishing summaries of completed access to information  requests</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.46">Publishing  summaries of completed access to information requests to the Government of  Canada Open Government portal within 30 calendar days after the end of each  month, in accordance with Appendix D: Mandatory Procedures for Publishing  Summaries of Completed Access to Information Requests. </clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Responding to informal requests for completed Access to  Information requests</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.47">Establishing  service standards for responding to informal requests for completed access to  information requests.</clause><clause anchor="4.1.48">When  an informal request is received for a previously completed access to information  request, providing the previously provided information to the requester within  established service timelines.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Monitoring and reporting</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.1.49">Monitoring and reporting on the  requirements of this directive as specified in the <em>Policy on Access to Information</em>. </clause></clauses></section></clause><clause anchor="4.2">Employees of government institutions are responsible  for:
	 		   
	  <section><header><h3>Informal access</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.2.1">Recommending  to the head or the delegate, when appropriate, that information requested under  Part 1 of the Act be disclosed informally.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Complete, accurate and timely responses</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.2.2">Making  every reasonable effort to locate and retrieve requested records under the control of the government institution. </clause><clause anchor="4.2.3">Ensuring  searches for records are comprehensive and consider both the letter and the spirit  of the request. </clause><clause anchor="4.2.4">Referring  questions about whether records are under the control of the government  institution to Access to Information and Privacy (ATIP) officials with  delegated authority for their determination. </clause><clause anchor="4.2.5">Advising  ATIP officials at an early stage if a request cannot be responded to within the  legislated 30-day timeframe.</clause><clause anchor="4.2.6">Making  every reasonable effort to respond to requests within the timelines prescribed  in the Act, including extensions taken in accordance with the Act.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Recommendations</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.2.7">Providing  recommendations and contextual information to inform the head of the government  institution, or their delegate, about possible exemptions or exclusions applicable  to the records requested under Part 1 of the Act, taking into account the  purpose of the Act.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Contracts and agreements</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.2.8">Establishing  measures to support the right of public access to information when entering into  contracts, arrangements and agreements.</clause></clauses></section><section><header><h3>Reporting suspected obstruction of the right of access</h3></header><clauses><clause anchor="4.2.9">Following  departmental procedures to report any suspected obstruction of the right of  access.</clause></clauses></section></clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="Roles of other government organizations"><clauses><clause anchor="5.1">The roles and responsibilities of government  institutions with respect to this directive are identified in Section 5 of the <em>Policy on Access to Information</em>.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="6" title="Application"><clauses><clause anchor="6.1">This directive applies as described in section 6 of the <em>Policy on Access to Information</em>.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="7" title="References"><clauses><clause anchor="7.1">Legislation 
    <ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SI-83-113/"><em>Access to Information Act  Heads of Government Institutions Designation Order</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-83-507/index.html"><em>Access to Information  Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-5/"><em>Canada Evidence Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/I-21/"><em>Interpretation Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/L-7.7/"><em>Library and Archives of  Canada Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/"><em>Official Languages Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-83-508/"><em>Privacy Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-31.9/"><em>Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/S-8.4/index.html"><em>Service Fees Act</em></a></li></ul></clause><clause anchor="7.2">Related policy instruments
    <ul><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16577"><em>Directive on Identity Management</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32502"><em>Directive on Charging and  Special Financial Authorities</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32601"><em>Directive on Service and  Digital</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to  Information</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=30683"><em>Policy on Communications and  Federal Identity</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603"><em>Policy on Service and Digital</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578"><em>Policy on Government Security</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=23601"><em>Standard on Web Accessibility</em></a></li></ul></clause><clause anchor="7.3">Related guidance
    <ul><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/access-information-manual.html">Access to Information Manual</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information-privacy-notices.html">Access to Information and Privacy Implementation Notices</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/delegation-under-access-information-act-privacy-act.html">Delegation under the Access to Information Act  and the Privacy Act</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/info-source-decentralized-publishing-requirements.html">Info-Source  Decentralized Publishing Requirements</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/access-information-privacy/access-information/supporting-tool-access-information-personal-information-requests-principles-assisting-requesters.html">Principles for  Assisting Requesters</a></li></ul></clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="8" title="Enquiries"><clauses><clause anchor="8.1">Members of the public  may contact <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html" title="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/tbs-sct/cmn/contact-eng.asp#enquiries">Treasury  Board of Canada Secretariat (TBS) Public Enquiries</a> regarding any questions about this directive. </clause><clause anchor="8.2">Employees of federal institutions may contact their <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/ap/atip-aiprp/coord-eng.asp">Access to Information and Privacy Coordinator</a> regarding any questions  about this directive. </clause><clause anchor="8.3">Access to Information and Privacy Coordinators may contact the <a href="mailto:ippd-dpiprp@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Access to Information  Policy and Performance Division</a> regarding any questions  about this directive </clause></clauses></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix  A: Definitions"><dl><dt><strong>access to information training (<span lang="fr"><em>formation en matière  d’accès 	à l’information</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>All activities that serve to increase awareness about  access to information, including formal training, discussion groups,  conferences, Access to Information and Privacy community meetings, shared  learning among colleagues, on-the-job training, special projects, job  shadowing, and communications activities that promote learning in the areas identified  in the Appendix B of this directive.</dd><dt><strong>class test (<span lang="fr"><em>critère objectif</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>A test that objectively identifies the categories of information or documents to which certain exemption provisions of the  Act can be applied. The following sections of the Act are based on a class  test: 13(1), 16(1)(a), 16(1)(b), 16(3), 16.1, 16.2, 16.3, 16.4, 16.5, 16.6, 18(a),  18.1, 19(1), 20(1)(a), 20(1)(b), 20(1)(b.1), 20.1, 20.2, 20.4, 21(1), 22.1, 23,  23.1, 24 and 26.</dd><dt><strong>discretionary exemption (<span lang="fr"><em>exception  discrétionnaire</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>An exemption provision of the Act that  contains the phrase "may refuse to disclose." The exemptions set out  in the following sections of the Act are discretionary: 14, 15(1), 16(1),  16(2), 16.3, 17, 18, 18.1, 21(1), 22, 22.1, 23, 23.1 and 26.</dd><dt><strong>every reasonable effort (<span lang="fr"><em>tous les efforts  raisonnables</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>A level of effort that a fair and reasonable person  would expect or would find acceptable.</dd><dt><strong>informal request (<span lang="fr"><em>demande  informelle</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>A  request for information made to the ATIP office of a government institutions  that is not made or processed under the Act.   There are no deadlines for responding.   In addition, the requester has no statutory right to complain to the Information  Commissioner.</dd><dt><strong>injury test (<span lang="fr"><em>critère subjectif</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>A test to determine the reasonable expectation of  probable harm that must be met for certain exemption provisions of  the Act to apply. The following sections of the Act are based on an injury  test: 14, 15(1), 16(1)(c), 16(1)(d), 16(2), 17, 18(b), 18(c), 18(d), 20(1)(c),  20(1)(d) and 22.</dd><dt><strong>mandatory exemption (<span lang="fr"><em>exception  obligatoire</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>An exemption provision of the Act that  contains the phrase "shall refuse to disclose." The exemptions set  out in the following sections of the Act are mandatory: 13(1), 16(3), 16.1,  16.2, 16.4, 16.5, 16.6, 19(1), 20(1), 20.1, 20.2, 20.4 and 24.</dd><dt><strong>tracking  system (<span lang="fr"><em>système de suivi</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>A case management  system used in ATIP offices to track access requests and document their  processing.</dd></dl><p>Additional definitions are listed in <a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453&amp;section=text#appA">Appendix  A of the <em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a>.</p></appendix><appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix  B:  Mandatory Procedures for Access to  Information Training"><p>This Appendix provides guidance  related to training in the application of the Act that all employees of  government institutions should receive. </p><appendix anchor="B.1"><title>Effective date</title><clauses><clause anchor="B.1.1">These procedures take effect on July 13,  2022.</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2 ">These  procedures were previously set out in <em>Appendix B: Access to Information Awareness</em> in the <em>Interim Directive on the Administration of the Access to  Information Act</em> effective May 5, 2016.</clause></clauses></appendix><appendix anchor="B.2"><title>Procedures  applicable to all employees</title><clauses><clause anchor="B.2.1">These  procedures provide details on the  requirements set out in section 4.1.2 of the <em>Directive on Access to  Information Requests</em>. All employees of Government institutions must receive  training on their obligations under the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, the application  of the Act and related Treasury Board policies. The training should cover the  following:
    <clauses><clause anchor="B.2.1.1">The  purpose of the Act; </clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.2">The  applicable definitions;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.3"> Employees’ responsibilities under the Act,  including the principles for    assisting requesters; </clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.4">Delegation, exemption decisions  and the exercise of discretion; </clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.5">Employees’ obligation to make every reasonable effort  to locate and retrieve all corresponding records according to the letter and  the spirit of the request;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.6">The requirement  to provide complete, accurate and timely responses;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.7">The  complaint process, including the Information Commissioner’s order-making power,  and review by the courts;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.8"><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-10.html#h-28">Section 67.1 and 67.1(1) of the Act</a>, which make it an offence to obstruct the  Information Commissioner or the right of access, and which provides for  criminal sanctions;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.1.9">Specific institutional  policies and processes relating to the administration of the Act, including  policies on information management. </clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="B.2.2">All employees of government institutions who have functional or delegated  responsibility for the administration of the Act and the Regulations must  receive training that covers the items listed above and in addition:
    <clauses><clause anchor="B.2.2.1">The provisions concerning the  extension of time limits; fees; exemptions and exclusions; the third-party  notification process; the procedures and criteria respecting the authority to  seek the Information Commissioner’s approval to decline to act on a request; and  the language, format and method of access;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.2.2">The provisions of Part 2 of the Act  and how they relate to Part 1;</clause><clause anchor="B.2.2.3">Public Reporting  requirements, including annual reports to Parliament; and</clause><clause anchor="B.2.2.4">The role of the  Information Commissioner, the Privacy Commissioner, and the Parliamentary  Standing Committees in relation to the Act.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></appendix></appendix><appendix anchor="c" title="Appendix  C:  Classification of Exemptions"><p>The table below lists all exemptions under the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and indicates  whether they are based on a class test or an injury  test and whether they are mandatory or discretionary. The descriptions are  paraphrased and should be used as a memory aid only. For more detail, please  consult the relevant section of the Act.</p><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><thead><tr><th scope="col">Exemption</th><th scope="col">Short Description of the Exemption</th><th scope="col">Mandatory</th><th scope="col">Discretionary</th><th scope="col">Class</th><th scope="col">Injury</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="6"><section class="wb-fnote"><h2 id="table1-fn" class="wb-inv">Table 1 Notes</h2><dl><dt>Table 1 Note 1</dt><dd id="table1-fn1"><p>The exemption can only be claimed by the government institutions named in the provision.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table1-fn1-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 1 note </span>*<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Table 1 Note 2</dt><dd id="table1-fn2"><p>Where discretion is authorized.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table1-fn2-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 1 note </span>**<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd></dl></section></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Subsection 13(1)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained in confidence from: 
      <ol class="alpha-lower"><li>the government of a foreign state; </li><li>an international organization of states; </li><li>the government of a province; </li><li>a municipal or regional government  established by or pursuant to an act of the legislature of a province or an institution of such a government; or </li><li>an  Aboriginal government. </li></ol></td><td>yes </td><td>no<sup id="table1-fn2-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>**</a></sup></td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Section 14</a></th><td><a href="#_Federal-provincial_affairs">Federal - provincial affairs</a> Access may be refused as it could be expected to be injurious to the Government of Canada’s conduct of    federal-provincial affairs. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Subsection 15(1)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as it could be expected to be injurious to the conduct of international affairs; the defence of Canada or any state allied or associated with Canada; or Canada’s efforts to detect, prevent or suppress subversive or hostile activities. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Paragraph 16(1)(a)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as it was obtained or prepared by an investigative body (as per regulation) in the course of an investigation regarding: detecting, preventing or suppressing crime, enforcing any law of Canada or a province; or activities suspected of constituting threats to Canada’s security as set out in the <em>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</em>.</td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Paragraph 16(1)(b)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as the records contain investigative techniques or plans for specific lawful investigations. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Paragraph 16(1)(c)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as disclosure could be expected to be injurious to the enforcement of any law of Canada or a province or the conduct of lawful investigations. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Paragraph 16(1)(d)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as disclosure could be expected to be injurious to the security of penal institutions. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Subsection 16(2)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as the records contain information expected to aid in the commission of an offence. Includes, but is not limited to: information on criminal methods or techniques, technical information on weapons or potential weapons; or information on the vulnerabilities of buildings, structures or systems. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-2.html#h-339">Subsection 16(3)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police while performing policing services for a province or municipality. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 16.1</a><sup id="table1-fn1-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained or created by the Auditor General or Canada, the Commissioner of Official Languages, the Information Commissioner or the Privacy Commissioner during an investigation, examination or audit. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 16.2</a><sup id="table1-fn1a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained from or created by the Commissioner of Lobbying or on their behalf in the course of an investigation by the Commissioner. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 16.3</a><sup id="table1-fn1b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained or created by an individual who, in performing their functions under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/E-2.01/"><em>Canada Elections Act</em></a>, is conducting an investigation, examination, or review. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 16.4</a><sup id="table1-fn1c-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained or created by or on behalf of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner in the course of an investigation of a disclosure or an investigation commenced under section 33 of the <em>Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</em> (PSDPA); or <br />
      Received by a conciliator while attempting to reach a settlement of a complaint filed under the subsection 19.1(1) of the PSDPA </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 16.5</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it was created for the purpose of making a disclosure or in the course of an investigation into a disclosure under the PSDPA. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 16.6</a><sup id="table1-fn1d-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it was obtained or created by the Secretariat of the National Security and Intelligent Committee of Parliamentarians or on its behalf in the course of fulfilling its mandate. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 17</a></th><td>Access may be refused as disclosure would reasonably be expected to threaten the safety of individuals. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 18(a)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain trade secrets or financial, commercial, scientific or technical information that belongs to the Government of Canada of substantial value. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 18(b)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain information expected to prejudice the competitive position of a government institution or interfere with contractual or other negotiations. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 18(c)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain scientific or technical information obtained through research by an employee of a government institution, the disclosure of which could deprive the employee of priority of publication. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 18(d)</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain information expected to: materially injure the financial interests of a government institution; materially injure the ability of the Government of Canada to manage the economy of Canada; or result in an undue benefit to any person, including information relating to the operation of financial institutions, or the sale of property, among others.</td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 18.1</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain trade secrets or financial, commercial, scientific or technical information which belongs to and has been treated as confidential by: 
      <ul><li>Canada Post Corporation </li><li>Export Development Canada </li><li>Public Sector Pension Investment Board </li><li>VIA Rail Canada Inc. </li></ul></td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Subsection 19(1)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it is personal information as defined in Section 3 of the <em>Privacy Act</em>. </td><td>yes </td><td>no<sup id="table1-fn2a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>**</a></sup></td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 20(1)(a)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it contains trade secrets of a third party. </td><td>yes </td><td>no<sup id="table1-fn2b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>**</a></sup></td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 20(1)(b)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it is confidential financial, commercial, scientific or technical information supplied to a government institution by a third party and is consistently treated as confidential by the third party. </td><td>yes </td><td>no<sup id="table1-fn2c-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>**</a></sup></td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 20(1)(b.1)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it was supplied in confidence to a government institution by a third party in order to prepare, maintain, test or implement emergency management plans and which concerns the vulnerabilities of the third party’s structures, systems, or networks. </td><td>yes </td><td>no<sup id="table1-fn2d-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>**</a></sup></td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 20(1)(c)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it could reasonably be expected to cause material financial loss or gain to a third party, or could reasonably be expected to prejudice the competitive position of the third party. </td><td>yes </td><td>no<sup id="table1-fn2e-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>**</a></sup></td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Paragraph 20(1)(d)</a></th><td>Information must be protected as it could reasonably be expected to interfere with contractual or other negotiations of a third party. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 20.1</a><sup id="table1-fn1e-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it is advice or information relating to investment that the Public Sector Pension Investment Board has obtained in confidence from a third party and has consistently treated in a confidential manner. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 20.2</a><sup id="table1-fn1f-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it is advice or information relating to investment that the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board has obtained in confidence from a third party and has consistently treated in a confidential manner. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 20.4</a><sup id="table1-fn1g-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>*</a></sup></th><td>Information must be protected as it has been consistently treated as confidential by the National Arts Centre Corporation that would reveal the terms of a contract for the services of a performing artist or the identity of a donor who has made a donation in confidence. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-3.html#docCont">Section 21</a> 
      (Government Operations) </th><td>Access may be refused as records contain information less than 20 years old and which is: 
      <ul><li>Advice or recommendations developed by or for a government institution or a minister; </li><li>Accounts of consultations or deliberations in which directors, officers or employees of a government institution, a minister or the minister’s staff participate; </li><li>Positions or plans developed for negotiations carried out on behalf of the Government of Canada; or </li><li>Plans relating to the management of personnel or the administration of a government institution that have not yet been put into operation. </li></ul></td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-4.html#docCont">Section 22</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain information relating to testing or auditing procedures or techniques if the disclosure would prejudice the use or results of particular tests or audits. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-4.html#docCont">Section 22.1</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records contain a draft report of an internal audit of a government institution or any related audit working paper if the record came into existence less than fifteen years before the request was made. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-4.html#docCont">Section 23</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records are subject to solicitor-client privilege. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-4.html#docCont">Section 23.1</a></th><td>Access may be refused as records are subject to the privilege set out in section 16.1 of the <em>Patent Act</em> or section 51.13 of the <em>Trade-marks Act</em>. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-4.html#docCont">Section 24</a></th><td>Information must be protected as disclosure is restricted as set out in Schedule II. </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr><tr><th scope="row"><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/page-4.html#docCont">Section 26</a></th><td> Access may be refused as records will be published within 90 days of the request or within the time necessary for printing or translating the material for the purpose of printing it. </td><td>no </td><td>yes </td><td>yes </td><td>no </td></tr></tbody></table></appendix><appendix anchor="D" title="Appendix D:  Mandatory Procedures for Publishing Summaries  of Completed Access to Information Requests"><appendix anchor="D.1"><title>Effective date</title><clauses><clause anchor="D.1.1">These procedures  take effect on July 13, 2022. </clause><clause anchor="D.1.2">These procedures  replace <em>Appendix E – Criteria for posting  summaries of completed access to information requests</em> of the <em>Interim Directive on the Administration of  the Access to Information Act</em>, dated May 5, 2016. </clause></clauses></appendix><appendix anchor="D.2"><title>Publishing summaries of completed  Access to Information request responses</title><clauses><clause anchor="D.2.1">These procedures  provide details on the  requirement set out in section 4.1.46 of the <em>Directive on Access to  Information Requests</em>. Institutions must:<strong></strong><clauses><clause anchor="D.2.1.1">Publish summaries of the  responses to completed Access to Information requests on the Open Government  portal within 30 calendar days after the end of each month. Institutions also must  report when there are no ATI requests to publish for a given month. </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.2">The entry for each summary must include the  following: 
        <clauses><clause anchor="D.2.1.2.1">The request number  assigned by the institution;
            </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.2.2">The year and month that the request was completed by the institution;
            </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.2.3">A description  of the request that reflects the final wording of the request after  clarification was obtained from the requester, where applicable. Provide the  information in a format that is understandable by Canadians, specifies  institutions and dates, and which uses key words. The description must not  include personal information or any other information that would be exempted or  excluded under the Act, or that could reveal a requester’s identity;
            </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.2.4">The  disposition of the request (i.e., all disclosed; disclosed in part; all  exempted; all excluded; or no records exist); and
            </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.2.5">The number of pages disclosed.
            </clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.3">Publish the summaries simultaneously in both official languages,  in accordance with the requirements of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/">Official Languages Act</a>.
        </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4">Do not publish summaries of the following types  of requests:
        <clauses><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.1">Requests made under the <em>Privacy Act</em>; 
          </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.2">Requests  made under the <em>Access to Information Act</em> that contain primarily personal information of the requester or that are  uniquely of interest to the requester; 
          </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.3">Requests  that were treated informally; 
          </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.4">Requests  that were transferred to another government institution;
          </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.5">Requests  that were abandoned; 
          </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.6">Requests where the head of an institution has applied subsection 10(2) of the <em>Access  to Information Act</em> and did not confirm nor deny the existence of records  relevant to an access to information request; or
          </clause><clause anchor="D.2.1.4.7">Requests where the head of institution has declined to  act pursuant to section 6.1. of the Act </clause></clauses></clause></clauses></clause></clauses></appendix><appendix anchor="D.3"><title>Standard on data elements for the  publication of completed access to information request responses</title><p>This standard provides  details on the requirements set out in subsection 4.1.47 of the <em>Directive  on Access to Information Requests</em>.</p><p>These  are the fields that institutions need to complete when publishing summaries of  completed requests.</p><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">1. Year</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>The year the request was completed by the government institutions</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>YYYY  (For example: 2020) </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional</th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">2. Month</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>The month that the request was completed by the government institution</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>The full name of the month the request was completed. For example, December (Note: An abbreviation of the month is not acceptable).</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional</th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">3. Request Number/Numéro de demande</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>The unique identifier assigned to the request by the institution</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>A-YYYY-##### :  For example A-2020-01234 </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional</th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">4. Request Description (English)</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>Provide a clear and concise description of    the completed request without identifying the requester or any other    potentially sensitive, personal or redacted information. The description    should be:
      <ul><li>Summarize the request in plain language that would make sense to Canadians;</li><li>Reflect the final request; </li><li>Contain useful key words;</li><li>Reference specific dates (e.g. ‘covering 2015-2019’ vs. covering the last five years) and</li><li>Refer to the specific institution (e.g. ‘all records from Fisheries and Oceans Canada’ vs. ‘all records from your institution’).</li></ul>
      Request terms, such as ‘please provide’ ‘a    copy of’ ‘or all documentation related to’; internal file or reference    numbers; and hyperlinks or web addresses should be removed</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>Alpha-numeric; Free text</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional </th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">5. Request    Summary (French)</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>Provide a clear and concise description of the completed request    without identifying the requester or any other potentially sensitive or    redacted information. The field data should be:
      <ul><li>Summarized    in plain language that would make sense to Canadians;</li><li>Be    updated as necessary to reflect changes to the initial request; </li><li>Contain    useful key words;</li><li>Reference    specific dates (e.g. ‘covering 2015-2019’ vs. covering the last five years)    and</li><li>Contain    specific references to the institution (e.g. ‘all records from Fisheries and    Oceans Canada’ vs. ‘all records from your institution’).</li></ul>
      Request terms, such as ‘please provide’ ‘a copy of ‘‘or all  documentation related to’; internal file or reference numbers; and hyperlinks or web addresses should be removed</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>Alpha-numeric; Free text</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional  </th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">6. Disposition</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>Indicate the request is whether the records    were all disclosed, disclosed in part, all exempted, all excluded, or if not    records exist.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>The status must be one of the five options:
      <ul><li>All disclosed</li><li>Disclosed in part </li><li>All exempted</li><li>All excluded </li><li>No records exist </li></ul></td></tr><tr><th scope="row"> Mandatory/ Optional</th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title</th><th scope="col">7. Number of Pages</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Description </th><td>The number of pages which were fully or partly provided to the    requester, or a value of 0 if no records were released to the requester.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Field Format</th><td>Numeric.  For example 0, 10 or 25 </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional </th><td>Mandatory</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row">Field Title </th><th scope="col">8. Additional Information (English)</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Description</th><td>Institutions can provide any additional information in this field in English.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Format Type</th><td>Free text</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Example</th><td>The records provided were the most recent versions.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional</th><td>Optional</td></tr></table><table class="table table-condensed table-bordered"><tr><th scope="row"> Field Title</th><th scope="col">9. Additional Information (French)</th></tr><tr><th scope="row">Description</th><td>Institutions can provide any additional    information in this field in French.</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Format Type</th><td>Free text</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Example</th><td>Les documents fournis comprennent les versions les plus récentes. </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Mandatory/ Optional  </th><td>Optional </td></tr></table></appendix></appendix><appendix anchor="E" title="Appendix E: Prescribed  Platforms for Receiving and Processing Access to Information Requests"><p>This  Appendix provides details on the requirements set out in section 4.1.16 and 4.1.17 of the <em>Directive on Access to Information Requests</em>. </p><appendix anchor="E.1"><title>Effective date</title><clauses><clause anchor="E.1.1">This list was updated on July 13, 2022.</clause></clauses></appendix><appendix anchor="E.2"><title>Prescribed  Platforms</title><clauses><clause anchor="E.2.1">Receiving requests
    <clauses><clause anchor="E.2.1.1">The prescribed platform is TBS’s ATIP Online.
      </clause><clause anchor="E.2.1.2">Requests can be received in alternate formats  such as email or paper.
      </clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="E.2.2">There is no prescribed platform for processing requests. However, enterprise  approved solutions are available through established contracting vehicles for  ATIP Request Processing Software Solutions
    </clause><clause anchor="E.2.3">In order to request an exception from the prescribed platforms, government  institutions must contact the <a href="mailto:ippd-dpiprp@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Information and  Privacy Policy Division</a> for further information.</clause></clauses></appendix></appendix></appendices></doc>