<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Directive on Automated Decision-Making" documentID="32592" versionID="4" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on April 1, 2019, with compliance required by no later than April 1, 2020.</clause>
        <clause anchor="1.2">
          This directive applies to all automated decision systems developed or procured after April 1, 2020.
                   
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="1.2.1">Existing automated decision systems developed or procured prior to June 24, 2025, will have until June 24, 2026 to comply with the new or updated requirements.</clause>
            <clause anchor="1.2.2">Agents of Parliament will have until June 24, 2026, to comply with the requirements.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="1.3">This directive will be reviewed every two years, and as determined by the Chief Information Officer of Canada.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="2.1">
          This directive is issued pursuant to the same authority indicated in section 2 of the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603">
            <em>Policy on Service and Digital</em>
          </a>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="Definitions">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="3.1">
          Definitions to be used in the interpretation of this directive are listed in 
          <a href="#appA">Appendix A</a>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Objectives and expected results">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="4.1">The objective of this directive is to ensure that automated decision systems are used in a manner that reduces risks to clients, departments and Canadian society, and leads to more efficient, accurate, consistent and interpretable decisions made pursuant to Canadian law.</clause>
        <clause anchor="4.2">
          The expected results of this directive as it applies to automated decision systems are as follows:
                   	
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.2.1">Decisions made by departments are data-driven and responsible, and comply with procedural fairness and due process requirements.</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.2">Impacts to administrative decisions are assessed and negative outcomes are reduced.</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.3">Data and information on the use of automated decision systems in departments are made available to the public, while protecting privacy, security and intellectual property.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Scope">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="5.1">This directive applies to any automated decision system in production used to make an administrative decision or a related assessment about a client.</clause>
        <clause anchor="5.2">This directive excludes automated decision systems used solely for research and experimentation purposes, and those operating in test environments.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Requirements">
      <p>The assistant deputy minister responsible for the program using the automated decision system, or any other senior official named by the deputy head, is responsible for:</p>
      <chapter anchor="6.1" title="Algorithmic impact assessment">
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="6.1.1">
            Completing, approving and publishing the final results of an 
            <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/digital-government-innovations/responsible-use-ai/algorithmic-impact-assessment.html">algorithmic impact assessment</a>
             in an accessible format on the 
            <a href="https://search.open.canada.ca/opendata/?collection=aia&amp;page=1&amp;sort=date_modified+desc">Open Government Portal</a>
             prior to the production of any automated decision system.
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="6.1.2">Applying the relevant requirements prescribed in Appendix C as determined by the algorithmic impact assessment.</clause>
          <clause anchor="6.1.3">Reviewing, approving, and updating the published algorithmic impact assessment on a scheduled basis, including when the functionality or scope of the automated decision system changes.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="6.2" title="Transparency">
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Providing notice before decisions</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.2.1">Providing notice through all service delivery channels in use that the decision will be made or assisted by an automated decision system, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
            <clause anchor="6.2.2">
              Providing notices prominently and in plain language.
                             
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="6.2.2.1">
                  Providing notices pursuant to the 
                  <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/canada-content-style-guide.html#toc5">Canada.ca Content Style Guide</a>
                  .
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Providing explanations after decisions</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.2.3">Providing a meaningful explanation to clients of how and why the decision was made, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Access to components</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.2.4">Determining the appropriate licence for software components, including consideration of open source software.</clause>
            <clause anchor="6.2.5">Obtaining and safeguarding all released versions of software components used for automated decision systems.</clause>
            <clause anchor="6.2.6">
              If using a proprietary licence, ensuring that:
                             
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="6.2.6.1">The department responsible for the automated decision system retains the right to access, test and monitor the automated decision system, including all released versions of proprietary software components, in case it is necessary for a specific audit, investigation, inspection, examination, enforcement action, or judicial proceeding, subject to safeguards against unauthorized disclosure.</clause>
                <clause anchor="6.2.6.2">As part of this access, the department responsible for the automated decision system retains the right to authorize external parties to review, test, monitor, and audit these components as necessary.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Documenting decisions</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.2.7">
              Documenting the decisions and assessments made or assisted by automated decision systems in accordance with the 
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32601">
                <em>Directive on Service and Digital</em>
              </a>
              , and in support of the testing (6.3.1), monitoring (6.3.2), data governance (6.3.6) and reporting requirements (6.5.1 and 6.5.2).
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="6.3" title="Quality assurance">
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Testing and monitoring outcomes</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.1">Before an automated decision system is in production, testing the data, information, and underlying model for accuracy, unintended biases and all factors that may unintentionally or unfairly impact the outcomes or violate human rights and freedoms.</clause>
            <clause anchor="6.3.2">Monitoring the outcomes of the automated decision system to safeguard against unintentional or unfair outcomes and to verify compliance with human rights obligations, departmental and program legislation, and this directive, on a scheduled basis.</clause>
            <clause anchor="6.3.3">
              Ensuring that testing and monitoring assesses human rights and is consistent with applicable legislation such as the 
              <em>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</em>
              , 
              <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>
              , and the 
              <em>United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples Act</em>
              .
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="6.3.4">
              Documenting client feedback, unexpected impacts, human overrides of the decision or assessment made by the system and other system failures as appropriate.
                             
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="6.3.4.1">Using findings from outcome monitoring and documented feedback, unexpected impacts and human overrides to identify issues and take corrective actions.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Data quality</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.5">
              Validating that the data used to train the automated decision system and the data input into the system are relevant, accurate, up-to-date, and in accordance with the 
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603">
                <em>Policy on Service and Digital</em>
              </a>
               and the 
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/ACTS/P-21/">
                <em>Privacy Act</em>
              </a>
              .
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Data governance</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.6">
              Establishing measures to ensure that data used and produced by the automated decision system are traceable, protected and accessed appropriately, and lawfully collected, used, retained, disclosed and disposed of in accordance with the 
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32601">
                <em>Directive on Service and Digital</em>
              </a>
              , 
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18309">
                <em>Directive on Privacy Practices</em>
              </a>
              , and 
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32611">
                <em>Directive on Security Management</em>
              </a>
              .
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Peer review</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.7">Consulting the appropriate qualified experts to review the automated decision system, algorithmic impact assessment and supporting documentation, and publishing the complete review or a plain language summary prior to the automated decision system’s production, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Gender-based Analysis Plus</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.8">Completing a Gender-based Analysis Plus during the development or modification of the automated decision system, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Employee training</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.9">Providing training to each employee involved in any aspect of the development, use or management of automated decision systems, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Security</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.10">
              Conducting risk assessments during the development and maintenance of the automated decision system and implementing appropriate information management and information technology security protections, in accordance with the 
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578">
                <em>Policy on Government Security</em>
              </a>
               and the 
              <em>
                <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603">Policy on Service and Digital</a>
              </em>
              .
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="6.3.11">Implementing measures to secure data and model integrity to prevent tampering and unauthorized modifications, ensuring alignment with Government of Canada guidance, standards, and industry best practices, as prescribed by Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Legal</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.12">Consulting with the department’s legal services from the concept stage of an automation project to ensure that the use of the automated decision system is compliant with applicable legal requirements.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
        <section>
          <header>
            <h4>Ensuring human involvement</h4>
          </header>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="6.3.13">Ensuring that the automated decision system allows for human involvement, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
            <clause anchor="6.3.14">Obtaining the appropriate level of approvals prior to the production of an automated decision system, as prescribed in Appendix C.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="6.4" title="Recourse">
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="6.4.1">
            Informing clients of recourse options to challenge the administrative decision.
                       
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="6.4.1.1">Ensuring that recourse options are timely, effective, and easy to access.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="6.5" title="Reporting">
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="6.5.1">
            Publishing information on the effectiveness and efficiency of the automated decision system in meeting program objectives on the 
            <a href="https://search.open.canada.ca/opendata/?collection=aia&amp;page=1&amp;sort=date_modified+desc">Open Government Portal</a>
            .
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="6.5.2">Publishing information on the Open Government Portal on how the use of the automated decision system is fair and transparent and does not violate human rights and freedoms.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </chapter>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="Roles and responsibilities of Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat">
      <p>The Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat is responsible for:</p>
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="7.1">Providing government-wide guidance on the use of automated decision systems.</clause>
        <clause anchor="7.2">Developing and maintaining the Algorithmic Impact Assessment tool and any supporting documentation.</clause>
        <clause anchor="7.3">Communicating and engaging government-wide and with partners in other jurisdictions and sectors to develop common strategies, approaches, and processes to support the responsible use of automated decision systems.</clause>
        <clause anchor="7.4">Raising with the relevant deputy head as appropriate any compliance issues that arise with this directive.</clause>
        <clause anchor="7.5">Supporting policy implementation by working with departments, as appropriate, to ensure that automated decision systems are fair, effective and transparent.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="Application">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="8.1">
          This directive applies to all institutions subject to the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603">
            <em>Policy on Service and Digital</em>
          </a>
          .
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="8.2">
          Other departments or separate agencies that are not subject to the 
          <em>Policy on Service and Digital</em>
           are encouraged to meet the requirements of this directive as good practice.
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="8.3">
          <strong>Agents of Parliament</strong>
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="8.3.1">
              The following organizations are considered agents of Parliament for the purposes of the directive:
                            
              <ul>
                <li>Office of the Auditor General of Canada</li>
                <li>Office of the Chief Electoral Officer</li>
                <li>Office of the Commissioner of Lobbying of Canada</li>
                <li>Office of the Commissioner of Official Languages</li>
                <li>Office of the Information Commissioner of Canada</li>
                <li>Office of the Privacy Commissioner of Canada</li>
                <li>Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner of Canada</li>
              </ul>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="8.3.2">The heads of agents of Parliaments are solely responsible for monitoring and ensuring compliance with this directive within their organizations, as well as for responding to cases of non-compliance in accordance with any Treasury Board instruments that address the management of compliance.</clause>
            <clause anchor="8.3.3">The subsections 6.2.2.1 and 7.4 do not apply to agents of Parliament.</clause>
            <clause anchor="8.3.4">Agents of Parliament are not required to publish the algorithmic impact assessment (6.1.1) or reporting information on the Open Government Portal (6.5.1 and 6.5.2).</clause>
            <clause anchor="8.3.5">The heads of agents of Parliaments are responsible for approval of level 4 systems to operate (6.3.14, Appendix C).</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="9" title="References">
      <chapter anchor="9.1" title="Legislation">
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">
              <em>Financial Administration Act</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/">
              <em>Access to Information Act</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/page-12.html">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/h-6/">
              <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/u-2.2/page-1.html">United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples Act</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/">
              <em>Privacy Act</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-5/">
              <em>Security of Information Act</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-0.6/">
              <em>Accessible Canada Act</em>
            </a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </chapter>
      <chapter anchor="9.2" title="Related policy instruments">
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453">
              <em>Policy on Access to Information</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603">
              <em>Policy on Service and Digital</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578">
              <em>Policy on Government Security</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510">
              <em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32621">
              <em>Policy on People Management</em>
            </a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=28108">Directive on Open Government</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32805">Directive on Security Screening</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32611">Directive on Security Management</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32601">Directive on Service and Digital</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18309">Directive  on Privacy Practices</a>
            </em>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>
              <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049">Values and Ethics Code for the Public Service</a>
            </em>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </chapter>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="10" title="Enquiries">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="10.1">
          For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact 
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>
          .
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="10.2">
          Individuals from departments may contact 
          <a href="mailto:ai-ia@tbs-sct.gc.ca">ai-ia@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a>
           for any questions regarding this directive, including the Algorithmic Impact Assessment tool.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A - Definitions">
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <strong>administrative  decision</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Any  decision that is made by an authorized official of a department as  identified in section 8  of this directive pursuant to powers  conferred by an Act of Parliament or an order made pursuant to a prerogative of  the Crown that affects legal rights, privileges or interests.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>algorithmic  impact assessment</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>A framework  to help  departments better  understand and reduce the risks associated with automated decision systems and  to provide the appropriate  requirements that best match the  type of  system being designed. </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>automated  decision system</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Any  technology that either assists or replaces the judgment of human decision  makers. These systems draw from fields like statistics, linguistics and computer  science, and use techniques such as rules-based systems, regression, predictive  analytics, machine learning, deep learning, and neural networks.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>human  rights</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          The  rights to which persons are inherently entitled because they are human beings (
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/services/about-human-rights.html">Source</a>
          ).  Human rights are protected in the 
          <em>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</em>
          , 
          <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>
          ,  and the 
          <em>United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples Act</em>
          . 
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>production</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>An  automated decision  system is in production when it is in use and has impacts on real clients. This can include when it is in beta or user testing and producing outputs that  impact clients.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>proprietary</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>Refers to  systems, algorithms or software owned by an entity, such as a company or government. These systems are often closed  source, meaning the source code is not publicly available.</dd>
        <dt>
          <strong>test  environment</strong>
        </dt>
        <dd>An  environment containing hardware, instrumentation, simulators, software tools, and other support elements needed to conduct a test. A system in a test environment may mimic a production  environment but does not impact real clients. Test environments may include  exploration zones and sandboxes. </dd>
      </dl>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B - Impact Assessment Levels">
      <table class="table table-bordered table-condensed table-hover small">
        <thead>
          <tr class="active">
            <th scope="col">Level</th>
            <th scope="col">Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              <abbr title="1">I</abbr>
            </th>
            <td>
              The context in which the system is operating likely has low levels of risk associated with it. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the identity factors of the clients that may be impacted</li>
                <li>the line of business and the decision that the system is supporting</li>
                <li>the type of technology being used</li>
              </ul>
              
      The decision will likely have little to no, easily reversible, and brief impacts on some of: 
      
              <ul>
                <li>the rights of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the equality, dignity, privacy, and autonomy of individuals </li>
                <li>the health or well-being of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the economic interests of individuals, entities, or communities </li>
                <li>the ongoing sustainability of an ecosystem </li>
              </ul>
              
      The data used by the system likely presents low levels of risk. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the sensitivity of the data (such as the use of non-personal or unclassified information)</li>
                <li>the use of structured data </li>
                <li>the data collection approach</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              <abbr title="2">II</abbr>
            </th>
            <td>
              The context in which the system is operating likely has moderate levels of risk associated with it. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the identity factors of the clients that may be impacted</li>
                <li>the line of business and the decision that the system is supporting</li>
                <li>the type of technology being used</li>
              </ul>
              
      The decision will likely have moderate, likely reversible and short-term impacts on some or all of :
      
              <ul>
                <li>the rights of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the equality, dignity, privacy, and autonomy of individuals </li>
                <li>the health or well-being of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the economic interests of individuals, entities, or communities </li>
                <li>the ongoing sustainability of an ecosystem </li>
              </ul>
              
      The data used by the system likely presents moderate levels of risk. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the sensitivity of the data (such as the use of personal, non-personal, unclassified or protected information)</li>
                <li>the use of structured or unstructured data</li>
                <li>the data collection approach</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              <abbr title="3">III</abbr>
            </th>
            <td>
              The context in which the system is operating likely has high levels of risk associated with it. This may be because of:


      
              <ul>
                <li>the identity factors of the clients that may be impacted</li>
                <li>the line of business and the decision that the system is supporting</li>
                <li>the type of technology being used</li>
              </ul>
              
      The decision will likely have high, difficult to reverse and potentially ongoing impacts on some or all of :
      
              <ul>
                <li>the rights of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the equality, dignity, privacy, and autonomy of individuals </li>
                <li>the health or well-being of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the economic interests of individuals, entities, or communities </li>
                <li>the ongoing sustainability of an ecosystem </li>
              </ul>
              
      The data used by the system likely presents high levels of risk. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the sensitivity of the data (such as the use of personal or protected information)</li>
                <li>the use of unstructured data</li>
                <li>the data collection approach</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              <abbr title="4">IV</abbr>
            </th>
            <td>
              The context in which the system is operating likely has very high levels of risk associated with it. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the identity factors of the clients that will be impacted</li>
                <li>the line of business and the decision that the system is supporting</li>
                <li>the type of technology being used</li>
              </ul>
              
      The decision will likely have very high, irreversible and perpetual impacts on some or all of: 
      
              <ul>
                <li>the rights of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the equality, dignity, privacy, and autonomy of individuals </li>
                <li>the health or well-being of individuals or communities </li>
                <li>the economic interests of individuals, entities, or communities </li>
                <li>the ongoing sustainability of an ecosystem </li>
              </ul>
              
       The data used by the system likely presents very high levels of risk. This may be because of:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the sensitivity of the data (such as the use of personal, protected, or classified information)</li>
                <li>the use of unstructured or incomplete data</li>
                <li>the data collection approach</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="C" title="Appendix C - Impact Level Requirements">
      <table class="table table-bordered table-condensed table-hover table-responsive small">
        <thead>
          <tr class="active">
            <th scope="col">Requirement</th>
            <th scope="col">Level I</th>
            <th scope="col">Level II</th>
            <th scope="col">Level III</th>
            <th scope="col">Level IV</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Notice
              <br/>
               
      (sections 6.2.1–6.2.2)
            </th>
            <td>Plain language notice posted through all service delivery channels in use (Internet, in person, mail or telephone).</td>
            <td>Same as level I</td>
            <td>
              Plain language notice posted through all service delivery  channels in use (Internet, in person, mail or telephone).
              <br/>
                
      In addition, the notice must direct clients to the published explanation required under Explanation level I.
            </td>
            <td>Same as level III</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Explanation
              <br/>
               
      (section 6.2.3)
            </th>
            <td>
              In addition to any applicable legal requirement, ensure that a meaningful explanation is published on how the system works in general. The explanation must be in plain language and include information about:
      
              <ul>
                <li>the role of the system in the decision-making process</li>
                <li>input data, its source and method of collection</li>
                <li>the criteria used to evaluate input data and the operations applied to process it</li>
                <li>results of any reviews or audits</li>
                <li>the output produced by the automated decision system and any relevant information needed to interpret it in the context of the administrative decision</li>
                <li>the principal factors behind a decision</li>
              </ul>
              
      This explanation must be made on a discoverable  departmental website and linked in the algorithmic impact assessment.
              <br/>
                
        Explanations must also inform clients of relevant recourse options, where appropriate.
            </td>
            <td>
              The explanation from level I is published.
              <br/>
                
      In addition, a more detailed, meaningful, plain language, explanation is provided to the client with any decision that results in the denial of a benefit or service, or involves a regulatory action. 
              <br/>
                
      This explanation must inform the client of the reason or justification of the administrative decision. This involves a clear and client-focused description of how the automated decision system came to the output it did, including: 
      
              <ul>
                <li>the principal factors that led to it, such as, where appropriate, a description of the decision tree, scoring or weights of certain factors, and</li>
                <li>how the automated decision system output was used by human officers</li>
              </ul>
              
      The client must also be provided with the link to the published level I explanation.
            </td>
            <td>Same as level II</td>
            <td>Same as level II</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Peer review
              <br/>
               
      (section 6.3.7)
            </th>
            <td>None</td>
            <td>
              Consult at least one of the following qualified experts and publish the complete review or a plain language summary on a Government of Canada website:
      
              <ul>
                <li>Experts from a federal, provincial, territorial or municipal government institution</li>
                <li>Faculty members of a post-secondary institution</li>
                <li>Researchers from a relevant non-governmental organization</li>
                <li>Contracted third-party vendor with a relevant specialization</li>
                <li>A data and automation advisory board specified by Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
            <td>Same as level II</td>
            <td>
              Consult at least two of the following qualified experts and publish the complete review or a plain language summary on a Government of Canada website:
      
              <ul>
                <li>Experts from the National Research Council of Canada, Statistics Canada, the Communications Security Establishment, or Shared Services Canada</li>
                <li>Faculty members of a post-secondary institution</li>
                <li>Researchers from a relevant non-governmental organization</li>
                <li>Contracted third-party vendor with a relevant specialization</li>
                <li>A data and automation advisory board specified by Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Gender-based Analysis Plus
              <br/>
               
      (section 6.3.8)
            </th>
            <td>None</td>
            <td>
              Ensure that the 
              <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/women-gender-equality/gender-based-analysis-plus.html">Gender-based Analysis Plus</a>
               has been consulted with your department’s diversity and inclusion experts and includes:
      
              <ul>
                <li>An assessment of how the automation project might impact different population groups. This includes consideration of the impacts of the automated decision system  and data used in the project, as well as the likely impact of the final decision. Where possible, cite the data used to assess the impacts. It is recommended that the data be gender-disaggregated and include other intersecting identity factors such as age, disability and race. If the data is unavailable, identify where the data gaps exist</li>
                <li>Details of planned or existing measures to address risks identified through the Gender-based Analysis Plus or other assessments</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
            <td>Same as level II</td>
            <td>Same as level II</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Training
              <br/>
               
      (section 6.3.9)
            </th>
            <td>Role-based training on how to appropriately use and explain the functionalities of the automated decision system, at a high level. </td>
            <td>Same as level I</td>
            <td>
              Role-based training on how to appropriately manage, secure, and use the functionalities and explain the capabilities of the automated decision system, including: 
      
              <ul>
                <li>the technical aspects of the automated decision system to ensure an up-to-date understanding of the how the system works </li>
                <li>potential impacts of the automated decision system on privacy, fairness, and human rights and how to detect them</li>
                <li>how to evaluate and, if necessary, override decisions</li>
              </ul>
              
      Training must be recurring. 
            </td>
            <td>Same as level III</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Ensuring human involvement
              <br/>
               
      (section 6.3.13)
            </th>
            <td>
              The system may make decisions and assessments without direct human involvement.
              <br/>
                
      Humans are to be involved in system quality assurance and can intervene in the making of decisions by the system where appropriate.
            </td>
            <td>Same as level I</td>
            <td>
              The final decision must be made by a human.
              <br/>
                
      Decisions cannot be made without having clearly defined human involvement during the decision-making process.
              <br/>
                
      Humans review the decisions or recommendations made by the  system for accuracy and appropriateness. Humans are to be involved in ongoing quality assurance and can intervene in the making of decisions and assessments made by the system.
            </td>
            <td>Same as level III</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th scope="row">
              Approval for the system to operate
              <br/>
                
      (section 6.3.14)
            </th>
            <td>Assistant deputy minister responsible for the program.</td>
            <td>Same as level I</td>
            <td>Deputy head</td>
            <td>Treasury Board </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
</doc>
