<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Directive on Classification Oversight" documentID="28699" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on April 1, 2020.</clause>
        <clause anchor="1.2">
          This directive replaces the following Treasury Board policy instrument:
			
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Directive on Classification Oversight</em>
               (July 1, 2015)
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="2.1">
          This directive is issued pursuant to the same authorities indicated in section 2 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="Objectives and expected results">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="3.1">
          The objectives of this directive are as follows: 
			
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="3.1.1">Contribute to prudent management of the wage bill for the core public administration through effective oversight of the Classification Program; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="3.1.2">Provide assurance that classification relativity is maintained and that the integrity of the Classification Program is safeguarded.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="3.2">
          The expected results of this directive are as follows:
			
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="3.2.1">Organizations across the core public administration perform sound and effective classification oversight; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="3.2.2">Classification decisions are made in accordance with relevant occupational group definitions and job evaluation standards. </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Requirements">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="4.1">
          The head of human resources is responsible for the following:
			
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.1.1">Ensuring that an organizational classification oversight function is developed, implemented and maintained; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.2">Identifying, assessing and prioritizing key organizational design and classification risks through oversight; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.3">Informing the deputy head of potential risks and mitigation strategies in a timely fashion; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.4">
              Providing the Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer with the following information when requested to do so: 
					
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="4.1.4.1">Classification monitoring reports authorized by the deputy head; </clause>
                <clause anchor="4.1.4.2">Oversight information, such as departmental audit, performance evaluation and other similar reports related to the Classification Program; and</clause>
              </clauses>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.5">Developing and implementing corrective action plans that incorporate and respond to feedback and recommendations received from the Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer, organizational audits or performance evaluations.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Roles of other government organizations">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="5.1">Not applicable.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Application">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="6.1">
          This directive applies to the organizations listed in section 6 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
           and to positions in all occupational groups, including those in the Executive (EX) Group. 
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="6.2">
          This directive does not apply to organizations whose deputy heads are solely responsible for monitoring and ensuring compliance within their organizations as listed in subsection 6.5 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          . 
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="References">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="7.1">
          Legislation
		
		
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Financial Administration Act</em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="7.2">
          Related policy instruments
		
	      
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Policy on the Management of Executives</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Directive on Classification</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Directive on Classification Grievances</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Job Evaluation Standards</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Occupational Group and Subgroup Definitions</em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="7.3">
          Other
		   
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Organization and Classification Learning Curriculum</em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="Enquiries">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="8.1">
          For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact 
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>
          . 
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
</doc>
