<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Directive on Classification" documentID="28700" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on April 1, 2021.</clause>
        <clause anchor="1.2">
          This directive replaces the following  Treasury Board policy instrument:
    
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Directive  on Classification</em>
               (April 1, 2020)
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="2.1">
          This directive is issued pursuant to  the same authorities indicated in section 2 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          . 
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="Objectives  and expected results">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="3.1">
          In addition to the objectives indicated in section 3 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          , the  objective of this directive is to support the core public administration in  establishing the relative value of work in an equitable, consistent and  effective manner.
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="3.2">
          In addition to the expected results indicated in section 3 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          , the  expected results of this directive are as follows:  
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="3.2.1">Classification authority is properly  exercised; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="3.2.2">Classification decisions are sound, and  organizational design and classification activities are well managed. </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Requirements">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="4.1">
          The head of human resources is responsible for the following:  
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.1.1">
              Ensuring that jobs within the  organization are classified in accordance with the 
              <em>Directive on Classification</em>
              , job evaluation standards, occupational  group and subgroup definitions, and guidance from the Chief Human Resources  Officer;
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.2">Ensuring that classification conversion  and renaming initiatives are completed within the prescribed timelines and  guidance established by the Chief Human Resources Officer;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.3">Ensuring that persons approving classification  actions are trained as  stipulated by the Chief Human Resources Officer prior to exercising  organizational design and classification responsibilities; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.4">Ensuring that standardized and unique  job descriptions are used appropriately;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.5">Ensuring that an internal process is  established for the resolution of impasses and disagreements in a  classification decision; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.6">Ensuring that the organizational/departmental  level of approval and approval process required for effective dates carrying a  long retroactivity period (that is, six months or more) are established;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.7">Ensuring that deputy head–directed  decisions are used and administered in accordance with the mandatory procedures  in Appendix A;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.8">
              Ensuring that all classification  actions and decisions are:      
        
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="4.1.8.1">Tracked and recorded in the organization’s  human resources system; and </clause>
                <clause anchor="4.1.8.2">Submitted to the Chief Human Resources  Officer’s human resources systems; and </clause>
              </clauses>
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.9">Ensuring that controls are in place for  the management of vacant positions.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="4.2">
          Managers are responsible for the  following:  
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.2.1">Successfully  completing the required training stipulated by the Chief Human Resources  Officer prior to exercising organizational design and classification  responsibilities; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.2">Seeking  advice from persons accredited in organizational design and classification when  proposing changes to their organizational structure and when updating job  descriptions; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.3">
              Providing  all information required for rendering a classification decision and for  completing classification actions as described in the 
              <em>Standard on Classification</em>
               (subsection B.2.2.9); 
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.4">Implementing  interdepartmental and departmental standardized job descriptions wherever  possible; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.5">Maintaining  accurate organizational structures and current job descriptions for their area  of responsibility; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.6">Determining  the effective date of a job description and justifying the date chosen based on  evidence; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.7">Participating  in job evaluation committees and in job validation reviews, as required; and </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.8">Ensuring  that employees are notified each time a classification decision is rendered for  the position they occupy. </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="4.3">
          Persons accredited in organizational design  and classification and who have delegated  classification authority are responsible for:  
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.3.1">Evaluating  jobs and approving classification decisions;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.3.2">Providing  organizational design and classification advice; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.3.3">Participating on job evaluation committees. </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="4.4">
          Persons trained in organizational design and  classification are responsible for approving classification actions that do not  impact or modify a classification decision, including:  
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.4.1">Creating  a position using a standardized job description; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.4.2">Deleting  a position; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.4.3">Changing  the reporting relationship or title of a position.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Roles of other government organizations">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="5.1">
          The roles of other government  organizations in relation to this directive are described in section 5 of  the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Application">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="6.1">
          This directive applies to the  organizations listed in section 6 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          .
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="6.2">This directive does not apply to  positions classified in the Executive (EX) Group.</clause>
        <clause anchor="6.3">This directive does not apply to  persons appointed by the Governor in Council, to members of the Royal Canadian  Mounted Police, or to members of the Canadian Armed Forces.</clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="References">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="7.1">
          Legislation
    
          <ul>
            <li>
              <a href="https://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/H-6/page-1.html#h-256819">
                <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>
                , subsection 11(2)
              </a>
            </li>
            <li>
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/index.html">
                <em>Financial Administration Act</em>
              </a>
              , section 7  and subsection 11(1)
            </li>
            <li>
              <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-33.01/page-3.html#h-404225">
                <em>Public Service Employment Act</em>
                , section 30(2)
              </a>
            </li>
            <li>
              <a href="https://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-34/">
                <em>Public Service Rearrangement and Transfer of Duties Act</em>
              </a>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="7.2">
          Related  policy instruments
    
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Directive on Classification Oversight</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Directive on Classification Grievances</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/collective-agreements/job-evaluation/job-evaluation-standards-public-service-employees.html">Job evaluation standards</a>
            </li>
            <li>
              <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/collective-agreements/occupational-groups.html">Occupational group and subgroup definitions</a>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="7.3">
          Other
    
          <ul>
            <li>
              <a href="http://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/wiki/TBS_Classification_Program_for_the_CPA/Learning_Curriculum_and_Accreditation">Organization and Classification Learning Curriculum</a>
            </li>
            <li>
              <a href="https://open.canada.ca/en/proactive-disclosure">Proactive Disclosure – Position Reclassifications</a>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="Enquiries">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="8.1">Human resources advisors should direct enquiries  about this directive to their departmental human resources office. </clause>
        <clause anchor="8.2">
          For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact 
          <a href="mailto:Publicenquiries-demandesderenseignement@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Treasury  Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A: Mandatory Procedures for  Use and Administration of Deputy Head–Directed Classification Decisions">
      <appendix anchor="A.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.1.1">These procedures take effect on April 1, 2020. </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.1.2">
            These procedures replace the following instrument:
        
            <ul>
              <li>
                <em>Directive on Classification</em>
                , Appendix J: Deputy Head–Directed Classification  Decisions (July 1, 2015)
              </li>
            </ul>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.2">
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.2.1">
            These  procedures provide details on the requirements set out in subsection 4.1.7  of the 
            <em>Directive on Classification</em>
            .
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.2.2">
            Deputy  head–directed decisions used in the circumstances described in subsection A1.2  of the 
            <em>Policy on People Management</em>
              must:
        
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="A.2.2.1">Be documented in the classification  file; </clause>
              <clause anchor="A.2.2.2">Contain the deputy head’s authorization;</clause>
              <clause anchor="A.2.2.3">Be assigned a new job and position  number;</clause>
              <clause anchor="A.2.2.4">Be identified in the departmental human  resources system as not to be used for relativity purposes and not to be  replicated; and</clause>
              <clause anchor="A.2.2.5">Be deleted when the incumbent  vacates the position.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.2.3">
            For  purposes of subsection A1.2.2 of the 
            <em>Policy  on People Management</em>
            , prior to making a directed decision, detailed  proposals for organizational design and classification innovation solutions  must be submitted to the Chief Human Resources Officer for approval that include:
        
            <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
              <li>The  objectives and expected benefits of the organizational design and  classification innovation solution; </li>
              <li>A  risk assessment;</li>
              <li>Proposed  mitigation measures;</li>
              <li>The  duration with a specific end date; and</li>
              <li>Performance  measures, indicators and processes that will be used to evaluate and report on  the success of the innovation solution.</li>
            </ol>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B: Standard on  Classification">
      <appendix anchor="B.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="B.1.1">This standard takes effect on April 1,  2020.</clause>
          <clause anchor="B.1.2">
            This standard replaces the following Treasury Board policy instruments:
        
            <ul>
              <li>
                <em>Policy on Classification</em>
                 (July 1, 2015) 
              </li>
              <li>
                <em>Directive on Classification</em>
                 (July 1, 2015)
              </li>
            </ul>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="B.2">
        <title>Standards</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="B.2.1">
            This standard provides details on the  requirements set out in section 4 of the 
            <em>Directive on Classification</em>
            .
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="B.2.2">
            Standards are as follows: 


            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Job descriptions </h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.1">
                  Job descriptions must be written  concisely in bias‑free plain language, contain all significant aspects of the  work assigned to the job, and include: 
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>The organizational context, mandate and  supervisor–subordinate relationships; </li>
                    <li>A title that reflects the functions and nature  of the work described; and</li>
                    <li>The manager’s signature and the date the job  description was signed.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.2">
                  The following identifying information  must appear in the job description: 
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>Job number;</li>
                    <li>Position number;</li>
                    <li>Authorized group and level;</li>
                    <li>National Occupational  Classification (NOC) code;</li>
                    <li>Effective date;</li>
                    <li>Organization/department; </li>
                    <li>Branch/division;</li>
                    <li>Geographic location;</li>
                    <li>Official languages, security and  communication requirements; and</li>
                    <li>Supervisor’s position number, group and  level.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.3">
                  A new or updated job description is  required in the following circumstances:
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>When significant changes in the work  occur; or</li>
                    <li>When new work is assigned.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Reclassification </h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.4">
                  A job evaluation that results in a change in the occupational group, subgroup  (if applicable), or the level of an existing job or position is considered to  be a reclassification and may occur only as a result of: 
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>Central agency or organizational  oversight; </li>
                    <li>A grievance decision;</li>
                    <li>A correction of an error; </li>
                    <li>A substantial change in duties or  responsibilities; </li>
                    <li>Legislative changes that result in new  program requirements; </li>
                    <li>Central agency or departmental policy that  results in changes to existing programs or changes to organizational mandates; </li>
                    <li>Reorganization of work; and</li>
                    <li>Natural evolution of work within the  same work continuum.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.5">
                  The following situations do not  constitute a reclassification: 
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>
                      Jobs/individuals are transferred from non–core  public administration organizations to the core public administration pursuant  to the block transfer provisions of the 
                      <em>Public  Service Employment Act</em>
                       as a result of an order under the 
                      <em>Public Service Rearrangement and Transfer of  Duties Act</em>
                      ; 
                    </li>
                    <li>Jobs/individuals are transferred by  legislation to the core public administration; and </li>
                    <li>
                      There is a change to the minimum  qualifications established in accordance with subsection 30(2) of the 
                      <em>Public Service Employment Act</em>
                      .
                    </li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Job evaluation committee</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.6">
                  At a  minimum, a job evaluation committee is required when: 
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>Evaluating standardized job  descriptions; </li>
                    <li>Using an occupational group or subgroup  for the first time in an organization; </li>
                    <li>The evaluation outcome may have a  significant impact on departmental and interdepartmental relativity or result  in a significant increase of salary expenditures;</li>
                    <li>There is the likelihood of a  reclassification; and</li>
                    <li>The evaluation outcome could be  contentious or precedent‑setting.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.7">
                  A job evaluation committee is comprised  of: 
   
	  
                  <ul>
                    <li>At least one member who is designated as the Chair; </li>
                    <li>A minimum of three rating members who  are trained in job evaluation including one who is delegated in organizational design and classification;</li>
                    <li>One or more rating members who  represent(s) the organizations that use the interdepartmental standardized job  description, if applicable; and</li>
                    <li>Members who are not in a potential  conflict of interest.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Job  validation</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.8">
                  A job validation review is required  when:
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>A proposed or possible reclassification  may occur; and</li>
                    <li>A better understanding of the job is needed.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Documentation  and data management</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.9">
                  At a minimum, the following  documentation is required to substantiate a classification decision and must be retained in the classification  file:
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>A job description, signed and dated by  the manager, that describes the duties and responsibilities of the position and  indicates the effective date;</li>
                    <li>An organizational chart, signed and  dated by the manager, that depicts the organizational location of the position  and its relationship to the other positions in the same unit or division;</li>
                    <li>The classification action form (“Expanded  Position Activity Report”), signed by a person accredited with delegated  classification authority; </li>
                    <li>A job evaluation rationale, signed and  dated, that substantiates the classification decision;</li>
                    <li>An analysis and summary of the relevant  classification relativity; </li>
                    <li>The job validation report, if a job  validation review was conducted; and</li>
                    <li>Any other information that supports the  effective date. </li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.10">
                  For  reclassification decisions, the following documentation must also be retained: 
    
                  <ul>
                    <li>A statement from the manager  summarizing the evolution of the work.</li>
                  </ul>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Proactive disclosure</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.11">
                  Classification  decisions that result in the reclassification of an occupied position are  subject to 
                  <a href="https://open.canada.ca/en/proactive-disclosure">proactive disclosure</a>
                   and must be uploaded to the human resources 
                  <a href="http://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/wiki/Proactive_Disclosure_on_Open.Canada.ca">system</a>
                   on a quarterly basis. 
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
</doc>
