<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Directive on the Management of Communications and Federal Identity" documentID="30682" versionID="18" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <notetoreader>
    <p>Requirement 4.1.13 (misinformation and disinformation strategy) takes effect on March 27, 2026, as identified in Section 1.</p>
  </notetoreader>
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on March 27, 2025.</clause>
        <clause anchor="1.2">
          This directive replaces the following Treasury Board policy instruments:
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="1.2.1">
              <em>Directive on the  Management of Communications</em>
              , May 11, 2016.
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="1.2.2">
              <em>Procedures for Publishing</em>
              , June 1, 2013.
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="1.3">
          Transitional considerations:
    
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="1.3.1">Requirement 4.1.13 of this directive takes  effect on March 27, 2026.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="2.1">
          This directive is issued pursuant to the same  authorities indicated in section 2 of the 
          <em>Policy on Communications and  Federal Identity</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="Objectives  and expected results">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="3.1">
          The objectives indicated in section 3 of the 
          <em>Policy on Communications and Federal Identity</em>
           apply to this directive.
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="3.2">
          The expected results indicated in section 3 of  the 
          <em>Policy on Communications and Federal Identity</em>
           apply to this  directive.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Requirements">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="4.1">
          Heads of communications are responsible for the following:
	
	
		
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Managing and coordinating</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.1">Leading the communications and corporate  identity function within the department.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.2">Providing direction to departmental officials on  communications and corporate identity.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.3">Approving the most effective way to achieve  communications objectives and to reach the intended target audiences.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.4">Approving all communications plans, strategies  and products for external audiences.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.5">Monitoring and analyzing the public environment  as it relates to policies, programs, services and initiatives.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.6">Developing communications plans and procedures  in preparation for emergency or crisis situations.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.7">Providing internal communications support for  department-wide priorities.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.8">Collaborating with the Privy Council Office and  other departments on all communications activities and initiatives that require  input from multiple departments.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.9">Collaborating with regional offices to ensure  that communications objectives are met across the country.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.10">Ensuring that the department does not sell  advertising or publish advertisements from a non-government source in its  communications products and activities.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.11">Reviewing all departmental Memoranda to Cabinet and Treasury Board submissions to ensure that appropriate measures and adequate  resources are recommended to meet planned communications objectives.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.12">Ensuring that all communications products and activities do not endorse or provide an unfair competitive advantage, real or  perceived, to any individual, organization or private sector enterprise.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.13">Developing a strategy to manage misinformation and disinformation related to the mandate of the department.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.14">Ensuring all communications resources are used only for the purposes of non-partisan and official Government of Canada communications.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.15">Securing permission to reproduce, adapt, translate and publish third-party material.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.16">Managing the administration and licensing of Crown copyright.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.17">Ensuring that when the Government of Canada posts information about policies, programs, services and initiatives on  official social media accounts or other third-party platforms, comparable  information is also available on a Government of Canada website.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.18">Ensuring that contracts for audio-visual services are issued by the Communications and Advertising Procurement  Directorate at Public Services and Procurement Canada.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Informing audiences</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.19">
                Ensuring that all communications products and activities are:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.1">aligned  with the government’s priorities, themes and objectives;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.2">accurate;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.3">non-partisan;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.4">objective;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.5">timely;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.6">accessible;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.7">written in a manner that is inclusive and in plain language;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.8">available in English and French;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.9">
                    developed in a way that considers the information needs of:
          
                    <clauses>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.19.9.1">English and French linguistic minority communities in Canada;</clause>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.19.9.2">First Nations, Inuit and Métis; and</clause>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.19.9.3">regional and rural populations, and multicultural communities;</clause>
                    </clauses>
                  </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.10">cost-effective  and provides value for money; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.19.11">communicated  first through official Government of Canada channels.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.20">Using the most appropriate communications tools and channels to achieve communications objectives and reach the intended target audiences. </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.21">Determining when communications products should also be made available in other languages in addition to English and French.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Federal identity</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.22">Supporting the deputy head in administering the  Federal Identity Program.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.23">Using the applied title of the department or the  title “Government of Canada” in all internal and external communications  products and activities.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.24">
                Instructing departmental officials to:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.1">
                    adhere  to the Federal Identity Program in accordance with the 
                    <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/design-standard.html">
                      <em>Design  Standard for the Federal Identity Program</em>
                    </a>
                     and the 
                    <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/federal-identity-program/manual.html">
                      <em>Federal Identity Program Manual</em>
                    </a>
                    ;
                  </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.2">use  only versions of the official symbols of the Government of Canada that are  based on the digital master files maintained by the Communications and Federal  Identity Policy Centre at Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.3">
                    use  the Canada wordmark with a corporate signature in all fields of application  unless otherwise stipulated in the 
                    <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/design-standard.html">
                      <em>Design  Standard for the Federal Identity Program</em>
                    </a>
                     or the 
                    <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/federal-identity-program/manual.html">
                      <em>Federal Identity Program Manual</em>
                    </a>
                    ;
                  </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.4">use  the applied title of the department or “Government of Canada” in text format  when use of the official symbols is not possible;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.5">
                    use the Government of Canada signature when:
          
                    <clauses>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.24.5.1">two or more departments are involved, or</clause>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.24.5.2">a department does not have an approved applied  title;</clause>
                    </clauses>
                  </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.6">display the official symbols prominently, free from other visual elements and visually conflicting backgrounds; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.24.7">present both official languages with equal prominence in the corporate identity of the department including using the same colour, style, size and type.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.25">Approving the development and use of a creative  approach to promote programs, commemorative events and other initiatives.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Additional corporate  identifiers</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.26">Seeking direction from the Communications and  Federal Identity Policy Centre at Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat when  departmental officials are considering an additional corporate identifier.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.27">
                Overseeing additional corporate identifiers that  have been approved by Treasury Board by:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.27.1">managing  these identifiers throughout all stages of the lifecycle, including planning,  implementation and disposal;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.27.2">maintaining  an inventory of these identifiers; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.27.3">ensuring  that these identifiers are used as approved. </clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.28">
                Developing a graphic standards manual that  outlines how the additional corporate identifier will be used: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.28.1">in  all fields of application; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.28.2">with  the corporate signature and the Canada wordmark.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.29">Ensuring graphic standards manuals for  additional corporate identifiers have been approved by the Communications and  Federal Identity Policy Centre at Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat prior to  use.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Specialized symbols</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.30">Confirming with the Communications and Federal  Identity Policy Centre at Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat that the  proposed specialized symbols align with the definition. </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.31">Approving the adoption of specialized symbols.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.32">
                Developing a graphic standards manual that  outlines how the specialized symbol will be used: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.32.1">in  all communications products and activities; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.32.2">with  the corporate signature and the Canada wordmark.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.33">Ensuring graphic standards manuals for  specialized symbols have been approved by the Communications and Federal  Identity Policy Centre at Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat prior to use.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.34">
                Overseeing the use of specialized symbols by: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.34.1">managing  these symbols throughout all stages of the lifecycle, including planning,  approval, implementation and disposal;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.34.2">maintaining  an inventory of approved specialized symbols; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.34.3">ensuring  that these symbols are used as intended in all communications products and  activities.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Social media</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.35">
                Overseeing departmental social media presence  including: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.35.1">approving  the departmental social media strategy;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.35.2">approving  all official social media accounts; </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.35.3">approving  content posted on official social media accounts;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.35.4">
                    ensuring  that the official social media management tools administered by Service Canada  are used for: 
          
                    <clauses>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.35.4.1">managing official social media accounts; and</clause>
                      <clause anchor="4.1.35.4.2">collecting analytics.</clause>
                    </clauses>
                  </clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.36">Ensuring that all official social media accounts  do not follow, share, tag or link to the personal or political social media  accounts of ministers, members of Parliament or senators.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Websites</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.37">Overseeing the content and corporate identity of  external-facing departmental websites.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.38">
                Ensuring that external-facing departmental websites:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.38.1">
                    adhere  to Appendix D: 
                    <em>Standard on External-facing Websites and Mobile Applications</em>
                    ;  and
                  </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.38.2">use  the official web analytics tool administered by Service Canada.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Mobile applications</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.39">Overseeing the corporate identity of mobile  applications.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.40">
                Ensuring that mobile applications adhere to  Appendix D: 
                <em>Standard on External-facing Websites and Mobile Applications</em>
                .
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Advertising</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.41">Leading the process for the annual advertising  plan. </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.42">Submitting the annual advertising plan to the  deputy head for approval.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.43">
                Adhering to the principles of the 
                <a href="https://adstandards.ca/code/the-code-online/">Canadian  Code of Advertising Standards</a>
                .
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.44">
                Complying with the 
                <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/advertising-oversight-mechanism.html">oversight  mechanism for non-partisan advertising</a>
                .
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.45">Ensuring that all initiatives that require  parliamentary approval or trade deals that require ratification are not  advertised until such approval has been received.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.46">
                Determining when advertising that has a 
                <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/buying-ads-directly.html">total  media buy not exceeding $40,000</a>
                 can be purchased directly from media  outlets in compliance with Section 6 of the 
                <em>Government Contracts Regulations</em>
                .
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Partnering and sponsorships</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.47">Reviewing all partnering and sponsorship  arrangements and agreements to provide communications and corporate identity  advice.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.48">
                Ensuring all partnering and sponsorship  arrangements do not: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.48.1">focus  primarily on advertising or paid efforts involving the media; or</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.48.2">promote  or advertise the commercial goods or services of partners or sponsors.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.49">
                Ensuring all partnering and sponsorship  agreements outline: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.49.1">communications  roles and responsibilities of all parties;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.49.2">corporate  identity requirements; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.49.3">official  language requirements.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Media spokespersons</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.50">Designating and authorizing media spokespersons  to communicate with the media in an official capacity on behalf of the  department.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.51">Providing media training to designated  spokespersons, as needed.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.52">
                Instructing designated media spokespersons when  speaking on the record for public attribution to: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.52.1">identify  themselves by name and position; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.52.2">confine  remarks to facts concerning policies, programs, services or initiatives.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.53">
                Informing designated media spokespersons of  their obligation to respect:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.53.1">privacy  rights; </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.53.2">security  needs;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.53.3">matters  before the courts; </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.53.4">government  laws, regulations and policies;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.53.5">Cabinet  confidences and ministerial responsibilities; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.53.6">
                    <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049">
                      <em>Values and  Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em>
                    </a>
                    .
                  </clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.54">Engaging with the news media to promote  awareness and understanding about government policies, programs, services and  initiatives.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Publications</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.55">
                Instructing departmental officials of their obligation to adhere to the 
                <a href="https://publications.gc.ca/site/eng/managing-government-publications.html">criteria as prescribed by the Government of Canada Publications Directorate</a>
                 at Public Services and Procurement Canada.
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.56">
                Ensuring an index of all publications including  electronic, free, priced and co-publications is:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.56.1">
                    maintained  by the department in accordance with the 
                    <a href="https://publications.gc.ca/site/eng/managing-government-publications.html">criteria prescribed by the Government of Canada Publications Directorate</a>
                     at Public Services and Procurement Canada;  and
                  </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.56.2">submitted  annually to the Government of Canada Publications Directorate at Public  Services and Procurement Canada. </clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.57">
                Obtaining from the Government of Canada  Publications Directorate at Public Services and Procurement Canada:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.57.1">an International Standard Book Number (ISBN), if applicable; and </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.57.2">a Government of Canada Catalogue Number.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.58">Obtaining from Library and Archives Canada an  International Standard Serial Number (ISSN) for journals and other serial  publications.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.59">
                Providing all publications to the Government of  Canada Publications Directorate at Public Services and Procurement Canada in: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.59.1">an  HTML format; </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.59.2">a  portable format;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.59.3">both  official languages; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.59.4">any  other available languages.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.60">Providing the Legal Deposit Unit at Library and  Archives Canada with copies of any tangible publications that have been  created, in all available editions and language versions.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Printed products</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.61">Ensuring communications products are printed based  on demand.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Promotional items</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.62">Approving the development, production,  acquisition, distribution and use of promotional items.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Public opinion research</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.63">Leading the process for the annual public  opinion research plan for all contracted and significant non-contracted  projects. </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.64">Ensuring that all contracted and significant  non-contracted public opinion research projects align with the mandate of the  department. </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.65">Submitting the public opinion research annual  plan and any unanticipated public opinion research projects to the deputy head  for approval.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.66">
                Ensuring that resources are not used for public  opinion research activities to determine:
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.66.1">electoral voting intentions;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.66.2">political party preferences;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.66.3">party standings with the electorate; or </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.66.4">ratings of the performance of a political party or its leader.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Consultations</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.67">Providing communications advice at all stages of consultation projects.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
          <section>
            <header>
              <h3>Federal elections</h3>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.1.68">
                Suspending all advertising and public opinion  research activities on: 
      
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.68.1">the day that the Governor in Council issues a writ for a general federal election, or</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.1.68.2">June 30 in a year in which there is a fixed general federal election date.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.69">Ensuring that all advertising and public opinion research activities that have been suspended during a general federal election  do not resume until the newly elected government is sworn into office.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.1.70">
                Obtaining deputy head approval during a general  federal election for select advertising and public opinion research activities  listed in requirements 4.1.10 and 4.1.11 of the 
                <em>Policy on Communications and  Federal Identity</em>
                .
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </section>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
      <section>
        <header>
          <h3>Functional specialists</h3>
        </header>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="4.2">
            Functional specialists involved in communications  products and activities or those who manage activities involving the Federal  Identity Program are responsible for:
    
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.2.1">Supporting the head of communications in  complying with the communications and federal identity policy requirements.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.2.2">Identifying all policy compliance issues to the  head of communications.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </section>
      <section>
        <header>
          <h3>Subject-matter experts</h3>
        </header>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="4.3">
            Departmental subject-matter experts are  responsible for the following when speaking in a work capacity and on the  record for public attribution:
    
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="4.3.1">Identifying themselves by name and position.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.3.2">Addressing remarks to areas for which they have  responsibility and expertise.</clause>
              <clause anchor="4.3.3">
                Respecting:
        
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="4.3.3.1">privacy rights;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.3.3.2">security needs;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.3.3.3">matters before the courts;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.3.3.4">government laws, regulations and policies; </clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.3.3.5">Cabinet confidences and ministerial  responsibilities; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="4.3.3.6">
                    <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049">
                      <em>Values and Ethics  Code for the Public Sector</em>
                    </a>
                    .
                  </clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
            </clauses>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Roles  of other government organizations">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="5.1">
          The roles of other government organizations in  relation to this directive are described in section 5 of the 
          <em>Policy on Communications and Federal  Identity</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Application">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="6.1">
          This directive applies to the organizations  described in section 6 of the 
          <em>Policy on  Communications and Federal Identity</em>
          .
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="6.2">
          The heads of the following organizations are  solely responsible for monitoring and ensuring compliance with this policy  within their organizations:
    
          <ul>
            <li>Office of the Auditor General of Canada</li>
            <li>Office of the Chief Electoral Officer</li>
            <li>Office of the Commissioner of Lobbying of Canada</li>
            <li>Office of the Commissioner of Official Languages</li>
            <li>Office of the Public Sector Integrity  Commissioner of Canada</li>
            <li>Offices of the Information and Privacy  Commissioners</li>
            <li>Office of the Registrar of the Supreme Court of  Canada</li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="6.3">The organizations listed in 6.2 are not required  to use the Canada wordmark.</clause>
        <clause anchor="6.4">
          The requirements below do not apply to the  organizations listed in 6.2:
      
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>Directive  on the Management of Communications and Federal Identity</em>
              : 4.1.8, 4.1.19.1,  4.1.24.3, 4.1.24.5.1, 4.1.26, 4.1.28 to 4.1.30, 4.1.32, 4.1.33, 4.1.35.4,  4.1.38, 4.1.40, and 4.1.44
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Appendix A: Mandatory Procedures for Advertising</em>
              : A.2.2.4 to A.2.2.10, A.2.2.12,  A.2.2.14 to A.2.2.17, A.2.2.19, A.2.2.22, A.2.2.24, and A.2.2.27 to A.2.2.29
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Appendix B: Mandatory Procedures for Public Opinion Research</em>
              : B.2.2.4, B.2.2.6 to  B.2.2.15
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Appendix C: Standard on Managing Official Social Media Accounts</em>
              : C.2.2.2 and C.2.2.3
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>Appendix D: Standard on External-facing Websites and Mobile Applications</em>
              : D.2.2.1 to  D.2.2.3
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="6.5">
          The following requirements are not mandatory for  departments that have not migrated their external-facing websites to the  Canada.ca content management tool:
    
          <ul>
            <li>
              4.1.38.2 of the 
              <em>Directive on the Management of Communications and Federal Identity</em>
            </li>
            <li>
              D.2.2.2.1 of 
              <em>Appendix  D: Standard on External-facing Websites and Mobile Applications</em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="References">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="7.1">
          References in relation to this directive are  described in section 8 of the 
          <em>Policy on Communications and Federal Identity</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="Enquiries">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="8.1">
          For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact 
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html#toc02">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A: Mandatory Procedures for Advertising">
      <appendix anchor="A.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.1.1">These procedures take effect on March 27, 2025. </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.1.2">
            These procedures replace the 
            <em>Mandatory  Procedures for Advertising</em>
            , May 11, 2016.
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.2">
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.2.1">
            These procedures provide details on the requirements set out in subsections 4.1.41 to  4.1.46 of the 
            <em>Directive on the Management of Communications and Federal  Identity</em>
            .
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.2.2">
            Mandatory procedures are as follows:
	 
  
	
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Developing  the annual advertising plan</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.1">Engage with departmental officials to determine advertising needs.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.2">Develop the departmental annual advertising plan.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.3">Submit the annual advertising plan to head of communications for review.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Planning and coordinating</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.4">Confirm with Advertising Services Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada to determine whether the initiative falls within the definition of advertising.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.5">Consult with the Communications and Consultations Secretariat of Privy Council Office when planning advertising activities.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.6">Consult with Global Affairs Canada when planning to advertise in foreign markets.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.7">Establish performance indicators for advertising campaigns as prescribed by the Privy Council Office.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.8">Provide results based on the performance indicators to the Communications and  Consultations Secretariat of Privy Council Office.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Contracting  advertising activities</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.9">
                  Engage with the Communications and Advertising Procurement Directorate of Public  Services and Procurement Canada to undertake procurement of the advertising  activity, unless otherwise stipulated in 4.1.46 of the 
                  <em>Directive on the  Management of Communications and Federal Identity</em>
                  , including:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.1">media planning;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.2">creative testing;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.3">creative production;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.4">media placement; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.5">campaign evaluation.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.10">
                  Collaborate with the Advertising Services Directorate of Public Services and Procurement  Canada to:
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.10.1">develop the statement of work; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.10.2">obtain the project registration number before the contract is awarded.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.11">Manage the advertising contract after it has been awarded.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.12">
                  Inform the Advertising Services Directorate and Communications and Advertising  Procurement Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada of any  changes or amendments to the:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.12.1">scope of work;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.12.2">contract; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.12.3">media buy strategy.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Producing advertising  creatives and media planning</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.13">
                  Consider  the needs and interests, as applicable, of:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.13.1">First Nations, Inuit and Métis;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.13.2">English and French linguistic minority communities; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.13.3">ethnocultural communities.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.14">
                  Comply with the 
                  <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/government-communications/advertising-oversight-mechanism.html">non-partisan advertising oversight mechanism</a>
                  .
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.15">
                  Submit the following to the Communications and Consultations Secretariat of Privy Council Office for review:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.15.1">draft creative elements; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.15.2">media buy strategies and plans.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.16">
                  Submit the following to the Advertising Services Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada to confirm compliance with legislative and policy  requirements:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.16.1">draft creative elements; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.16.2">media buy strategies and plans.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.17">Obtain the authorization (ADV) number from the Advertising Services Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Direct media purchases for  media buys that do not exceed $40,000</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.18">Seek approval from the head of communications to purchase media space directly from  media outlets for advertising initiatives that have a total media buy not  exceeding $40,000.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Advertising Management Information System</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.19">Record information on all advertising activities in the Advertising Management Information System (AdMIS).</clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Testing creatives for an  advertising campaign with a media buy over $1 million</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.20">Collaborate with departmental public opinion research officials to add the advertising  creative testing to the annual public opinion research plan.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.21">Confirm that the creative testing has been included on the approved annual public opinion research plan.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.22">
                  Develop  the plan for creative testing in collaboration with: 
	 
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.22.1">the Communications and Consultations  Secretariat of Privy Council Office; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.22.2">the Public Opinion Research Directorate of  Public Services and Procurement Canada.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.23">Conduct the creative testing in collaboration with departmental public opinion research officials.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.24">Provide creative testing research results to the Communications and Consultations  Secretariat of Privy Council Office.
	 </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Evaluating an advertising  campaign with a media buy over $2 million</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.25">Collaborate with departmental public opinion research officials to add the campaign evaluation to the annual public opinion research plan.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.26">Confirm that the campaign evaluation has been approved as part of the annual public opinion research plan.</clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.27">
                  Develop the evaluation plan in collaboration with:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.27.1">the Communications and Consultations  Secretariat of Privy Council Office; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.27.2">the Public Opinion Research Directorate of  Public Services and Procurement Canada.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.28">
                  Conduct the evaluation of the advertising campaign in collaboration with departmental public opinion research officials:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.28.1">using the Advertising Campaign Evaluation Tool (ACET) as prescribed by the Communications and Consultations Secretariat of Privy Council Office. </clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.29">Provide research results of the campaign evaluation to the Communications and Consultations Secretariat of Privy Council Office. </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B: Mandatory Procedures for Public Opinion Research">
      <appendix anchor="B.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="B.1.1">These procedures take effect on March 27, 2025.</clause>
          <clause anchor="B.1.2">
            These procedures replace the 
            <em>Mandatory Procedures for Public Opinion  Research</em>
            , May 11, 2016.
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="B.2">
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="B.2.1">
            These procedures provide details on the  requirements set out in subsections 4.1.63 to 4.1.66 of the 
            <em>Directive on the  Management of Communications and Federal Identity. </em>
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="B.2.2">
            Mandatory procedures are as follows: 
	
	 
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Developing  the Annual Public Opinion Research Plan</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.1">Engage with departmental officials to determine public opinion research needs.</clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.2">Develop the annual public opinion research  plan.</clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.3">
                  Include in the annual public opinion  research plan:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.3.1">a description of each public opinion research project, including the objective and the intended use of the results;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.3.2">the total contract value, if applicable, including taxes;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.3.3">whether the project will be undertaken  by multiple departments;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.3.4">whether a project will be carried out over  more than 1 fiscal year;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.3.5">planned creative testing for advertising  campaigns with media buys over $1 million; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.3.6">planned evaluation of advertising campaigns  with media buys over $2 million.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.4">
                  Coordinate the annual public opinion research plan and any amendments, as well as any unanticipated public opinion  research projects not included in the plan with:  
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.4.1">the Public Opinion Research Directorate of  Public Services and Procurement Canada; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.4.2">the Communications and Consultations  Secretariat of Privy Council Office.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.5 ">Submit the annual public opinion research  plan to the head of communications for review. </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.6 ">
                  Submit, for information, the approved  annual public opinion research plan to:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.6.1">the Public Opinion Research Directorate of  Public Services and Procurement Canada; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.6.2">the Communications and Consultations  Secretariat of Privy Council Office. </clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Planning  Public Opinion Research projects</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.7">
                  Coordinate the planning of contracted  public opinion research projects with:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.7.1">the Public Opinion Research Directorate of  Public Services and Procurement Canada; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.7.2">the Communications and Consultations  Secretariat of Privy Council Office.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.8">
                  Consult with the Public Opinion Research  Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.8.1">before initiating procurement; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.8.2">to obtain project registration numbers before  contracts are awarded.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.9">Collaborate with the Public Opinion Research Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada to develop statements of work.</clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.10 ">Coordinate all procurement for public  opinion research projects with the Communications and Advertising Procurement  Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada.</clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.11">Inform the Public Opinion Research Directorate and the Communications and Advertising Procurement Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada before initiating any changes to the  contract.</clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.12">
                  Submit the following documentation for contracted public opinion research projects to the Public Opinion Research Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.1">estimates;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.2">contracts;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.3">justification of the choice of supplier;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.4">amendments to contracts;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.5">information on contract values;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.6">information on the intended use of the research; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.12.7">the dates of data collection. </clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Conducting</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.13">Consult with the Public Opinion Research Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada before conducting the  research. </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.14">Provide, on request, research  instruments, analysis plans, survey data, data tables, reports and status  updates to the Communications and Consultations Secretariat of Privy Council Office for review.</clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.15">Provide draft research instruments of  contracted public opinion research projects to the Public Opinion Research  Directorate of Public Services and Procurement Canada for review. </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Reporting</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.16">
                  Ensure that reports for all contracted  public opinion research projects comply with the 
                  <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-2007-134/page-1.html">
                    <em>Public Opinion  Research Contract Regulations</em>
                  </a>
                  .
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.17">
                  Ensure that executive summaries in reports for contracted public opinion research projects outline:
    
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.17.1">how results are expected to be used; and </clause>
                    <clause anchor="B.2.2.17.2">the total contract value.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="B.2.2.18">Provide to Library and Archives Canada separate electronic copies in English and French of final reports for all  contracted public opinion research projects within 6 months after the completion of any data collection. </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="C" title="Appendix C: Standard on Managing Official Social Media Accounts">
      <appendix anchor="C.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="C.1.1">This standard takes effect on March 27, 2025.</clause>
          <clause anchor="C.1.2">
            This standard replaces the 
            <em>Mandatory Procedures for Social Media and  Web Communications</em>
            , May 11, 2016.
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="C.2">
        <title>Standards</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="C.2.1">
            This standard provides details on the requirements set out in subsections 4.1.35 to  4.1.36 of the 
            <em>Directive on the Management of Communications and Federal  Identity</em>
            .
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="C.2.2">
            Standards are as follows:
    
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="C.2.2.1">Seek the approval of the head of communications to create all official social media  accounts.</clause>
              <clause anchor="C.2.2.2">
                Adhere  to the 
                <a href="https://gcxgce.sharepoint.com/teams/10001402/SitePages/Prescribed-Processes-for-Official-Social-Media-Accounts.aspx">Prescribed Processes for Official Social  Media Accounts</a>
                 (accessible  only on the Government of Canada network) outlined by Service Canada.
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="C.2.2.3">
                Use  the official social media management tool administered by Service Canada:
        
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="C.2.2.3.1">to manage official social media accounts; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="C.2.2.3.2">to collect social media analytics to evaluate and optimize the effectiveness of  content.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
              <clause anchor="C.2.2.4">Include a link to a social media notice from the official social media account profile.</clause>
              <clause anchor="C.2.2.5">Manage official social media accounts throughout all stages of the life cycle, from  planning to disposal.</clause>
            </clauses>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="D" title="Appendix D: Standard on External-facing Websites and Mobile  Applications">
      <appendix anchor="D.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="D.1.1">This standard takes effect on March 27, 2025.</clause>
          <clause anchor="D.1.2">
            This standard replaces the 
            <em>Mandatory  Procedures for Social Media and Web Communications</em>
            , May 11, 2016.
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="D.2">
        <title>Standards</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="D.2.1">
            This standard provides details on the requirements set out in subsections 4.1.37 to 4.1.40 of the 
            <em>Directive on the Management of Communications and Federal Identity</em>
            .
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="D.2.2">
            Standards are as follows:

     
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>External-facing  websites</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="D.2.2.1">
                  Prepare external-facing websites in accordance with the 
                  <a href="https://design.canada.ca/specifications.html">Canada.ca  Specifications</a>
                  .
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="D.2.2.2">
                  Evaluate and optimize the effectiveness of external-facing web content:
        
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="D.2.2.2.1">using data collected by the official web  analytics tool of the Government of Canada. </clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Mobile applications</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="D.2.2.3">Follow the prescribed processes for mobile  applications outlined by Service Canada.</clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
    <appendix anchor="E" title="Appendix E: Definitions">
      <p>
        Definitions  to be used in the interpretation of this directive can be found in 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=30683#appA">
          Appendix A  of the 
          <em>Policy on Communications and  Federal Identity</em>
        </a>
        .
      </p>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
</doc>
