<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Directive on the Duty to Accommodate</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=32634", title: "Directive on the Duty to Accommodate"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=32634&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2021-07-16",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Directive on the Duty to Accommodate</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.1</span>This directive takes effect on April 1, 2020.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.2</span>This directive replaces the <em>Policy on the Duty to Accommodate Persons with Disabilities in the Federal Public Service</em> dated June 3, 2002.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Authorities</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1</span>This directive is issued pursuant to the same authorities indicated in section 2 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Objectives and expected results</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1</span>In addition to the objectives indicated in section 3 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>, the objective of this directive is to develop an inclusive, barrier‑free workplace in which all persons have equal access to opportunities in the core public administration.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2</span>In addition to the expected results indicated in section 3 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>, the expected results of this directive are as follows:

	<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.1</span>Candidates for employment and persons employed are treated with dignity and respect in an inclusive, barrier‑free environment;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.2</span>When barriers cannot be removed, individuals are accommodated up to the point of undue hardship, taking into consideration issues of health, safety and cost; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2.3</span>Accommodations are made based on the circumstances of each case while the individual’s right to privacy and confidentiality are respected. </li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Requirements</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1</span>The head of human resources is responsible for the following: 
  
	<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1</span>Ensuring that candidates for employment and persons employed are informed of: 
    
		<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1.1</span>Their right to accommodation under the<em> Canadian Human Rights Act</em>; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1.2</span>Any mandatory procedures to be followed when seeking an accommodation;</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2</span>Ensuring that managers and supervisors are informed about their responsibilities and obligations with regard to:
    
		<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.1</span>Addressing individuals’ accommodation needs with regard to work‑related policies, practices, systems or procedures that exclude or hinder their full and equal participation in employment in the core public administration; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2.2</span>The relevant confidentiality and privacy considerations.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2</span>Managers and supervisors are responsible for the following: 
  
	<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.1</span>Maintaining the dignity and respect of persons employed by addressing their work‑related needs without resorting to a formal request for accommodation, to the extent reasonable;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.2</span>Satisfying the employer’s legal obligation to accommodate an individual’s needs when they stem from one of the grounds prohibited by the <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>, up to the point of undue hardship and in a timely manner;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.3</span>Providing persons employed with work‑related information, including on employment opportunities, in accessible formats;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.4</span>Identifying the resources necessary to fulfill their duty to accommodate in their business and human resources plans; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.5</span>Ensuring that accommodation arrangements are reviewed and updated at least annually;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.6</span>Ensuring that persons employed are informed that they have a responsibility to respect the accommodation requirements and privacy of others; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.7</span>Restricting access to any information about an individual’s request for accommodation to the people who have a need to know. The type of information required will depend on the specific facts of each case; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.8</span>Retaining a written record of the accommodation in accordance with relevant information management requirements, when appropriate;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.9</span>Ensuring that the needs of individuals who may require accommodation are taken into consideration when planning or designing work‑related processes, events or conferences; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.10</span>Consulting persons employed when there are changes to physical structures, systems or equipment so that the workplace remains barrier‑free.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3</span>Persons employed are responsible for the following:
  
	<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.1</span>Informing their manager of their functional limitations or their work‑related needs;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.2</span>Providing their manager with the information necessary to identify appropriate accommodation, including information on relevant limitations and restrictions;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.3</span>Cooperating and collaborating in good faith with their organization’s representative(s) to find one or more means to accommodate such needs, taking into consideration issues of health, safety and cost;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.4</span>Notifying their manager if their accommodation needs change; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.5</span>Respecting the accommodation requirements and privacy of others.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Roles of other government organizations</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1</span>This section identifies the roles of other key government organizations in relation to this directive. In and of itself, this section does not confer any authority.
 </li></ul><section><header><h3>Canadian Human Rights Commission</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2</span>The Canadian Human Rights Commission is responsible for administering the <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>, including the process for handling complaints of discrimination under the prohibited grounds of race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, marital status, family status, genetic characteristics, disability, and a conviction for an offence for which a pardon has been granted or in respect of which a record suspension has been ordered.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Canadian Human Rights Tribunal</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.3</span>The Canadian Human Rights Tribunal is responsible for adjudicating complaints referred to it by the Canadian Human Rights Commission, related to the prohibited grounds of discrimination.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Federal Public Sector Labour Relations and Employment Board</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.4</span>The Federal Public Sector Labour Relations and Employment Board is responsible for adjudicating labour relations complaints related to issues such as refusals of accommodation and situations in which employees believe that they have not received appropriate accommodation.</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Public Service Commission of Canada</h3></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.5</span>The Public Service Commission of Canada is responsible for the following: 
  
	<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.5.1</span>Identifying and eliminating barriers in recruitment and staffing; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.5.2</span>Providing guidance on accommodation in staffing processes. </li></ul></li></ul></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Application</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.1</span>This directive applies to the persons employed and the organizations listed in section 6 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.1</span>Legislation
  
	<ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/h-6/"><em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/e-5.401/"><em>Employment Equity Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/index.html"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.2</span>Related policy instruments
  
	<ul><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26164"><em>Directive on Official Languages for Communications and Services</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for People Management</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12044"><em>Accessibility Standard for Real Property</em></a></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.1</span>For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>.</li></ul></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix: Mandatory Procedures for the Duty to Accommodate</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.1">A.1 Effective date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.1</span>These mandatory procedures take effect on April 1, 2020.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.2">A.2 Procedures</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.1</span>These mandatory procedures provide details on the requirements set out in section 4 of the <em>Directive on the Duty to Accommodate</em>.


	 <section><header><h4>Candidates seeking employment</h4></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2</span>With regard to subsection 4.2, the mandatory procedures for managers when dealing with candidates are as follows:
  <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.1</span>If, after being informed of their right to accommodation under the <em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em>, a candidate identifies an accommodation need, clarify with the candidate the nature of the barrier and the associated implications;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.2</span>Obtain from the candidate the necessary information and documentation about any limitations or restrictions and, if applicable, any relevant professional assessments or recommendations;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.3</span>Consult appropriate subject matter experts with regard to the accommodation measure(s), if required;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.4</span>Inform the candidate about the proposed accommodation measure(s); and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.5</span>Retain a record of the accommodation requested and provided in the appropriate departmental records.</li></ul></li></ul></section><section><header><h4>Persons employed</h4></header><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3</span>With regard to subsection 4.2, the mandatory procedures for managers of persons employed are as follows:
  <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.1</span>If a person employed has indicated a work-related need, clarify the nature of the barrier and the associated implications with the person employed;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.2</span>Determine in consultation with the person employed whether the work-related need can be addressed without resorting to a formal request for accommodation, e.g., temporary change in hours of work, alternate work location, no costs associated with solution;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.3</span>Obtain from the person information and documentation about any limitations or restrictions and, if applicable, any relevant professional assessments or recommendations;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.4</span>Request additional information from the individual or obtain the individual’s consent prior to seeking information from a medical practitioner or other relevant third party, in support of a request for accommodation;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.5</span>Consult internal subject matter experts with regard to the accommodation measure(s), including any related implications (e.g., security, technology, financial), if required;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.6</span>Work with employee representatives when accommodation affects other individuals or if the person employed being accommodated requests that employee representatives be consulted;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.7</span>Inform the person about the proposed accommodation measure(s);</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.8</span>Provide training to individuals who have been accommodated on the use of any adjusted equipment or systems;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.9</span>Communicate information about the accommodation with the individual’s colleagues only when necessary and only with the consent of the individual;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.10</span>Retain a record of the accommodation requested and provided in the appropriate departmental records; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.11"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.11</span>Allow persons employed to retain technical aids, equipment and support materials if they move to another position in the core public administration and still require that accommodation.</li></ul></li></ul></section></li></ul></div></section></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2020, <br/>ISBN:                  </p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>