<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification" documentID="14219" versionID="11" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date"><clauses><clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on July 8, 2023.</clause><clause anchor="1.2">This directive replaces the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14219"><em>Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification</em></a> dated April 1, 2021.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities"><clauses><clause anchor="2.1">This directive is issued pursuant to the authorities indicated in section 2 of the <em>Policy on the Management of Executives</em>.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="Objectives and expected results"><clauses><clause anchor="3.1">The objectives of this directive are as follows:
  <clauses><clause anchor="3.1.1">To ensure that organizational design and classification activities in the Executive (EX) Group are well managed; and</clause><clause anchor="3.1.2">To safeguard the integrity of EX Group classification.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="3.2">The expected results of this directive are as follows:
  <clauses><clause anchor="3.2.1">Executive organizational structures are designed and managed to support the delivery of organizational mandates; and</clause><clause anchor="3.2.2">EX Group positions are classified consistently across the core public administration.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="Requirements"><clauses><clause anchor="4.1">Heads of human resources are responsible for complying with standards and mandatory procedures associated with the requirements set out in the Appendices of this directive, and:
  <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.1">Approving classification actions on behalf of the deputy head;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.2">Ensuring the recommendations to the deputy head on the creation and classification of EX Group positions are in accordance with this Directive;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.3">Ensuring that classification decisions are documented promptly, accurately and completely in:
    <clauses><clause anchor="4.1.3.1">Classification files;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.3.2">Organizational human resources information management systems; and</clause><clause anchor="4.1.3.3">Information management systems identified by the Chief Human Resources Officer;</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="4.1.4">Ensuring that employees in the EX Group are notified each time a classification decision is rendered for the position they occupy;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.5">Ensuring that persons who provide advice on EX Group classification have experience in classification and have completed the required training on the <em>Executive Group Job Evaluation Standard</em>;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.6">Consulting the Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer when a classification decision is contentious, precedent setting, or may impact inter‑organizational relativity;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.7">Consulting the Chief Financial Officer when creating or reclassifying any EX-04 and EX-05 positions;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.8">Ensuring that positions that have assistant deputy head status are classified in accordance with Appendix C; </clause><clause anchor="4.1.9">Ensuring that associate assistant deputy head positions are classified in accordance with Appendix D;</clause><clause anchor="4.1.10">Ensuring an internal process is established to review the creation or the reclassification of EX-04 and EX-05 positions; and</clause><clause anchor="4.1.11">Ensuring an internal process is established for the resolution of disagreements in EX Group classification decisions. </clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="4.2">The Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer is responsible for:
  <clauses><clause anchor="4.2.1">Providing advice and guidance on the evaluation of EX Group positions;</clause><clause anchor="4.2.2">Providing oversight, monitoring, and reporting activities on the overall health of the Classification Program for EX Group positions; and </clause><clause anchor="4.2.3">Informing deputy heads of cases of non-compliance with this Directive, the <em>Policy on the Management of Executives</em>, or with the <em>Executive Group Job Evaluation Standard</em> and directing them to take appropriate corrective actions where required.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="Roles of other government organizations"><clauses><clause anchor="5.1">The roles of other government organizations in relation to this directive are described in section 5 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="6" title="Application"><clauses><clause anchor="6.1">This directive applies to the organizations described in section 6 of the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12572"><em>Policy on the Management of Executives</em></a>.</clause><clause anchor="6.2">This directive applies to positions classified in the EX Group in the core public administration.</clause><clause anchor="6.3">This directive does not apply to persons appointed by the Governor in Council, to members of the RCMP, or to members of the Canadian Armed Forces.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="7" title="References"><clauses><clause anchor="7.1">Legislation
  <ul><li><a href="https://www.laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/p-4.2/"><em>Pay Equity Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/p-33.01/"><em>Public Service Employment Act</em></a></li></ul></clause><clause anchor="7.2">Related policy instruments
  <ul><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25583"><em>Policy on the Management of Executives</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32621"><em>Policy on People Management</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=28699"><em>Directive on Classification Oversight</em></a></li><li><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=28698"><em>Directive on Classification Grievances</em></a></li></ul></clause><clause anchor="7.3">Other
  <ul><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/collective-agreements/job-evaluation/executive-group-position-evaluation-plan-2022.html"><em>Executive Group Job Evaluation Standard</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/collective-agreements/occupational-groups/executive.html#grp-ex">Executive (EX) Group definition</a></li></ul></clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="8" title="Enquiries"><clauses><clause anchor="8.1">Human resources advisors should direct enquiries about this directive to their departmental human resources office.</clause><clause anchor="8.2">For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact <a href="mailto:questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>.</clause></clauses></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A: Standard on Classification for Executive (EX) Group Positions"><appendix anchor="A.1"><title>
	Standards
	</title><clauses><clause anchor="A.1.1">This standard provides details on the requirements set out in section 4.1 of the <em>Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification.</em></clause><clause anchor="A.1.2">Standards are as follows:
  <clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1">The classification file must include the following:
		 
		 <section><header><h4>Job descriptions</h4></header><clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1">Job descriptions must:
  <clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1.1">Describe the duties and responsibilities of the job concisely, using bias free language;</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1.2">Contain the information required to evaluate the job using the <em>Executive Group Job Evaluation Standard</em>, including:
    <ul><li>General accountability;</li><li>Organization structure;</li><li>Nature and scope of duties;</li><li>Dimensions; and</li><li>Specific accountabilities;</li></ul></clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1.3">Contain the following identifying information:
    <ul><li>Position title;</li><li>Position group and level;</li><li>Organization;</li><li>Branch/division;</li><li>Position number;</li><li>Geographic location; and</li><li>National Occupational Classification (NOC) code;</li></ul></clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1.4">Be updated and evaluated within one year when affected by significant changes, including but not limited to mandate, organizational structure, dimensions or reporting relationships;</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1.5">Be authorized, signed and dated by the immediate manager (when the position reports to the deputy head, the deputy head must authorize, sign and date the job description); and</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.1.6">Indicate the effective date.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h4>Organizational charts </h4></header><clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.2">Organizational charts must:  
  <clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.2.1">Depict the organizational location of the position and its relationship to the other positions in the same work unit;</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.2.2">Represent the organizational structure described in the job description; and</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.2.3">Be authorized, signed and dated by the immediate manager (when the position reports to the deputy head, the deputy head must authorize, sign and date the organizational chart).</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h4>Job evaluation rationale</h4></header><clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.3">The job evaluation rationale must:
  <clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.3.1">Provide the justification for occupational group allocation;</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.3.2">Identify and justify the degrees and points chosen for each factor and sub‑factor;</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.3.3">Include a comparative analysis of the position to the benchmarks in the <em>Executive Group Job Evaluation Standard</em>; and</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.3.4">Include an analysis of the relevant organizational and inter-organizational relativity used to confirm the decision; and</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.3.5">Be signed and dated by the evaluator(s).</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h4>Classification action form</h4></header><clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.4">The classification action form must:
  <clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.4.1">Describe the nature of the action or decision;</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.4.2">Identify the ratings and effective date; and</clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.4.3">Be signed and dated by the deputy head or, in the case of classification actions, be signed and dated by the head of human resources.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section><section><header><h4>Other items</h4></header><clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.5">Other items included in the classification file may include the following:
   <clauses><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.5.1">Information that substantiates the selection of the effective date; and
     </clause><clause anchor="A.1.2.1.5.2">Any other data, reports or information that substantiate the classification decision.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></section></clause></clauses></clause></clauses></appendix></appendix><appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B: Mandatory Procedures for Executive (EX) Group Classification Actions and Decisions"><appendix anchor="B.1"><title>Procedures</title><clauses><clause anchor="B.1.1">These procedures provide details on the requirements set out in section 4.1 of the <em>Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification</em>.</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2">Mandatory procedures are as follows:
  <clauses><clause anchor="B.1.2.1">For each classification action and decision, the following actions must be completed:
    <clauses><clause anchor="B.1.2.1.1">Each classification action and decision must be documented in the classification file in accordance with Appendix A;</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2.1.2">Data on the classification action and decision must be entered into the organizational human resources information management system; and</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2.1.3">Data and documentation on the classification action and decision must be uploaded to the information management systems identified by the Chief Human Resources Officer.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="B.1.2.2">In addition to the procedures described in subsection B.1.2.1, for each reclassification, the following actions must be completed:
    <clauses><clause anchor="B.1.2.2.1">Job descriptions must be updated and evaluated within one year of changes that result in the reclassification of a position;</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2.2.2">The evaluation rationale must include a justification for the reclassification of the existing position instead of the creation of a new position, and the effective date;</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2.2.3">A statement must be included in the classification file that summarizes the evolution of the work; and</clause><clause anchor="B.1.2.2.4">Classification decisions on the reclassification of occupied positions must be <a href="https://open.canada.ca/en/proactive-disclosure">proactively disclosed</a>.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></clause></clauses></appendix></appendix><appendix anchor="C" title="Appendix C: Standard on Positions That Have Assistant Deputy Head Status"><appendix anchor="C.1"><title>Standards</title><clauses><clause anchor="C.1.1">This standard provides details on the requirements set out in subsection 4.1.8 of the <em>Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification</em>.</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2">Standards are as follows:
  <clauses><clause anchor="C.1.2.1">Classified positions that have assistant deputy head status:
    <clauses><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.1">Report directly to the deputy head or the associate deputy head;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.2">Sustain classification at the EX‑04 or EX‑05 level;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.3">Are delegated a significant part of the deputy head’s authority;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.4">Hold accountability for the results and outcomes of their programs, including the means and resources employed;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.5">Reflect full responsibility for advising the deputy head and the Minister on policies for areas they direct;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.6">Reflect participation on the organization’s senior management committee;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.7">Are delegated a level of signing authority that is second only to the deputy head’s for particular areas of organizational operations and priorities;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.8">Have the authority to communicate publicly on their programs and, as required, on all the organization’s activities; and</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.1.9">Have titles that reflect the organization’s operating mode and the deputy head’s own title. Such titles include Assistant Deputy Minister, Vice-President, Deputy Commissioner, Deputy Secretary or Assistant Secretary.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.2">Classified positions that have senior assistant deputy head titles:
    <clauses><clause anchor="C.1.2.2.1">Sustain classification at the EX‑05 level and direct an operation that is a major program or function of the organization;</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.2.2">Do not impact the deputy head’s delegation of authority to other assistant deputy heads or their accountability to the deputy head; and</clause><clause anchor="C.1.2.2.3">May, in exceptional circumstances or to resolve cross‑jurisdictional issues, coordinate the work of other assistant deputy heads to reduce the burden on the deputy head.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></clause></clauses></appendix></appendix><appendix anchor="D" title="Appendix D: Standard on Evaluating Associate Assistant Deputy Head Positions"><appendix anchor="D.1"><title>Standards</title><clauses><clause anchor="D.1.1">This standard provides details on the requirements set out in subsection 4.1.9 of the <em>Directive on Executive (EX) Group Organization and Classification</em>.</clause><clause anchor="D.1.2">Standards are as follows:
  <clauses><clause anchor="D.1.2.1">An associate assistant deputy head position:
    <clauses><clause anchor="D.1.2.1.1">Must sustain classification at the EX‑04 level;</clause><clause anchor="D.1.2.1.2">Shares the mandate, delegated authority and accountability of an existing EX‑05 position of exceptional size and complexity where both positions report to the same deputy head or associate deputy head and comprise a single shared point of accountability in a program or policy sector that cannot feasibly be subdivided;</clause><clause anchor="D.1.2.1.3">Does not constitute an additional hierarchical level below the deputy head or associate deputy head;</clause><clause anchor="D.1.2.1.4">Is normally limited to a specified period; and</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="D.1.2.2">The EX‑05 position is ultimately accountable for all program and policy decisions within the mandate.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></appendix></appendix><appendix anchor="E" title="Appendix E: Definitions"><p>Definitions to be used in the interpretation of this directive can be found in this appendix, in the <em>Policy on People Management</em>, and in the <em>Policy on the Management of Executives</em>.</p><dl><dt>classification action (<span lang="fr-CA">Action de classification</span>)</dt><dd>A classification activity that does not require a new classification decision and does not have an impact on the position’s surrounding organizational structure.</dd><dt>classification decision (<span lang="fr-CA">Décision de classification</span>)</dt><dd>A decision made by the deputy head, a senior official designated by the deputy head for classification grievances purposes, or an accredited person exercising classification authority, which establishes or confirms the occupational group, subgroup (if applicable), level, or ratings assigned to a job.</dd><dt>Job evaluation rationale <span lang="fr-CA">(justification de l’évaluation de l’emploi)</span></dt><dd>A document that substantiates a classification decision as a result of a detailed analysis and evaluation of duties using the appropriate job evaluation standard.</dd></dl></appendix></appendices></doc>