<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Directive on Performance Management" documentID="27146" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="Effective date">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="1.1">This directive takes effect on April 1, 2020.</clause>
        <clause anchor="1.2">
          This directive replaces the 
          <em>
            <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32644">Directive on Performance Management</a>
          </em>
           dated April 1, 2014.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="Authorities">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="2.1">
          The directive is issued pursuant to the same authorities indicated in section 2 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="Objective and expected results">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="3.1">
          The objective indicated in section 3 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
           applies to this directive.
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="3.2">
          The expected results indicated in section 3 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
           apply to this directive.
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="Requirements">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="4.1">
          The head of human resources is responsible for the following:
			
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.1.1">Administering performance and talent management programs in a fair and consistent manner in accordance with this directive and guidance from the Chief Human Resources Officer, Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.2">Determining, in consultation with the deputy head, the departmental criteria for talent management plans in accordance with the appendix to this directive;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.3">Establishing an organizational review panel or panels and setting the terms of reference to oversee employee performance and annually assess the quality of the organization's performance and talent management programs in accordance with the appendix to this directive; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.4">Ensuring that managers have guidance and support to implement their department's performance and talent management programs; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.1.5">
              Maintaining records on performance and talent management for all employees in accordance with the 
              <em>Privacy Act</em>
              , using the system(s) prescribed by the Chief Human Resources Officer.
            </clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="4.2">
          Managers are responsible for the following:
			
          <clauses>
            <clause anchor="4.2.1">Conducting regular formal and ongoing informal performance discussions with each employee in accordance with each employee'_'s language of work rights; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.2">Establishing an annual performance agreement with each employee;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.3">Establishing an annual learning and development plan with each employee;</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.4">Supporting employees to perform effectively; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.5">Assessing performance and assigning performance ratings annually; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.6">Recognizing performance, both formally and informally; </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.7">
              Monitoring and reporting on the probationary periods of new employees in accordance with the 
              <em>Regulations Establishing Periods of Probation</em>
               and 
              <em>Periods of Notice of Termination of Employment During Probation</em>
              ;
            </clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.8">Establishing and supporting talent management plans for employees in accordance with the appendix to this directive; and</clause>
            <clause anchor="4.2.9">Establishing and implementing a performance improvement plan for employees whose performance is unsatisfactory, in accordance with the appendix to this directive.</clause>
          </clauses>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="4.3">Employees are responsible for actively participating in their organization's performance management program in accordance with the appendix to this directive.  </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="Roles of other government organizations">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="5.1">
          The roles of other government organizations in relation to this directive are described in section 5 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          .
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="Application">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="6.1">
          This directive applies to the persons and organizations listed in section 6 of the 
          <em>Policy on People Management</em>
          . 
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="References">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="7.1">
          Legislation
		
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/e-5.401/index.html">Employment  Equity Act</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-33.3/">Federal  Public Sector Labour Relations Act</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/page-1.html">Financial  Administration Act</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/">Official Languages Act</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/">Privacy Act</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-33.01/index.html">Public Service  Employment Act</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-2005-375/page-1.html">Regulations  Establishing Periods of Probation and Periods of Notice of Termination of  Employment During Probation</a>
              </em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="7.2">
          Related policy instruments
			
          <ul>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12754">Directive on  Information Management Roles and Responsibilities</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16552">Directive  on Recordkeeping</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12742">Policy on  Information Management</a>
              </em>
            </li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26160">Policy on Official  Languages</a>
              </em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
        <clause anchor="7.3">
          Other
			
          <ul>
            <li>Collective agreements</li>
            <li>
              <em>
                <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=22379">Guidelines for  Termination or Demotion for Unsatisfactory Performance; Termination or Demotion  for Reasons Other than Breaches of Discipline or Misconduct; and Termination of  Employment During Probation</a>
              </em>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="Enquiries">
      <clauses>
        <clause anchor="8.1">
          For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact 
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>
          . 
        </clause>
      </clauses>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix: Standard on Performance Management">
      <appendix anchor="A.1">
        <title>Effective date</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.1.1">This standard takes effect on April 1, 2020.</clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
      <appendix anchor="A.2">
        <title>Standards</title>
        <clauses>
          <clause anchor="A.2.1">
            This standard provides details on the requirements set out in section 4 of the 
            <em>Directive on Performance Management</em>
            . 
          </clause>
          <clause anchor="A.2.2">
            Standards are as follows:
			  
			  
            <header>
              <h4>Performance agreement</h4>
            </header>
            <clauses>
              <clause anchor="A.2.2.1">
                Performance agreements must include:
					
                <clauses>
                  <clause anchor="A.2.2.1.1">Clear and measurable work objectives, with associated performance measures, that are linked to the priorities of the organization and of the Government of Canada;</clause>
                  <clause anchor="A.2.2.1.2">Observable and measurable expected behaviours; </clause>
                  <clause anchor="A.2.2.1.3">A learning and development plan; and</clause>
                  <clause anchor="A.2.2.1.4">Sign-off by the manager and employee acknowledging that the content of the performance agreement has been discussed.</clause>
                </clauses>
              </clause>
            </clauses>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Mid-year review</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.2">
                  A mid year performance review must include:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.2.1">A review of progress against established work objectives;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.2.2">A review of whether the employee is demonstrating the expected behaviours;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.2.3">A review of learning and development needs and activities; </clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.2.4">Amendments to the performance agreement and learning and development plan, as required; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.2.5">Sign-off by the manager and employee acknowledging that the content of the mid year review has been discussed.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Performance assessment</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.3">
                  The performance assessment must include:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.3.1">A narrative assessment of performance that supports the assigned performance rating(s); and </clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.3.2">Sign-off by the manager and employee acknowledging that the content of the performance assessment has been discussed.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Learning and development plan</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.4">
                  A learning and development plan must be developed for each employee and include:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.4.1">Employee career goals and aspirations; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.4.2">Planned activities that support the achievement of the employee_s established work objectives, expected behaviours and continuous development.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Talent management</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.5">
                  A talent management plan must be initiated when:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.5.1">Prescribed by the organization's performance and talent management program;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.5.2">Prescribed for the functional community to which the employee belongs;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.5.3">Required to support ongoing high performance; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.5.4">Mutually agreed upon by the manager and employee.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.6">
                  A talent management plan must identify the:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.6.1">Employee's career goals and aspirations;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.6.2">Employee's strengths and areas for development; </clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.6.3">Activities to support the continued development of the employee; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.6.4">A timeline and milestones against which to measure the employee's progress.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Performance improvement plan</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.7">
                  A performance improvement plan must be initiated when:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.7.1">Employee performance does not meet expectations; or</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.7.2">Any time the manager determines that a performance issue needs to be documented.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.8">
                  A performance improvement plan must include:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.8.1">Specific areas for improvement;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.8.2">Actions that will be taken by the employee to address the identified areas needing improvement;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.8.3">Description of the support that will be provided by the manager to the employee to improve performance; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.8.4">A timeline and milestones against which to measure the employee's progress.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
            <section>
              <header>
                <h4>Departmental review panels</h4>
              </header>
              <clauses>
                <clause anchor="A.2.2.9">
                  Departmental review panels will undertake the following:
					
                  <clauses>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.1">Ensuring that performance and talent management initiatives in the organization are conducted fairly and consistently;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.2">At least annually, reviewing data on the organization_s management of performance and talent, including progress made against individual action plans for improvement;</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.3">Making recommendations to recognize exceptional performance, as applicable, in accordance with the organizational recognition program; and</clause>
                    <clause anchor="A.2.2.9.4">Making recommendations to the deputy head and head of human resources to improve the organization's performance and talent management programs, as appropriate.</clause>
                  </clauses>
                </clause>
              </clauses>
            </section>
          </clause>
        </clauses>
      </appendix>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
</doc>
