<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Directive on Telework</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=32636", title: "Directive on Telework"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=32636&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2025-04-01",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Directive on Telework</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.1</span>This directive takes effect on April 1, 2025.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.2</span>This directive replaces the <em>Telework Policy</em> dated December 9, 1999.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Authorities</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1</span>This directive is issued pursuant to the same authorities indicated in section 2 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>. </li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Objectives and expected results</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1</span>The objectives indicated in section 3 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em> apply to this directive.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2</span>The expected results indicated in section 3 of the Policy on People Management apply to this directive.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Requirements</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1</span>The head of human resources is responsible for the following:
  <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1</span>Ensuring that managers and employees are informed that participation in telework is voluntary and that employees are not required to telework;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2</span>Identifying and assessing any relevant considerations, in collaboration with other senior officials in the areas of occupational health and safety, security, cyber security, privacy, information technology, information management, values and ethics, conflict of interest, financial management and material management; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.3</span>Providing information, procedures and practices about entering into a telework agreement to employees and managers, and making them readily available; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.4</span>Providing employees and managers information, training, procedures, and practices about departmental occupational health and safety policy and program and their responsibilities when teleworking;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.5</span>Establishing organizational criteria to distinguish between telework arrangements and ad hoc telework; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.6</span>Informing employees and managers that telework arrangements are subject to review and may be modified or terminated by either party at any time, with reasonable notice. </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2</span>Delegated managers are responsible for the following:
  <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.1</span>Entering into a telework agreement only where an employee’s participation is voluntary;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.2</span>Respecting departmental processes and procedures when making a decision to enter into a telework agreement with an employee;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.3</span>Considering the impacts of a proposed telework arrangement on operational requirements before approving an employee’s telework request;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.4</span>Assessing an employee’s request to telework on a case-by--case basis and that the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the requester;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.5</span>Validating the employee is aware of the departmental health and safety policy and program requirements when teleworking;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.6</span>Validating the employee is aware and knows how to report immediately to the supervisor any accident, injury, occurrence of harassment and violence related to work; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.7</span>Assuming the costs associated with the equipment deemed necessary to perform the work safely when teleworking as determined by the departmental occupational health and safety policy and program; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.8</span>Validating the employee is aware of their security responsibilities and informed on how to minimize security risks; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.9</span>Completing a telework agreement in accordance with the Standard on Telework Agreements in the appendix to this directive, and retained in accordance with the appropriate departmental information management policies and procedures prior to the commencement of a telework agreement;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.10</span>Reviewing telework agreements with employees at a minimum on an annual basis.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3</span>Employees who wish to participate in a telework arrangement are responsible for the following:
  <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.1</span>Requesting a telework agreement, in accordance with the processes and procedures established by their organization;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.2</span>Protecting, safeguarding, managing records, personal and sensitive information in accordance with the Government of Canada privacy, security, and information management legislation and policies; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.3</span>Adhering to government security policy and departmental security practices to effectively safeguard information, assets and individuals; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.4</span>Informing their manager immediately in the event that any information or Crown assets are lost, stolen or damaged;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.5</span>Maintaining vigilance and reporting changes in circumstances, potential security deficiencies, security incidents, suspected criminal activity, and other security issues through appropriate departmental channels;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.6</span>Respecting the relevant terms and conditions of their employment, their collective agreement, legislation, and Treasury Board and departmental policies while at the telework location;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.7</span>Adhering to departmental health and safety policy and program, including at their telework location;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.8</span>Reporting immediately, in accordance with the departmental health and safety policy and program, any accidents, incidents of harassment or violence, or any other event that has caused or could cause injury, illness, or harassment and violence during work;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.9</span>Assuming all costs related to their telework location such as, but not limited to, utilities, appropriate insurance, internet and any equipment not provided by the employer.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Roles of other government organizations</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1</span>Not applicable</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Application</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.1</span>This directive applies to the employees and organizations listed in section 6 of the <em>Policy on People Management</em>. For greater certainty, this directive also applies to students, casuals, and part-time workers. </li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.1</span>Legislation 
<ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><em><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/L-2/page-23.html#h-341197">Canada Labour Code, Part II</a></em> and associated Regulations</li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-86-304/index.html"><em>Canada Occupational Health and Safety Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/h-6/"><em>Canadian Human Rights Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/f-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-5/"><em>Government Employees Compensation Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/index.html"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/e-5.401/index.html"><em>Employment Equity Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/page-1.html"><em>Official Languages Act</em></a><em> </em></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.2</span>Related policy instruments
<ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32691"><em>Directive on the Management of Real Property</em> which includes the Standard on Barrier-Free Access to Real Property</a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578"><em>Policy on Government Security</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32603"><em>Policy on Service and Digital</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593"><em>Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32690"><em>Directive on the Management of Materiel</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495"><em>Policy on Financial Management</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27228"><em>Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18309"><em>Directive on Privacy Practices</em></a></li><li><em>Directive on Security Management</em></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26160"><em>Policy on Official Languages</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for People Management</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049"><em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32627"><em>Directive on the Conflict of Interest</em></a></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.1</span>For interpretation of any aspect of this directive, contact <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html#enquiries">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>.</li></ul></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix A: Standard on Telework Agreements</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.1">A.1 Effective date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.1</span>This standard takes effect on April 1, 2025.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.2">A.2 Standards</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.1</span>This standard provides details on the minimum requirements for a telework agreement as set out in subsection 4.2.9 of the <em>Directive on Telework.</em></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2</span>The telework agreement must include, at a minimum, the following details:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.1</span>Telework agreement information:
      <ul><li>Name; </li><li>Occupational group and level;</li><li>Position; </li><li>The address of the designated worksite. </li><li>The address of the primary telework location;</li><li>The address of any supplemental telework location(s) (if applicable);</li><li>The start and end date of the telework agreement;</li><li>The telework schedule;</li><li>A list of the equipment supplied by the employer;</li><li>Employee’s contact information at the telework location; and</li><li>Manager’s name.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.2</span>Acknowledgement from the employee that:
      <ul><li>telework is a voluntary flexible work arrangement that can be modified or terminated by either party with reasonable notice. Modifications or terminations to the telework agreement must be provided in writing;</li><li>the telework agreement must be reviewed on an annual basis at minimum;</li><li>they are responsible for reporting to their designated worksite on their own time and at their own expense;</li><li>telework is not a substitute for taking the appropriate leave, such as elder care, childcare, or other family related responsibilities. The employee is expected to have arrangements in place during working hours;</li><li>they have appropriate internet services (secure, high speed, reliable);</li><li>they are aware of any applicable departmental procedures to be followed in the event of an interruption of network or internet connectivity, such as consulting with their manager, performing tasks that do not require network connectivity (where possible), reporting to the designated worksite, or taking appropriate leave.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.3</span>Attestation from the employee that:
      <ul><li>they are expected to uphold the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049"><em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em></a> and comply with the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32627"><em>Directive on Conflict of Interest</em>;</a></li><li>their telework location is a distraction free environment;</li><li>they have appropriate insurance coverage for their telework location;</li><li>they will assume the cost of equipping and maintaining the telework location, including costs such as utilities, high speed internet and any equipment not provided by the employer.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.4</span>Confirmation from the employee that they have:
      <ul><li>completed or renewed any relevant training as determined by the department prior to entering or renewing a telework agreement, including, but not limited to, privacy, security awareness, health and safety, information management practices, and asset management.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.5</span>Departments should consider developing a health and safety checklist based on their occupational health and safety policy and program for managers to complete. Ensure at least annually:
      <ul><li>that the employee knows how to and can adjust their workstation to meet ergonomic standards in accordance with the departmental program; </li><li>A regular method of communication is established between the employee and manager to ensure that the employee is safe and healthy;</li><li>The manager has an emergency contact for the employee. </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.6</span>An attestation that the employee understands and will comply with government security requirements outlined in the Policy on Government Security and related policy suite as well as departmental security practices at the telework location.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7</span>An attestation that the employee understands and will comply with the applicable requirements of the Privacy Act and related policy suite.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.8</span>An attestation that the employee will comply with cyber security and cyber hygiene requirements.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix B: Interim Standard on Occasional Travel to a Designated Worksite</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.1</span>This interim standard is a pilot and takes effect on June 1, 2023. It will remain in effect until March 31, 2027.
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.1.1</span>This standard may be amended or rescinded at any time.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2</span>Employees are expected to travel to their designated worksite on their own time and at their own expense. Notwithstanding this, pursuant to the Treasury Board <em>Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conferences and Event Expenditures</em>, an employee with a full-time telework agreement pursuant to the <em>Directive on Telework</em> can be placed on travel status under the National Joint Council<em> Travel Directive</em> for the purpose of reporting to the designated worksite subject to the following conditions:
    
      <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.1</span>Eligibility<br /><br /><p>An employee who resides 125 kilometres or more from the designated worksite and who:</p><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.1.1</span>Is excluded or unrepresented, or is a member of a bargaining unit represented by one of the following bargaining agents in the core public administration:
      <ul><li>Public Service Alliance of Canada;</li><li>Professional Institute of the Public Service of Canada;</li><li>Association of Canadian Financial Officers;</li><li>National Police Federation;</li><li>Association of Justice Counsel;</li><li>Professional Association of Foreign Service Officers;</li><li>Canadian Federal Pilots Association;</li><li>Unifor, Local 2182;</li><li>Canadian Association of Professional Employees; or</li><li>International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, Local 2228; and</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.1.2</span>Has a full-time telework agreement signed after March 2020 and who was authorized in writing to move to the telework location at their own expense; or</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.1.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.1.3</span>Has been and continues to work with a full-time telework agreement signed before March 2020; or</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.1.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.1.4</span>Has a full-time telework agreement signed after March 2020 and who normally would have been relocated at Crown expense.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2</span>Exception to 125-kilometre distance<br /><br /><p>A deputy head may authorize an employee mentioned above that does not reside 125 kilometres or more from the designated worksite to be placed on travel status when due to a geographical barrier there is no alternative to using commercial transportation (for example, ferry) to travel from the telework location to the designated worksite and the cost of that transportation is more than $150 for a return trip.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.3</span>Frequency<br /><br /><p>Deputy heads should consider the operational requirements for occasional travel, balancing the frequency of the travel with the cost.</p></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.3</span>Reporting requirements<br /><br /><p>Organizations monitor and report semi-annually on the application of this authority.</p></li></ul><section><header><h3>Definition</h3></header><dl class="dl-horizontal"><dt class="small"><strong>designated worksite </strong></dt><dd>A physical location under the organization’s control. It is  not a virtual location or residential address. The employer determines the  location of the designated worksite associated with each position.</dd></dl></section></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2025, <br/>ISBN: 978-0-660-76821-2</p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>