<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=27228", title: "Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=27228&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2020-07-31",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.1</span>This directive takes effect on <time datetime="2017-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2017</time> and incorporates changes effective as of <time datetime="2020-08-21" class="nowrap">August 1, 2020</time>.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.2</span>This directive replaces the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures dated <time datetime="2013-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2013</time>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Authorities</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1</span>This directive is issued pursuant to section 7 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/page-3.html#h-8">Financial Administration Act</a>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Objectives and expected results</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1</span>The objectives indicated in section 3 of the Policy on Financial Management apply to this directive.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2</span>The expected results indicated in section 3 of the Policy on Financial Management apply to this directive.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Requirements</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1</span>The chief financial officer (CFO) is responsible for the following:
			
					<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1</span>Approving the departmental total annual budgets for travel, hospitality and conferences;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2</span>Disclosing the total annual expenditures for each of travel, hospitality, and conference fees for the department, including the main variances from the previous fiscal year’s actual expenditures. This disclosure is to coincide with the tabling of the Departmental Results Report; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.3</span>Ensuring that the standards for travel, hospitality, conferences and events, set out in <a href="#appA">appendices A</a> to <a href="#appD">D</a>, are clearly communicated to departmental staff.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2</span>Senior departmental managers and delegated managers are responsible for the following within their areas of responsibility:
			
					<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.1</span>Considering in the approval process the means to avoid or minimize travel, hospitality, conference and event costs;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.2</span>Ensuring that travel, hospitality, conference and event expenditures are necessary to support the departmental mandate, operational activities, objectives or priorities; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.3</span>Ensuring that any applicable provisions of legislation, regulation, orders-in-council, National Joint Council directives, collective agreements or Treasury Board–approved instruments are respected in the management of travel, hospitality, conference and event expenditures; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.4</span>Ensuring that standards for travel, hospitality, conferences and events, set out in <a href="#appA">appendices A</a> to <a href="#appD">D</a>, are applied.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Roles of other government organizations</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1</span>Not applicable.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Application</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.1</span>This directive applies to the organizations listed in section 6 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495">Policy on Financial Management</a>.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.2</span>With respect to the Office of the Auditor General, the Office of the Chief Electoral Officer, the Office of the Commissioner of Lobbying of Canada, the Office of the Commissioner of Official Languages, the Office of the Information Commissioner of Canada, the Office of the Privacy Commissioner of Canada and the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner, the deputy heads of these organizations can exercise the ministerial approval authorities in this Directive, including the delegation of approval authorities to the appropriate managers.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.3</span>Appendix B of this directive does not apply to <a href="#hospitality">hospitality</a> governed by the Official Hospitality Outside Canada (OHOC) policy established by Global Affairs Canada and the Heads of Post and Foreign Service Official Hospitality directives.
				</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.1</span>Legislation
			
					<ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">Financial Administration Act – Sections 7 and 9</a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a> (proactive publication requirements outlined in sections 82 and 83)</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.2</span>Other relevant documents
			
					<ul><li><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d3/en">National Joint Council Foreign Service Directives</a></li><li><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d4/en">National Joint Council Isolated Posts and Government Housing Directive</a></li><li><a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d6/en">National Joint Council Relocation Directive</a></li><li><a href="https://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d10/en">National Joint Council Travel Directive</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/travel-relocation/special-travel-authorities.html">Special Travel Authorities</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/serviceshttps://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html">Policies for Ministers’ Offices</a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049">Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/information-notice/conference-2019-01-18.html">Information Bulletin: Conference attendance by members of the Research (RE) group</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.1</span>Members of the public may contact <a href="mailto:questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca">TBS Public Enquiries</a> regarding any questions about this directive.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.2</span>Individuals from departments should contact their departmental financial policy group regarding any questions about this directive.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.3</span>Individuals from a departmental financial policy group may contact <a href="mailto:fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Financial Management Enquiries</a> for interpretation of this directive.</li></ul></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix A: Standard on Travel</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.1">A.1 Effective date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.1</span>This standard takes effect on <time datetime="2016-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2017</time>, and incorporates changes effective as of <time datetime="2020-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2020</time>.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.2</span>This standard replaces the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures, Appendix 1 dated <time datetime="2013-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2013</time>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.2">A.2 Standards</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.1</span>This standard provides details on the requirements set out in sections 4.1 and 4.2 of the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2</span>The CFO is responsible for the following standards:
				
						<section><h4>Planning</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.1</span>Ensuring that travel for both public servants and non-public servants is avoided where appropriate and that travel is cost efficient including:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.1.1</span>Limiting the number of departmental travellers to the minimum necessary to deliver the business of the government; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.1.2</span>Selecting the most economical means of travel when booking transportation, accommodations and meeting facilities;</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.2</span>Ensuring that the travel entitlements under provisions in the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/fsd-dse/index-eng.php">National Joint Council Foreign Service Directives</a>, the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/nrd-drc/index-eng.php">National Joint Council Relocation Directive</a> or the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/ipgh-pile/index-eng.php">National Joint Council Isolated Posts and Government Housing Directive</a> are not subject to travel expenditure initiation under this Appendix. Travel costs authorized by these directives are to be coded in the Government-wide Chart of Accounts solely to those items;
								</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.3</span>Advising ministers and their exempt staff that their travel undertaken in support of departmental business is not subject to travel expenditure initiation under this Appendix;</li></ul></section><section><h4>Travel Authorization (Approval authority required for expenditure initiation)</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.4</span>Ensuring that the travel approval authorities that are delegated below the senior departmental manager level are supported by the following operational needs:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.4.1</span>The program’s operations are regionally or globally dispersed and there is no senior departmental manager present in certain offices;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.4.2</span>The operational requirements for travel are frequent, may involve a significant number of travellers and concentrating approvals with one position would create potential delays; or</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.4.3</span>The potential for delay in obtaining approval could be injurious to the public interest or the timely delivery of departmental services or operations;</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.5</span>Ensuring that travel authorization is exercised in either of the followings ways:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.5.1</span>Approval by the delegated manager for a trip; or</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.5.2</span>Approval by the delegated manager of a travel plan that reasonably covers the authorization elements of Table 1;
				
											<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.5.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.5.2.1</span>Significant changes to trips within the travel plan are to be reapproved by the delegated manager;</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.6</span>Ensuring that travel approval authorities under this directive do not apply to:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.6.1</span>Local travel within the normal office location and surrounding working area of a public servant; or</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.6.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.6.2</span>Travel required to respond rapidly to urgent and unforeseeable events that require public servants or non–public servants to provide expertise or delivery of departmental programs or services to safeguard health, safety and security;
				
											<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.6.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.6.2.1</span>Expenditure initiation approval for such emergency travel can be authorized by the appropriate fund centre manager with subsequent disclosure of the travel costs to the deputy head;  </li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7</span>Ensuring that the following categories of travel are identified as part of the travel authorization for each proposed trip:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7.1</span>Operational activities - Travel required to support the department’s operational activities (other than the following categories), legislative or legal requirements;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7.2</span>Key stakeholders - Travel necessary to engage key stakeholders in relation to such matters as policy, program or regulatory development or renewal;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7.3</span>Internal governance - Travel necessary to support sound internal departmental governance;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7.4</span>Training - Travel necessary to enable the training of public servants; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.7.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.7.5</span>Other travel;</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.8</span>Ensuring that the trip data elements of Table 1 are included, at a minimum, in the travel authorization form for expenditure initiation purposes.
				
									<table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><caption class="text-left">
											Table 1 Checklist of Trip Authorization Elements
										</caption><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Element</th><th scope="col">Description</th></tr><tr><td>A. Objective</td><td>Summarize the objective of the travel.</td></tr><tr><td>B. Category</td><td>Include the applicable category from A.2.2.7. Provide a detailed explanation of the purpose of the travel if the “Other travel” category is selected.</td></tr><tr><td>C. Traveller as public servant or non-public servant</td><td>Identify whether a public servant or non-public servant.</td></tr><tr><td>D. Virtual presence or other remote meeting solutions</td><td>Rationale why virtual presence or other remote meeting solutions were not applied.</td></tr><tr><td>E. Number of travellers</td><td>Rationale for the number of travellers as it relates to the suitability of the named traveller for the stated objective.</td></tr><tr><td>F. Mode of transportation</td><td>Identify the estimated cost and rationale for the use of each of the applicable modes of transport: air, rail, taxi, personal motor vehicle, rental motor vehicle, and other modes.</td></tr><tr><td>G. Accommodations</td><td>Identify the estimated cost and rationale for the accommodation selected.</td></tr><tr><td>H. Meals</td><td>
			
												Identify the estimated cost of the meals based on the meal allowances set out in the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=10&amp;lang=eng">National Joint Council Travel Directive</a>, excluding those meals that are paid as part of the event or the mode of transportation.
											</td></tr><tr><td>I. Incidentals and other costs</td><td>Identify the estimated cost of the incidentals and other costs based on the allowances set out in the National Joint Council Travel Directive.</td></tr></table></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.9</span>Acting as the delegated travel approval authority in situations where the traveller is the deputy head;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.10</span>Ensuring that a blanket travel authority (BTA), as specified under the National Joint Council Travel Directive, include all Table 1 information;</li></ul></section><section><h4>Companion Travel</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.11"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.11</span>Ensuring that travel expenditures for companions are prohibited unless expressly provided for under legislation, regulations, orders-in-council, National Joint Council directives, collective agreements or other Treasury Board–approved instruments, or unless ministerial approval is granted pursuant to A.2.2.12.
								</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.12"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.12</span>Seeking ministerial approval for expenditure initiation of companion travel expenses in situations not provided for under legislation, regulations, orders-in-council, National Joint Council directives, collective agreements or other Treasury Board–approved instruments. This authority can only be delegated to the deputy head.</li></ul></section><section><h4>Additional Reporting</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.13"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.13</span> Ensuring that the department collects and retains the following in its departmental financial management or related systems:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.13.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.13.1</span>The travel category (element B specified in Table 1) for authorized travel; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.13.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.13.2</span>Both authorized and actual data for elements F to I specified in Table 1.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.14"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.14</span>Disclosing the aggregate of actual annual expenditures of the travel categories, as part of 4.1.2 under this directive.</li></ul></section></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix B: Standard on Hospitality</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secB.1">B.1 Effective date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.1.1</span>This standard takes effect on <time datetime="2016-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2017</time>, and incorporates changes effective as of <time datetime="2020-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2020</time>.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.1.2</span>This standard replaces the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures, Appendix 2 dated <time datetime="2013-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2013</time>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secB.2">B.2 Standards</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.1</span>This standard provides details on the requirements set out in sections 4.1 and 4.2 of the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2</span>The CFO is responsible for the following standards:
				
						<section><h4>Planning</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.1</span>Ensuring that decisions to offer hospitality are carefully considered and necessary based on courtesy, diplomacy, protocol or to facilitate the achievement of the business of the government.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.2</span>Ensuring that the provision of food and beverages is in accordance with the cost limits in Table 2 where:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.2.1</span>The standard cost per person is the expected meal cost per person to be applied in normal circumstances;
				
											<table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><caption class="text-left">
													Table 2 – Maximum Food and beverage Cost Per Person (based on allowances set out in the <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/index.php?did=10&amp;lang=eng">National Joint Council Travel Directive</a>)
												</caption><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Food and beverages</th><th scope="col">Standard Cost per Person</th><th scope="col">Maximum Cost per Person</th></tr><tr><td>Breakfast</td><td><strong>1.5 <abbr title="Times">X</abbr></strong> Breakfast Allowance</td><td rowspan="5"><strong>1.5 <abbr title="Times">X</abbr></strong> Standard Cost Per Person</td></tr><tr><td><a href="#refreshments">Refreshment</a></td><td><strong>0.5 <abbr title="Times">X</abbr></strong> Breakfast Allowance</td></tr><tr><td>Lunch</td><td><strong>2.0 <abbr title="Times">X</abbr></strong> Lunch Allowance</td></tr><tr><td><a href="#refreshments">Reception</a></td><td><strong>2.0 <abbr title="Times">X</abbr></strong> Breakfast Allowance</td></tr><tr><td>Dinner</td><td><strong>1.75 <abbr title="Times">X</abbr></strong> Dinner Allowance</td></tr></table></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.3</span>Ensuring that when only public servants are present, hospitality can only be provided in situations where:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.3.1</span>Participation is required in operational meetings, training or events that extend beyond normal working hours including where:
				
											<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.3.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.3.1.1</span>There are no nearby or appropriate facilities to obtain <a href="#refreshments">refreshments</a> or meals; or
												</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.3.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.3.1.2</span>Staff dispersal is not effective or efficient;</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.4</span>Ensuring that meals provided to public servants in the course of their duties, where a department has no discretion in their provision, are not subject to hospitality authorization under this directive;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.5</span>Ensuring that hospitality, including with any of the following elements, is only provided to non-public servants and the minimum required number of public servants for reasons of courtesy, diplomacy or protocol:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.5.1</span>Alcoholic beverages;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.5.2</span>Entertainment activities;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.5.3</span>Local transportation to and from an event or activity; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.5.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.5.4</span>Facility rental and associated items which are directly and inherently for hospitality purposes;</li></ul></li></ul></section><section><h4>Hospitality Authorization (Approval authority required for expenditure initiation)</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6</span>Seeking ministerial approval when the following hospitality components are present, unless any or all components have been delegated by the minister to the deputy head:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.1</span>Total hospitality costs exceed $10,000;
										</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.2</span>Alcoholic beverages will be provided;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.3</span>Food and beverage costs exceed the standard cost per person, up to the maximum cost per person (Table 2);</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.4</span>Food and beverage costs exceed the maximum cost per person (Table 2);</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.5</span><a href="#entertainment">Entertainment</a> will be provided;
										</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.6</span>Hospitality or <a href="#entertainment">entertainment</a> will be provided to a person accompanying an event participant; or
										</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.6.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.6.7</span>Hospitality paid by the federal government will be extended at the residence of a public servant;</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.7</span> Seeking deputy head approval for the following:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.7.1</span>When the total hospitality costs exceed $3,000 but are $10,000 or less and, if delegated to the deputy head, any components listed in B.2.2.6 requiring ministerial approval that are present; </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.8</span>Ensuring that approval of the senior departmental manager, or the delegated manager, is obtained when total hospitality costs associated with the event are $3,000 or less, and none of the elements listed in B.2.2.6 are present;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.9</span>Ensuring that, with the exception of the minister, an appropriate alternative approval authority is obtained when the individual who would normally approve the hospitality is also a participant at the hospitality activity;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.10"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.10</span>Approving hospitality up to the deputy head limits set out in B.2.2.7 in situations where the deputy head is in attendance at a hospitality activity and would normally approve the hospitality;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.11"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.11</span>Ensuring that blanket hospitality authorities (BHA) for expenditure initiation, which do not include any elements requiring ministerial approval as set out in B.2.2.6 or as delegated to the deputy head, are:
				
									<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.11.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.11.1</span>Approved for use within a particular fiscal year;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.11.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.11.2</span>Supported by sound rationale and proper oversight, accountabilities and controls including:
				
											<ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.11.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.11.2.1</span>Quarterly internal departmental reporting, at a minimum, of planned and actual blanket hospitality authorities expenditures; and</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.11.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.11.3</span>Reapproved for individual hospitality prior to its occurrence, if possible, when there are any exceptions to the BHA parameters.</li></ul></li></ul></section><section><h4>Private Club Memberships</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.12"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.12</span>Ensuring that the purchase of private club memberships is prohibited unless expressly permitted under legislation, regulations, orders-in-council, National Joint Council directives or other Treasury Board–approved instruments, or unless ministerial approval is granted pursuant to B.2.2.13. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claB.2.2.13"><span class="pol-cla-id">B.2.2.13</span>Seeking ministerial approval for private club memberships in situations not covered under legislation, regulations, orders-in-council, National Joint Council directives or other Treasury Board–approved instruments. This authority can only be delegated to the deputy head.</li></ul></section></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appC">Appendix C: Standard on Conferences</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secC.1">C.1 Effective date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.1.1</span>This standard takes effect on <time datetime="2016-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2017</time>.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.1.2</span>This standard replaces the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures, Appendix 3 dated <time datetime="2013-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2013</time>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secC.2">C.2 Standards</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.2.1</span>This standard provides details on the requirements set out in sections 4.1 and 4.2 of the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.2.2</span>The CFO is responsible for the following standards:
				
						<section><h4>Planning</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.2.2.1</span>Ensuring that the objective of attending a conference is specified in the applicable conference approval document. Where travel is involved, the travel authorization elements of Table 1 in Appendix A will apply;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.2.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.2.2.2</span>Limiting the number of public servants attending a conference from a department to the minimum necessary to achieve the departmental objective;</li></ul></section><section><h4>Conference Authorization (Approval authority required for expenditure initiation)</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.2.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.2.2.3</span>Ensuring that the conference approval authority set out in the departmental delegation of financial and spending authorities chart is at the senior departmental manager level; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claC.2.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">C.2.2.4</span>Ensuring that when multiple public servants attend the same conference, event approval is obtained for the total planned conference costs as set out in Appendix D.</li></ul></section></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appD">Appendix D: Standard on Events</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secD.1">D.1 Effective date</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.1.1</span>This standard takes effect on <time datetime="2016-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2017</time>.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.1.2</span>This standard replaces the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures, Appendix 4 dated <time datetime="2013-08-01" class="nowrap">August 1, 2013</time>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secD.2">D.2 Standards</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.1</span>This standard provides details on the requirements set out in sections 4.1 and 4.2 of the Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2</span>The CFO is responsible for the following standards:
				
						<section><h4>Planning</h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2.1</span>Ensuring that the appropriate number of public servants attend an event when the total event costs are submitted for approval, as specified in D.2.2.3 to D.2.2.6;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2.2</span>Ensuring that training activities are not considered as an event and are approved as part of an individual’s training plan by the appropriate manager as set out in the departmental delegation of financial and spending authorities chart;</li></ul></section><section><h4><strong>Event Authorization (Approval authority required for expenditure initiation)</strong></h4><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2.3</span>Seeking ministerial approval when total departmental costs associated with an event exceed $50,000;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2.4</span>Ensuring that the minister is provided with the total estimated federal cost for all participating departments, including the total estimated travel costs, for information purposes, when their approval is required for an event hosted by the department;</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2.5</span>Seeking deputy head approval of an event when total departmental costs associated with the event exceed $25,000 but are $50,000 or less; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claD.2.2.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">D.2.2.6</span>Ensuring that approval of the senior departmental manager or the delegated manager of an event is obtained when the total departmental costs associated with the event are $25,000 or less.</li></ul></section></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appE">Appendix E: Definitions</h2><div class="pol-content"><dl><dt>blanket hospitality authority <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(autorisation générale pour l’accueil)</span></dt><dd>Authorization for hospitality which is continuous or repetitive in nature and where it is not practical or administratively efficient to obtain prior approval for each individual hospitality occurrence.</dd><dt>companion <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(personne accompagnante)</span></dt><dd>Spouse, common-law partner, conjugal partner or family member of the traveller or any other individual accompanying a traveller and who is not on government business.</dd><dt>conferences <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(conférences)</span></dt><dd>Refer to a congress, convention, seminar, symposium or other formal gathering, which are usually organized by a third party external to government, where participants debate or are informed of the status of a discipline (e.g. sciences, economics, technology, management). (This definition is based on the object of expenditure 0823 Conference Fees of the Government-wide Chart of Accounts).</dd><dt id="entertainment">entertainment activities <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(activités de divertissement)</span></dt><dd>The action of being provided with amusement or enjoyment and includes, but is not limited to tickets to musical, theatre, sporting or similar events, tours of local or other places of interest, and other similar activities for reasons of courtesy, diplomacy and protocol.</dd><dt id="events">events <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(événements)</span></dt><dd><p>Involve gatherings of individuals (both public and/or non-public servants) engaged in activities other than operational activities of the department. Examples of events include, but are not limited to:</p><ul><li>Management and staff retreats;</li><li>Participation in conferences;</li><li>Awards and recognition ceremonies; and</li><li>Departmental celebrations.</li></ul></dd><dt id="hospitality">hospitality <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(accueil)</span></dt><dd>Consists of the provision of meals, beverages or refreshments in events which are necessary for the effective conduct of government business and for courtesy, diplomacy or protocol purposes.</dd><dt>operational activities <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(activités opérationnelles)</span></dt><dd><p>Are those activities undertaken to deliver departmental programs and services including departmental internal services.</p><p>For individuals, operational activities are those activities undertaken in the performance of their assigned tasks, as set out in position descriptions, terms of reference, statements of work or other like documents.</p><p>Any gathering of individuals, the purpose of which is not to conduct operational activities, shall be defined as an “event”.</p></dd><dt>private club  <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(club privé)</span></dt><dd>An organization, institution, facility or premises offering common social and recreational amenities for the enjoyment of members and their guests. Members of private clubs share common goals and interests, and often use private clubs to create business and networking contacts in order to advance their organization’s strategies, plans and priorities.</dd><dt>reception <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(réception)</span></dt><dd>A function over a prolonged period of time, where food may be served for the purpose of sustaining attendees and where a meal may or may not be served afterward.</dd><dt id="refreshments">refreshments <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(rafraîchissements)</span></dt><dd>Beverages or food (e.g. light snacks) or both, served between meals.</dd><dt>training <span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA">(formation)</span></dt><dd>Fees paid for formal learning activities, which include a curriculum and established learning objectives, and where the primary purpose is to enable participants to maintain or acquire skills or knowledge.</dd></dl></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2017, <br/>ISBN: 978-0-660-09713-8</p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>