<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Directive on Union Dues</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=21104", title: "Directive on Union Dues"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=21104&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2025-09-01",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Directive on Union Dues</h1><section class="alert alert-info"><h2>Note to reader</h2><p>This directive will be updated September 1, 2025. The changes will take effect on thay date.</p><p>The previous version of the directive has been archived. </p></section><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.1</span>This directive takes  effect on March 1, 2011.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.2</span>It replaces the <em>Treasury Board Manual, Chapter 11, Union Dues Check-off,</em> dated May 1, 1995.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Authorities</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1</span>This directive is issued pursuant to the authorities indicated in section 2 of the <em>Policy on Terms and Conditions of Employment</em>.  It identifies mandatory requirements for the application of union dues that are  not specified in collective agreements.
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1.1</span>The authority to deduct and remit union dues to bargaining agents is governed by the relevant collective agreement provisions. Where there is a conflict between a collective agreement and this directive, the provisions of the collective agreement apply. </li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Objective and expected results</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1</span>The objective of this  directive is to ensure the accurate, consistent and effective administration of union dues across the CPA. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2</span>The expected results of this directive are that the deductions and remittance of union dues are administered in accordance with the relevant collective agreement provisions and this directive.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Requirements</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1</span>Organizational senior human resources officials or any other person named by the deputy head are responsible for the following:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1</span>Ensuring that the necessary organizational structure, resources, systems, service standards and controls are in place to facilitate the accurate, consistent and effective administration of union dues; and </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2</span>Monitoring compliance with this directive  within their organization by reviewing, on an ongoing basis, the processes and procedures associated with the administration of union dues and  implementing, when required, changes in a timely manner. </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2</span>Organizational human resources representatives are responsible  for the following:

  <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.1</span>Ensuring that issues associated with the administration of union dues are effectively  managed in cooperation with administrators of compensation, as required; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.2</span>Ensuring that administrators of compensation are provided with letters of offer, secondment or assignment agreements, or any other relevant document in a timely manner, to administer union dues effectively, and enter the information in the human resources system; </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.3</span>Ensuring that assignment or secondment agreements specify if a position is unrepresented or has been declared to be a managerial or confidential (excluded) position, and if so, the impact of the agreement on union dues. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.4</span>Ensuring that employees are provided accurate information in a timely manner regarding union dues; and </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.5</span>Ensuring timely, accurate and complete data entry in the human resources system, for the administration of union dues.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3</span>Organizational finance representatives are responsible for the following:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.1</span>Remitting payments related to union dues (arrears and refunds) to bargaining agents and employees in accordance with the relevant collective agreement provisions and this directive.
       </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4</span>Administrators of compensation are responsible for the following:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.1</span>Data entry of union dues transactions in the pay systems in accordance with the relevant collective agreement provisions and this directive; and</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.2</span>Notifying bargaining agents in a timely manner of changes in union representation and/or employment status.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Roles of other government organizations</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1</span>The Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat (TBS) is responsible for the following:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1.1</span>Notifying organizations within the CPA of changes in the administration of union dues and union dues deduction rates as communicated by bargaining agents;
    </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1.2</span>Notifying the appropriate authority to cease union dues deductions for employees should labour relations circumstances warrant it; and
      </li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.1.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.1.3</span>Monitoring compliance of organizations within the  CPA with this directive, as required, through the reconciliation of information obtained by bargaining agents, Public Service Procurement Canada (PSPC), and organizations within the CPA.
      </li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2</span>PSPC is responsible for the following:
    <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla5.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">5.2.1</span>Deducting union dues each month for employees paid through the public service pay system and remitting them to bargaining agents. Organizations not serviced by the public service pay system are responsible to deduct union dues for their employees and remitting them to bargaining agents.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Application</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.1</span>This directive applies to employees and organizations covered in section 2 of the <em>Policy on Terms and Conditions of Employment</em>.</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.1</span>Legislation
<ul><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/p-33.3/"><em>Federal Public Sector Labour Relations Act</em></a>(FPSLRA)(section  2(1))</li><li><a href="https://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/index.html"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>(FAA)  (section 11)</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla7.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">7.2</span>Related policy instruments
<ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/agreements-conventions/list-eng.aspx">Collective agreements</a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15771"><em>Policy on Terms and Conditions of Employment</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=15772"><em>Directive on Terms and Conditions of Employment</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12602">Guidelines on Managerial or Confidential Exclusions</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.1</span>Individuals from  organizations within the CPA should contact their human resources division for information about this directive.
</li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla8.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">8.2</span>Delegated representatives from corporate labour relations or corporate compensation may contact:
	
	<p>Strategic Compensation Management<br />
        Employee Relations and Total Compensation<br />
        Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer<br />
        Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat</p></li></ul></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix A: Requirements for the Administration of Union Dues</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.1">A.1 General</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.1</span>With the exceptions specified in this appendix, union dues are deducted each month from an employee's pay and remitted to the bargaining agent.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.1.2</span>Union dues are not deducted: 
        <ul><li>when an employee is the occupant of a managerial or confidential (excluded) position;</li><li>when an employee is exempt from paying union dues because of religious affiliation in accordance with the specific check-off (union dues) provisions of the relevant collective  agreement;</li><li>when an employee is the occupant of an unrepresented position;</li><li>when a person is not an employee as defined in the FPSLRA (see definitions);</li><li>from overtime and bonuses; or</li><li>from retroactive pay related to the signature of a collective agreement, except where bargaining agents have determined that their union dues  are based on a percentage of salary and have chosen to deduct union dues to such retroactive pay.</li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.2">A.2 Commencing union dues</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.1</span>Initial appointment to the CPA
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.1.1</span>The date used to establish when to commence union dues is the effective date of the initial appointment. Union dues deductions commence on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the effective date of the initial appointment is the first day of that month; or
              </li><li>the first day of the following month if the effective date of the initial appointment is any other day during that month.
              </li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2</span>Subsequent appointments within the CPA (including but not limited to, promotions, demotions, and acting appointments) deployments, assignments and secondments
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.2.1</span>The date used to establish when to commence union dues is the effective date when the employee starts that employment. Union dues deductions commence on: 
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the effective date of the action is the first day of that month; or</li><li>the first day of the following month if the effective date of the action is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3</span>Reclassifications or conversions
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.2.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.2.3.1</span>The date used to establish when to commence union dues is the issue  date of the letter notifying the employee of the reclassification or conversion, or the effective date of such reclassification or conversion, whichever is later. For clarity, union dues for reclassifications or conversions are adjusted on a go-forward basis. Union dues deductions commence  on: 
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the issue date of the letter notifying the employee of the reclassification or conversion, or the effective date of such reclassification or conversion, whichever is later, is the first day of that month; or</li><li>the first day of the following month if the issue date of the letter notifying the employee of the reclassification or conversion, or the effective date of such reclassification or conversion, whichever is later, is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.3">A.3 Ceasing or amending union dues</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.1</span>Subsequent appointments (except for reclassifications or conversions) and other resourcing options or when the employee returns to their  substantive position
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.1.1</span>The date used to establish when to cease or amend union dues is the effective date of the action or when the employee returns to their substantive position. Union dues deductions cease or are amended on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the effective date of the action or when the employee returns to their substantive position is the first day of that month; or </li><li>the first day of the following month if the effective date of the action or when the employee returns to their substantive position is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.2</span>Religious affiliation
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.2.1</span>In accordance with the relevant collective agreement, once a request for exemption by an employee has been approved, in writing, by the bargaining agent, union dues deductions will cease on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the effective date that the request for exemption has been approved is the first day of that month; or </li><li>the first day of the following month if the effective date that the request for exemption has been approved is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.3</span>Leave without pay (LWOP) and return from LWOP
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.3.1</span>Union dues are deducted for the month of departure. Where the LWOP begins on the first day of the month or where an employee does not have sufficient earnings to deduct union dues for the month of departure after statutory and mandatory deductions are taken, the employer shall not be obligated to make such deductions from subsequent salary.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.3.2</span>Upon return from a LWOP, union dues are deducted for the month. Where an employee does not have sufficient earnings to deduct union dues for the month of return from a LWOP after statutory and mandatory deductions  are taken, the employer shall not be obligated to make such deductions from  subsequent salary. This provision also applies  to an employee returning to work on an approved rehabilitation program with reduced hours of work. In such a case, union dues are deducted based on the employee’s employment status prior to the period  of disability.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.4</span>Termination of employment
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.4.1</span>Upon termination of employment, union dues for the last month of employment are recovered from any termination payment. Where there are insufficient earnings  after statutory and mandatory deductions are taken, the employer shall not be obligated to make such deductions from subsequent payments, if any.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.4.2</span>Union dues arrears owed by an employee, which have been remitted to a bargaining agent by the employer, are recovered from any termination payment. If any outstanding balance remains, an amount due to the Crown is created.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.4.3</span>Union dues refunds, including those discovered after termination of employment, are refunded to the employee within 30 calendar days of discovering the error, unless both parties agree otherwise. Administrators of compensation will notify the bargaining agent who received union dues in error.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.4.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.4.4</span>Union dues arrears, including those discovered after termination of employment, are recovered from any termination payment unless both parties agree otherwise. If any outstanding balance remains, an amount due to the Crown is created.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.5</span>Death
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.5.1</span>Upon death, union dues  for the month of death are recovered from any termination payment. Where there are insufficient earnings after statutory and mandatory deductions are taken, the employer shall not be  obligated to make such deductions from subsequent payments, if any. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.5.2</span>Union dues owed by an employee, which have been remitted to a bargaining agent by the employer, are recovered from any termination payment. If any outstanding balance remains, an amount due to the Crown is not created. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.3.5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.3.5.3</span>Union dues arrears are not recovered. Union dues refunds are paid by the employer to the estate. Administrators of compensation will contact the bargaining agent who received union dues in error to discuss the amount to  be refunded. Arrears and refunds are processed within 30 calendar days of discovering the error, unless both parties agree otherwise. </li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.4">A.4 New proposal for a managerial or confidential (excluded) position </h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.1</span>No objection from the bargaining agent 
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.1.1</span>The position becomes excluded on the date specified in the order issued by the Federal Public Sector Labour Relations and Employment Board (FPSLREB). Union dues deductions cease on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the date specified in the order is the first day of that month; or </li><li>the first day of the following month if the date specified in the order is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.2</span>Objection from the bargaining agent
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.2.1</span>In accordance with the FPSLRA, if a bargaining agent files an objection to the exclusion of a position, union dues are held in suspense until the case is resolved, starting on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the date of the objection is the first day of that month; or </li><li>the first day of the following month if the date of the objection is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.2.2</span>If the FPSLREB determines that the position is not excluded or if the employer withdraws the proposal, all monies held in suspense in respect to this proposal are redirected to the bargaining agent.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.2.3</span>If the FPSLREB determines that the position is excluded or if the bargaining agent withdraws the objection, all monies held in suspense in respect to this  proposal are refunded to the occupant(s) of the position and union dues deductions cease on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the date of the order is the first day of that month; or </li><li>the first day of the following month if the date of the order is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.3</span>Return of a position to the bargaining unit
        <ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.4.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.4.3.1</span>The date used to  establish when to start union dues deductions is the date of the order by the FPSLREB. Union dues deductions start on:
            <ul><li>the first day of the month if the effective date of the order is the first day of that month; or</li><li>the first day of the following month if the effective date of the order is any other day during that month.</li></ul></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="secA.5">A.5 Union dues arrears and refunds</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.5.1</span>Employees are responsible for any under-deduction or will be refunded on any over-deduction as a result of errors. Administrator of compensation are to refund employees any over-deduction of union dues or recover any under-deduction of dues within 30 calendar days of discovering the error, unless the bargaining agent and the employer agree  otherwise in writing. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.5.2</span>When arrears in union dues are outstanding, the amount owed is directed to the bargaining agent by a departmental finance representative  within 30 calendar days of the administrator of compensation discovering the error, unless the bargaining agent and the employer agree otherwise in writing. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.5.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.5.3</span>When union dues were directed in error to a  bargaining agent, the bargaining agent that received the union dues in error,  must reimburse the amount to the Employer within 30 calendar days of being  advised, unless the bargaining agent and the employer agree otherwise in  writing. </li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.5.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.5.4</span>Where possible, refunds and arrears are  administered at the same time. These  amounts may be subject to validation by the bargaining agent and adjustments  may subsequently occur.</li><li class="pol-cla" id="claA.5.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">A.5.5</span>Administrators of compensation recovers the  amount owed from the employee's pay at the rate of one current month of union  dues plus the equivalent amount of an additional month of dues. A higher recovery rate than that stated above  may be applied at the employee’s written request. </li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix B: Definitions</h2><div class="pol-content"><dl><dt><strong>administrator of compensation (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>administratrice ou administrateur de la rémunération</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>person responsible for pay administration within organizations or at the Public Service Pay Centre.</dd><dt><strong>arrears (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>arrérage</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>in the context of this directive means an amount owing when union dues have not been deducted or an inadequate amount of union dues that has been deducted.</dd><dt><strong>bargaining agent (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>agent né;gociateur</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd> an employee organization that is certified by the FPSLREB to represent employees in a bargaining unit.</dd><dt><strong>bargaining unit (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>unité de négociation</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>a group of two or more employees that is determined by the FPSLREB to constitute a unit of employees appropriate for collective bargaining.</dd><dt><strong>collective agreement (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>convention collective</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>an agreement in writing, entered into under Part 1 of the FPSLRA between the employer and a bargaining  agent, containing provisions pertaining to terms and conditions of employment and related matters. </dd><dt><strong>effective date (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>date d’entrée en vigueur</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>the day that an action, decision, document, order, etc. takes effect.</dd><dt><strong>employee (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>employé-e</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>in the context of this directive has the same meaning as in sub-section 2(1) of the FPSLRA.</dd><dt><strong>full calendar month of employment (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>mois civil complet d'emploi</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>the period from the first day of the month to the last day of the month inclusively. </dd><dt><strong>full month of employment (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>mois complet d'emploi</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>has the same meaning as full calendar month of employment referred to in some collective agreements. </dd><dt><strong>leave  without pay (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>congé non payé</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>an authorized unpaid absence from work, in accordance with the relevant  collective agreement or terms and conditions of employment, while maintaining continuity of employment.</dd><dt><strong>occupant of a managerial or confidential (excluded) position(<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>titulaire d'un poste de direction ou de confiance (exclu)</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>the incumbent or the person who is acting in a position that has been declared to be a managerial or confidential (excluded) position.</dd><dt><strong>refund (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>remboursement</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>an amount of money owing to a bargaining agent, the employer, and/or an employee as a result of union dues being deducted in error or directed in error.</dd><dt><strong>union dues (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>cotisations syndicales</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>has the same meaning as “membership dues” and “check-off” referred to in collective agreements. Should these expressions not be defined in a collective agreement, then they have the  same meaning as “membership dues” found in the FPSLRA. In all cases, initiation fees, insurance premiums, special levies, or fines are excluded.</dd><dt><strong>unrepresented position (<span xml:lang="fr-CA" lang="fr-CA"><em>poste non représenté</em></span>)</strong></dt><dd>a position that is not represented by a bargaining agent.</dd></dl></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2017, <br/>ISBN: 978-0-660-09716-9</p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>