<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><doc title="Guideline on Acceptable Network and Device Use" space="preserve" language="en" versionID="27907" documentID="27907" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="About This Guideline"><p>The <em>Guideline on  Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> (the Guideline) provides guidance to  departmental managers and functional specialists responsible for implementing  the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122"><em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em></a> (the Policy). This guideline is intended for departments to which the Policy  applies (see <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#cha2">Section  2 of the Policy</a>). Other Government of Canada institutions are encouraged to  follow the advice in this guideline, as appropriate.</p><p>This guideline was prepared by the Chief Information Officer  Branch of the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat in consultation with  departments and agencies. It replaces those sections of the <em>Guideline for External Use of Web 2.0</em> that relate to the use of social media for professional and limited personal  use.</p></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="1. Introduction"><p>The widespread adoption of the Internet and the rapid  evolution of networks and devices have changed the way public servants work,  and have improved the ability to communicate, collaborate, and share  information and expertise. For many public servants this advancement has  inspired innovative ways of working, including: </p><ul><li>Conducting consultations on new policy  instruments through wikis; </li><li>Following and engaging experts and thought  leaders on social media platforms; </li><li>Submitting questions or requests through the  Internet and social media; and</li><li>Accessing information via smartphones and other  user devices.</li></ul><p>The Policy requires departments to ensure acceptable and  efficient use of Government of Canada electronic networks and devices and to  provide open access to Web 2.0 tools and services, in accordance with the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16578"><em>Policy on Government Security</em></a>. This  guideline defines professional and personal use of Government of Canada  electronic networks, devices and Web 2.0 tools and services. This guideline  also provides practical advice and tools that relate to the implementation of  the Policy requirements.</p><p>Departments are encouraged to consider these best practices  when developing their implementation plans. </p></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="2. Defining Professional and Personal Use"><p>In an interactive and mobile work environment, it is  important that employees are aware of the expectations of acceptable use when  using Government of Canada electronic networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools  and services. This is particularly pertinent given that the networks, devices  and social media platforms used for professional purposes are sometimes the  same as those used for personal activities, thus potentially blurring the  boundaries between the professional and personal use by public servants.</p><p>This guideline applies to professional and personal use of  Government of Canada electronic networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools and  services by <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#ai">authorized individuals</a>,  irrespective of location of access. This includes using government-issued  devices on government and public networks, as well as using personal devices,  if permitted, on Government of Canada networks (e.g., use of a Virtual Private  Network on a personal computer).</p><section anchor="3.1" title="2.1 Social Media Activities"><p>Social media and other Web 2.0 tools and services are  providing new opportunities for networking and collaborating. There are three  key types of use:</p><p>"Professional use", which refers to the use of a personal  social media account for purposes related to professional activities, such as  communicating with professional associations, professional networking (e.g.,  participating in an online conference), gathering and sharing knowledge (e.g.,  using Twitter to stay up-to-date on trends or visiting government Facebook  pages) and career development (i.e., maintaining a LinkedIn profile).</p><p>"Personal use", which refers to the use of a personal social  media account for purposes unrelated to professional development or employment  (e.g., blogging about gardening tips, checking the weather or bus schedules, or  sharing personal or family photos). This type of use is limited and must be  conducted on personal time.</p><p>A third category is "official use". Only those individuals  who have been authorized to represent the Government of Canada can use official  social media accounts. Advice on the official use of social media is provided  in the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27517"><em>Guideline on Official Use of Social Media</em></a>.</p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appF">Appendix F</a> provides sample learning tools related to employee use of social media.</p><p><strong>Note:</strong> Adherence  to the behaviours outlined in the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049"><em>Values and Ethics Code of the Public Sector</em></a> and departmental  codes of conduct is expected for all types of use of electronic networks, devices  and Web 2.0 tools and services, including social media. It is important to  apply the same judgement to online activities as would apply to similar  activities offline. Examples of acceptable and unacceptable use are provided in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix  B of the Policy</a> and <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix  C of the Policy</a>.</p></section></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="3. Planning for Implementation"><p>The expected results of the Policy are that authorized  individuals use Government of Canada electronic networks and devices in an  acceptable manner and that they have open access to Web 2.0 tools and  services on the appropriate Government of Canada network domains and associated  devices. Formulating a course of action to implement the Policy requirements in  a timely and effective manner is critical to achieving these outcomes.</p><p>A department's approach to planning for implementation will  be affected by a number of variables that depend on the department's current  state of open access. Departments are encouraged to adapt these recommendations  to their own needs.</p><p>As a best practice, departments are encouraged to conduct  the following activities as part of the planning process:</p><ol><li>Identify a departmental champion; </li><li>Conduct a gap analysis; </li><li>Engage departmental subject matter experts; and</li><li>Develop an implementation plan.</li></ol><section anchor="4.1" title="3.1 Identifying a Champion"><p>Implementation is the process of turning policy into  practice. Executive support can increase the potential for success in  implementing the Policy. An effective champion can provide strategic direction  to inform the development of an implementation plan and assist in securing the  resources needed for implementation. The champion can also be an agent of  change.</p><p>The Policy requires open access to Internet tools and  services, which for some departments will require  a culture shift. The  presence of an influential leader can help form a new shared value by  encouraging others to work differently by promoting the acceptable use of  Government of Canada electronic networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools and  services and open access to Internet tools, and by demonstrating change through  positive results. </p></section><section anchor="4.2" title="3.2 Conducting a Gap Analysis"><p>A gap analysis involves determining what steps need to be  taken to move from a current state to a target state. Knowledge of expected  practices in the target state can help identify actions to close any potential  gaps. Departments may wish to frame their gap analyses by using the  requirements of the Policy as the future state and determining what gaps exist  between the current and future states. Departments can then propose actions to  fill the gaps. Highlighting deficiencies will help create the basis of an  implementation plan, within which departments can include the resources needed  to meet the objectives. </p></section><section anchor="4.3" title="3.3 Engaging Departmental Subject Matter Experts"><p>Engaging the right people through existing  departmental networks or through the creation of a team of experts can support  the Policy's implementation goals. It can also demonstrate a more coherent  approach to the champion and other executives. It is recommended that  departmental representatives be consulted throughout the life cycle of  implementation, to ensure that relevant policy and legal considerations are  met. <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B</a> suggests the departmental experts that could be involved and the value they can  add.</p></section><section anchor="4.4" title="3.4 Developing an Implementation Plan"><p>Developing a formal implementation plan can build a common  understanding about what is to be achieved, and the roles and responsibilities  of those involved in implementing the Policy. It is a good practice to create  an implementation plan in consultation with the members of the team of experts.  It is suggested that the plan include the following:</p><ul><li>Purpose;</li><li>Background or Introduction;</li><li>Goals;</li><li>Consultations;</li><li>Roles and Responsibilities;</li><li>Key Tasks;</li><li>Resources;</li><li>Risk Mitigation; and</li><li>Performance Measurement and Evaluation.</li></ul><p>An example of an Implementation Plan Template is provided in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C</a>.</p></section></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="4. Implementing the Requirements of the Policy"><p>The objective of the Policy is to ensure acceptable and  efficient use of Government of Canada electronic networks and devices, and Web  2.0 tools and services to support enhanced communication and collaboration,  thereby improving productivity and program and service delivery to individuals  and businesses.</p><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#cha6">Section  6 of the Policy</a> states that deputy heads are responsible for ensuring that:</p><ul><li>Effective management and monitoring practices  for the acceptable use of Government of Canada electronic networks and devices,  and Web 2.0 tools and services are implemented; </li><li>Authorized individuals are informed of the  expectations of acceptable use of Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices, and Web 2.0 tools and services, departmental monitoring practices and  consequences of unacceptable use;</li><li>Open access to the Internet and Web 2.0 tools  and services is implemented while meeting the security objectives of the <em>Policy on Government Security</em>; </li><li>Learning opportunities regarding the acceptable  use of Government of Canada electronic networks and devices and Government of  Canada and external Web 2.0 tools and services are provided to authorized  individuals; and</li><li>Reports on the use of Government of Canada  networks and devices are made available monthly and as required, to help deputy  heads identify, investigate and implement corrective action on issues relating  to unacceptable use.<a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#ftn1" id="ftnref1"><span class="cn-invisible"> See footnote </span><sup>1</sup></a></li></ul><section anchor="5.1" title="4.1 Establishing Effective Management and Monitoring Practices"><p>Effective management involves planning, coordinating and  monitoring to accomplish desired goals and objectives while using available  resources efficiently. Sound operational practices can aid departments in  adequately protecting departmental and informational assets and allowing  authorized individuals to use networks and devices effectively, efficiently and  securely. </p><p>As a best practice, departments may want to review existing  operational management practices for opportunities to optimize and to validate  that the appropriate resources and tools supporting the implementation of the  Policy are well coordinated. Finally, ensuring effectiveness of these operating  practices through periodic reviews can help ensure ongoing compliance with the  Policy.</p><p>Examples of best practices are:</p><ul><li><strong>Establishing monitoring practices:</strong><ul><li>Defining requirements for regular and special  practices for monitoring networks and devices for acceptable use;</li><li>Communicating monitoring requirements to  departmental representatives or Shared Services Canada equivalents responsible  for managing network and device monitoring tools; and</li><li>Coordinating and implementing modifications to  monitoring practices as a result of corrective action measures. </li></ul></li><li><strong>Managing appropriate and inappropriate use:</strong><ul><li>Communicating monitoring practices to authorized  individuals accessing networks and devices, and any subsequent changes to  practices; </li><li>Receiving, tracking and responding to questions  about the Policy;</li><li>Responding to requests received from management  to investigate suspected cases of unacceptable use;</li><li>Informing the Champion and other executives of  compliance with the Policy, including incidents and corrective action measures;</li><li>Submitting requests for special monitoring to  departmental or Shared Services Canada representatives when potential issues of  unacceptable use arise;</li><li>Handling confirmed cases of unacceptable use  detected by network and device monitoring tools (examples of informal and  formal approaches are outlined in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appD">Appendix D</a>); and</li><li>Informing departmental security officials if a  security incident resulting from unacceptable use is suspected or confirmed.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Reporting:</strong><ul><li>Receiving data on a monthly basis from the  various monitoring tools for analysis to ensure compliance with the Policy; and</li><li>Requesting the generation of unscheduled reports to  assist in the investigation of suspected cases of unacceptable use of  electronic networks, devices and Web 2.0 tools and services.</li></ul></li></ul></section><section anchor="5.2" title="4.2 Informing Authorized Individuals"><p>Communication plays a pivotal role in the successful  implementation and application of a policy. Key messages can be developed and  communicated using different channels of delivery, ensuring that managers are  informed of their responsibilities and that employees are briefed on what is  expected of them.</p><p>Authorized individuals who use Government of Canada  electronic networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools and services must be  informed of expectations for acceptable use, departmental monitoring practices and  consequences of unacceptable use. Sample statements for consideration are  available in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appE">Appendix E</a>.</p><p>There are several options, both formal and informal, to  consider when disseminating required information (<a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appF">Appendix F</a> provides sample learning tools directed to authorized individuals), such  as: </p><ul><li>Network login acknowledgements and notifications  or security banners (<a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appG">Appendix G</a> provides examples of daily and quarterly network sign-on notifications); </li><li>Departmental electronic newsletters, pamphlets  and bulletins; </li><li>Intranets (e.g., Content pages, Frequently Asked  Questions (FAQs), wikis and blogs); </li><li>E-mail messages, which can be confirmed by an  electronic receipt; </li><li>Streaming video sites (e.g., <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JRvY1SzWhl0&amp;list=TLzGuz2cZqZt7ROwwW_GJbyJ3ZRWaYL7aN">Transport  Canada Social Media at Work YouTube video</a>);</li><li>Topic discussions, lunch and learn sessions, and  team meetings; </li><li>Policy and procedures manuals or departmental  codes of conduct;</li><li>Orientation of new employees;</li><li>Information posted in common areas (e.g.,  posters and fact sheets);</li><li>Text included in user account application forms;  or</li><li>Terms of use agreements for department-issued  devices (e.g., smartphones, external storage devices and tablets), which are  signed before taking possession of these devices.</li></ul><p>Whether the Policy requirements are being communicated upon  the introduction of the new Policy, as part of ongoing awareness, or during  periods of amendments to the Policy, it is recommended that departments develop  a multi-faceted approach, using as many channels as possible to reach the  intended audience.</p><p>A best practice is to ensure that relevant information about  the Policy is available at all times on the departmental intranet or wiki. By  keeping information up to date, departments can adapt messaging to include  changes brought about by the introduction of new technologies and Web 2.0  tools and services. </p></section><section anchor="5.3" title="4.3 Providing Open Access"><p>Open access to Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices, including internal and external Web 2.0 tools and services, is  essential in transforming the way public servants work and serve Canadians.  Open access to an array of Internet-based tools and services (e.g., <a href="http://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/wiki/?setlang=en">GCpedia wiki</a>, <a href="http://gcconnex.gc.ca/">GCconnex</a> and social  networking platforms such as Twitter, YouTube and Facebook) can enhance  collaboration and communication. </p><p>The information gathered in the gap analysis, outlined  in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#sec4.2">Section  3.2 of this Guideline</a>, may have identified the need to provide more  open access within the department to meet the Policy requirements. If a  strategy is needed to enhance access, the following components could be  considered:</p><h4>4.3.1. Identifying Needs and Aligning with Departmental Priorities</h4><ul><li>How are departmental priorities supported by  open access? </li><li>Which sites or groups of sites will support  authorized individuals' use of the network for government business and for  professional development (e.g., social media platforms where the department has  an official presence)?</li><li>Are there any responsibilities of specific  authorized individuals or groups of authorized individuals that may require  access to websites that would normally fall into the category of unacceptable  use (e.g., employees conducting investigation or policy research into an area  relating to criminal behaviour)? </li></ul><h4>4.3.2. Identifying and Overcoming Challenges of Providing Open Access</h4><ul><li>What are the perceived or real challenges to  providing open access?
            <ul><li>Information or information technology (IT)  security concerns;</li><li>Network bandwidth; </li><li>Employee productivity;</li><li>Access to information and privacy; and</li><li>Other.</li></ul></li><li>What are the risk mitigation strategies for  these challenges?
            <ul><li>Use Government of Canada issued devices;</li><li>Ensure that web browsers and associated  applications are up to date and support the functionality of modern websites  and tools;</li><li>Set bandwidth controls, providing reasonable  weekly or monthly limits on data use by authorized individuals;</li><li> Provide  warnings to employees if these limits are exceeded; </li><li>Develop a strategy to acquire more bandwidth  capacity as demand for resources continues to grow; and</li><li>Address employee inefficiency through human  resources management processes and consult with human resources to determine  the appropriate approach.</li></ul></li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> See <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appE">Appendix  E of the Policy</a> for additional mitigation measures.</p><h4>4.3.3. Implementing Open Access</h4><p>As a baseline, departments could begin by providing default  access to social media platforms for which the department has an official  account registered, and by limiting access to functionality on those sites that  support the objectives of the Policy (e.g., prohibiting access to Facebook  games or applications). Departments are also encouraged to document their plans  for the incremental expansion of open access once a baseline is established.</p><p>In the rare case where business requirements or  operational circumstances may dictate the need for restricted access due to  security issues, options are available to departments to meet requirements of  the Policy. Some options include:</p><ul><li>Providing a standalone unclassified network on  which Web 2.0 tools are enabled; or</li><li>Installing kiosk stations or Wi-Fi hotspots that  provide open access.</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> The  implementation of an environment supporting open access does not extend to  access from classified domains. Connectivity of the classified domains  continues to be regulated under existing policy and standards on government  security, as well as lead security agency and departmental direction.</p><p>It is suggested that departments provide a process for  authorized individuals to request access to new websites or online tools, which  can be considered in future plans to expand access, given security  considerations.</p><h4>4.3.4. Reviewing and Evaluating Open Access Practices</h4><p>Departments are encouraged to review their open  access practices on an annual basis to assess progress and to address issues  that arise regarding changes in policy or emerging technologies. This will also  ensure that open access is being provided in accordance with the <em>Policy on Government Security</em>. Appendix  E of the Policy provides guidance on security measures to support the  implementation of the Policy and to protect Government of Canada networks,  devices and information.</p></section><section anchor="5.4" title="4.4 Providing Learning Opportunities for Authorized Individuals"><p>In general, risks associated with unacceptable use, security  incidents, and privacy breaches can be minimized through the provision of  effective learning opportunities supported by an effective monitoring  capability. Learning activities can reinforce the role of managers and  authorized individuals in ensuring good practices and compliance with policy  requirements. </p><p>When generating awareness about the Policy, departments may  want to inform managers and supervisors of the implications of the new Policy  in advance. Their role can help ensure compliance with the Policy, thereby  assuring the operational effectiveness and integrity of the department. This  can also better equip management and supervisors to respond to questions from  employees. </p><p>Consideration may also be given to linking key messages  about expected behaviours when using Government of Canada networks, devices and  Web 2.0 tools to the <em><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25049">Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</a></em> and the  departmental code of conduct. It may be important to reinforce that the same  rules regarding upholding the values of the public sector apply both online and  offline.</p><p>Learning opportunities may include, but are not limited  to:</p><ul><li>Information sessions (e.g., online or  in-person);</li><li>Orientation sessions for new employees,  including discussions on acceptable and unacceptable use of networks and  devices; </li><li>Canada School of Public Service and the Communications  Security Establishment IT Security Learning Centre course offerings; </li><li>Regular discussions between managers and their  staff;</li><li>Online learning products, including  self-assessment tests and YouTube videos;</li><li>Presentations at branch-level town halls, meetings  or workshops;</li><li>Communications products that can be distributed  to authorized individuals or posted in prominent locations in the workspace (<a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appF">Appendix F</a> provides sample  communication tools);</li><li>Communities of practice discussions, either  in-person or via internal Government of Canada online collaborative tools;</li><li>Mentoring programs, especially when helping  employees transition to the use of Web 2.0 tools as part of their work; and</li><li>Leveraging existing activities (e.g., Security  Awareness Week) to communicate key messages about the Policy.</li></ul><p>Ongoing learning opportunities allow departments to  update information as Internet-based tools continue to evolve, and can be  supplemented with examples that represent the department's individual  circumstances. It is recommended that the definitions (in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appA">Appendix A</a>) and the lists of non-exhaustive  examples of acceptable and unacceptable use, as described in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B of the Policy</a> and <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C of the Policy</a>, be considered when developing learning materials. Appendix F provides sample  learning tools.</p></section><section anchor="5.5" title="4.5 Monitoring Networks and Reporting"><p>Having the appropriate tools and processes in place to  identify and investigate suspected cases of unacceptable use can support the  accountability of deputy heads to address Policy non-compliance in an effective  and organized manner.</p><p>Data from network monitoring tools supply some of the  evidence needed to recognize and confirm incidents of unacceptable use. The  Policy requires that regular monthly, and as required, reports be provided  based on this data to assist departments in the identification, investigation,  and implementation of corrective action pertaining to unacceptable use. Where  network services are supplied by Shared Services Canada, the responsibility for  providing these reports lies with the deputy head of Shared Services Canada.  For those departments not served by Shared Services Canada, the responsibility  to meet this requirement resides with the individual department.</p><p>Following the validation of the initial implementation of  the Policy requirement regarding monitoring and reporting, departments may  consider liaising regularly with Shared Services Canada or the departmental  equivalent to ensure that monitoring tools are configured to generate the data  needed to assess the acceptable use of networks and devices.</p><p>Unacceptable use can range from minor to very serious  issues. Developing a Corrective Action Plan in advance to address incidents of  unacceptable use can assist the deputy head in resolving matters of  non-compliance efficiently and consistently. <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appD">Appendix D</a> provides a list  of key elements and suggested options for remedial action that could be  included in a Corrective Action Plan.</p></section></chapter><chapter anchor="6" title="5. Enquiries"><p>For questions on this guideline, please contact <a href="/contact/contact-eng.aspx">TBS Public Enquiries</a>.</p></chapter></chapters><appendices><appendix anchor="A" title="Appendix A: Definitions"><dl><dt><strong>Acceptable use</strong></dt><dd><p>Permitted  use of Government of Canada electronic networks and devices by authorized  individuals:</p><ul><li>To perform activities as a part of their  official duties;</li><li>For career development and other professional  activities; and</li><li>For limited personal use that is conducted on  personal time; that is not for financial gain; that does not incur any  additional costs for the department; and that does not interfere with the conduct  of business.</li></ul><p>All use of Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices must be in compliance with the Values and Ethics Code for the Public  Sector and all other related Treasury Board policies and departmental codes of  conduct and policies. Use of Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices must not give rise to a real, potential or apparent conflict of  interest or in any way undermine the integrity of the department. (See also <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B of the Policy</a>)</p></dd><dt><strong>Access</strong></dt><dd><p>Gaining  entry to an electronic network that the federal government has provided to  Government of Canada authorized individuals. Access to such electronic networks  may be from inside or outside government premises. Access may support telework  and remote access situations, or situations where authorized individuals are  using electronic networks provided by the federal government on their own time  for limited personal use.</p></dd><dt id="ai"><strong>Authorized  individuals</strong></dt><dd><p>Individuals working with the Government of Canada, including  employees of the federal government as well as casuals, contractors, students  and other persons who have been authorized by the deputy head to access  Government of Canada electronic networks and devices. </p></dd><dt><strong>Electronic network</strong></dt><dd><p>Groups  of computers and computer systems that can communicate with each other,  including without limitation, the Internet, Government of Canada electronic  data networks, voice and video network infrastructure, and public and private  networks external to a department. The network includes both wired and wireless  components.</p></dd><dt><strong>Internet</strong></dt><dd><p>A global  system of interconnected computer networks that use the standard Internet  protocol suite (<abbr title="Transmission Control Protocol and Internet Protocol">TCP/IP</abbr>) to serve users worldwide.</p></dd><dt><strong>Learning opportunities</strong></dt><dd><p>Diverse  learning methods or tools, formal or informal, to generate awareness or acquire  knowledge about the acceptable use of Government of Canada electronic networks  and devices and Government of Canada and external Web 2.0 tools and services.  These approaches can include, but are not limited to, information or  orientation sessions, YouTube video, information provided on departmental  intranet sites, manager debriefs, account sign-on notifications and electronic  newsletters.</p></dd><dt><strong>Monitoring  practices</strong></dt><dd><p>Use of a software system that monitors an electronic network for  slow or failing components, and notifies the network administrator in cases of  outages, and that can monitor the network activity of specific individuals for  which there is suspicion of unacceptable network usage. Recording and analysis  of the use of electronic networks are used for operational purposes and for  assessing compliance with government policy.</p><dl><dt><strong>Regular  monitoring</strong></dt><dd><p>Includes practices conducted in the course of operations within  a department. These practices can include operational analysis of logs  indicating the Internet sites visited by authorized individuals, the files  downloaded or uploaded, and the key-word searches of files on Government of  Canada network servers or user devices accessing the network.</p></dd><dt><strong>Special  monitoring</strong></dt><dd><p>May be used when unacceptable use is suspected because of  anomalies found in network usage patterns; logged attempts to access restricted  areas on the network or sites that are unacceptable or deemed a legitimate IT  security threat to the network; or reports of possible unacceptable use.</p></dd></dl></dd><dt><strong>Open access</strong></dt><dd><p>Refers  to the provision of Internet access, in accordance with the Policy on  Government Security, to authorized individuals via Government of Canada  electronic networks and devices that, from the perspective of firewall  settings, is substantively equivalent irrespective of department or access  medium. Internet sites that enhance productivity, communication and  collaboration are not blocked with the exception of those that present a  legitimate IT security threat and where content substantively falls into the  category of unacceptable use.</p></dd><dt><strong>Unacceptable use</strong></dt><dd><p>Any  activity that violates Treasury Board or departmental policy instruments or  other published requirements, including, but not limited to, activity or  behavior that:</p><ul><li>May give rise to criminal offences;</li><li>Violates federal and provincial statutes; </li><li>Impacts negatively on the performance of  Government of Canada electronic networks and devices;</li><li>Impedes departmental operations or the delivery  of services; </li><li>Breaches the Duty of Loyalty requirement for  public servants (i.e., does not refrain from public criticism of the Government  of Canada); and</li><li>Could be deemed to reasonably result in civil  lawsuits. (See also <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C of the Policy</a></li></ul></dd><dt><strong>User devices</strong></dt><dd><p>Physical  devices found or brought into the work environment that are used by authorized  individuals to access Government of Canada electronic networks and databases.  The physical devices can include, but are not limited to, the following:  desktop workstations, laptops, notebooks, tablets, smartphones, cellphones,  peripherals such as printers and scanners, memory devices such as <abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr> flash  drives, <abbr title="Compact Disc">CD</abbr> drives and <abbr title="Digital Versatile Disc">DVD</abbr> drives, webcams and any other computer hardware used  to obtain, store or send information.</p></dd><dt><strong>Web  2.0</strong></dt><dd><p>Includes Internet-based tools and services that  allow for participatory multi-way information sharing, dialogue, syndication,  and user-generated content. This can include social media and collaborative  technologies.</p></dd></dl></appendix><appendix anchor="B" title="Appendix B: Consulting Departmental Subject Matter Experts"><p>The following is a list of departmental subject  matter experts to engage when implementing the <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> (the Policy) and developing Corrective Action Plans. Consultations with these  specialists can confirm a sound management approach to implementation and  ensure that related legislation and policy requirements are being respected.</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Subject Matter<br />
            Experts</th><th scope="col">Reasons To Consult</th></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Access to Information and Privacy</strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Ensures    that privacy concerns are considered;</li><li>Confirms    that the operational processes and procedures needed to implement the Policy    requirements are compliant with the Access to Information and Privacy (<abbr title="Access to Information and Privacy">ATIP</abbr>)    legal and policy framework; and </li><li>Provides    expert advice when investigating potential cases of unacceptable use and    Policy non-compliance.</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Communications</strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Provides    strategic communications advice for the creation of key messages and    materials conveying the Policy oversight responsibilities of management and    the expected behaviour of authorized individuals when using departmental    networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools and services;</li><li>Assists    in the development and review of key messages for managers to support a    consistent approach to communicating the Policy requirements that authorized    individuals can understand and can act upon; and</li><li>Identifies    opportunities in the department's communications calendar for promoting    Policy awareness (e.g., intranet spotlights or articles in the departmental    newsletter).</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Human Resources </strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Assists    in the development or review of the Corrective Action Plan to ensure that    proposed resolutions (informal and formal) address cases of unacceptable use;    and </li><li>Assists    on a case-by-case basis on known cases of unacceptable use.</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Information Management</strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Validates    business needs and determines how appropriate information management    practices can be incorporated into operational processes relating to the    implementation of the Policy (e.g., what and why information needs to be    collected and who needs access to it and for how long); and</li><li>Checks    proposed retention and disposition schedules of data supporting the    identification, investigation and corrective action of non-compliance with    the Policy (e.g., monitoring data, reports, and documentation linked to    investigations of unacceptable use).</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Security</strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Provides    expert advice when investigating potential cases of unacceptable use and    policy breaches from both an IT Security and the corporate security    perspective;</li><li>Ensures    that effective management and monitoring practices supporting the    implementation of the Policy comply with the <em>Policy on Government Security</em>;</li><li>Ensures    that IT Security and corporate security concerns are considered (i.e., an    understanding of the risks, potential threats and necessary mitigation    measures in order to support the policy). See Appendix    E of the <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> for security    consideration best practices;</li><li>Ensures    that the departmental network security authorizations consider and include    the operation of Web 2.0 tools and open access;</li><li>Provides    endorsement that the operational processes and procedures needed to implement    Policy requirements are compliant with the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-5/">Security of Information Act</a>;</li><li>Confirms    the appropriate security clearance for individuals granted access rights to    information gathered through regular and special monitoring of networks and    devices; and</li><li>Identifies    opportunities to generate awareness about the Policy through departmental    security awareness initiatives (e.g., Security Awareness Week, departmental    security training and awareness programs).</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Legal Services</strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Confirms    that the management approach and the proposed operational processes and    procedures supporting implementation of the Policy respect related laws and    regulations;</li><li>Advices    on privacy considerations relating to regular and special monitoring    practices; and</li><li>Reviews    network sign-on and other electronic and paper-based notifications used to    inform authorized individuals of expectations of acceptable use, monitoring    practices and consequences of unacceptable use.</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Values and Ethics</strong></p></td><td><ul><li>Examines    the communication materials used to inform authorized individuals of    expectations of acceptable use of networks, devices, and social media to    ensure alignment with the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public    Sector</em> and the departmental code of conduct;</li><li>Answers    questions about the linkage between conflict of interest and wrongdoing in    the workplace, and appropriate and inappropriate use of electronic networks,    devices and Web 2.0 tools and services; and</li><li>Identifies    opportunities to raise awareness about the Policy during corporate awareness    activities on values and ethics.</li></ul></td></tr></table><p>A continuing liaison with subject matter experts  during implementation and beyond is considered a best practice to support  monitoring of policy compliance. In addition to consulting internally,  gathering best practices and lessons learned from colleagues external to the  department may also yield concrete benefits. Engaging horizontally can identify  solutions to implementation challenges, identify efficiencies by avoiding  duplication of effort and encourage a more consistent implementation approach  across the Government of Canada. This can be accomplished by consulting  established networks and by leveraging the knowledge and expertise of active  interdepartmental corporate service communities on <a href="http://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/wiki/?setlang=en">GCpedia</a> and <a href="http://www.gcforums.gc.ca/">GCforums</a> (e.g., <abbr title="Access to Information and Privacy">ATIP</abbr>,  Human Resources, Information Management, Internal Services, IT Security and the  Security Awareness Working Group).</p></appendix><appendix anchor="C" title="Appendix C: Sample Implementation Plan Template"><p>This appendix provides a sample implementation  plan template for the <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> (the Policy). It is recommended that departments adapt this tool and others in  this Guideline for their own needs based on their current state of open access.  A good practice is to include all subject matter experts in the creation of the  implementation plan to ensure that other policy considerations will be  addressed in the plan.</p><div class="borderSimple"><h3 class="alignCenter darkgreyBG">Sample Implementation Plan Template</h3><h4 class="lightgreyBG">1.0 Document Title</h4><p>[Department Name] Plan to Implement the Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">2.0 Purpose</h4><p>This section states the goal(s) and objectives of the plan (i.e., what is to be achieved).</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">3.0 Background or Introduction</h4><p>This section provides an overview of the work to be done as well as appropriate information about the requirements and the approach to implement the Policy. </p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">4.0 Consultations</h4><p>This section identifies subject matter experts who have been consulted during the creation of the implementation plan and outlines the rationale for including them in the process.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">5.0 Roles and Responsibilities</h4><p>This section identifies the name of the responsible individual or functional team leading and coordinating the implementation, and the departmental areas that will be responsible for key functions. It also outlines the roles and responsibilities of those who will be involved in completing the tasks needed to implement the Policy.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">6.0 Scheduled Tasks</h4><p>This section lists the tasks to be implemented chronologically, the individual or group responsible and the timeline for completion. It is recommended to include beginning and end dates for each task.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">7.0 Resources</h4><p>This section proposes the various resources needed to implement the plan (e.g., human, financial, and software). It may also include the training necessary for personnel implementing the plan.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">8.0 Risk Mitigation</h4><p>This section describes the options and actions to reduce the risks that may pose a threat to the implementation of the plan. The risks and mitigation strategies may be identified through a separate risk management process (i.e., Harmonized Threat and Risk Assessment and Security Assessment and Authorizations).</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">9.0 Measuring Performance and Evaluation</h4><p>This section describes the approach to measuring the success of the implementation. It states how success will be defined and what data will be used to report on implementation results.</p></div></appendix><appendix anchor="D" title="Appendix D: Corrective Action Plans and Options for Remedial Action"><p>This section lists remedial solutions and suggests that  remedial action is taken on a case-by-case basis. A Corrective Action Plan is a  series of steps that are undertaken to address non-compliance and prevent its  reoccurrence. Remedial action does not always have to be reactive; preplanning  can potentially reduce the response time and increase the ability to handle  issues in a timely manner. </p><p>It is conceivable that options for addressing  different cases of unacceptable use may be available, depending on the severity  of the situation. Incidents of unacceptable use may be easily identified,  contained or eliminated through immediate corrective action, while others may  require a longer period of review to confirm the non-compliance, and to propose  and implement a resolution. In either situation, it is recommended that  departments be proactive in developing a Corrective Action Plan with options  for remedial action to ensure that instances of unacceptable use are handled  effectively and efficiently.</p><section anchor="D.1" title="Corrective Action Plan"><p>The details of a Corrective Action Plan will depend on departmental needs; however, the plan does not have to be overly complex to be practical. Some elements of a Corrective Action Plan could include, but are not limited to, the following:</p><div class="borderSimple"><h3 class="alignCenter darkgreyBG">Sample Corrective Action Plan Template</h3><h4 class="lightgreyBG">1.0 Document Title</h4><p><em>Corrective Action Plan for Incidents of Non-Compliance  With the "Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use".</em></p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">2.0 Purpose</h4><p>This section states the goal(s) and objectives of the plan (i.e., what is to be achieved).</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">3.0 Background or Introduction</h4><p>This section provides an overview of the corrective action process as well as high-level information about the requirements and the approach to implementing corrective action in suspected cases of non-compliance with the Policy. </p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">4.0 Corrective Action Plan Process</h4><p>This section outlines all actions needed to identify, investigate and resolve any deficiencies in meeting Policy requirements. </p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">5.0 Schedule of Activities</h4><p>This section maps the activities to a schedule, including target completion timelines for actions to alleviate immediate risks and in some cases, for preventive measures to curtail the threat of reoccurrence.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">6.0 Resources</h4><p>This section proposes the various resources needed to  implement the plan (e.g., human, financial, and software). This section highlights:</p><ul><li>The position responsible for monitoring and  maintaining the corrective action process;</li><li>Positions or functional units responsible for  implementing the corrective action activities;</li><li>Information needed to identify and investigate  suspected cases of unacceptable use; and</li><li>Special equipment, software or services (e.g.,  management of network monitoring software and reports supplied by departmental  functional specialists or Shared Services Canada equivalents) needed to execute  the plan.</li></ul><h4 class="lightgreyBG">7.0 Training and Learning Opportunities</h4><p>This section identifies any special training needed to  execute the plan for:</p><ul><li>Individuals implicated in the corrective action  process, including notifications and guidance on procedural updates; and</li><li>Managers and their role in executing the  corrective action activities.</li></ul><p>It also identifies any new materials needed for  management or authorized users of the network to reduce the risk of  reoccurrence.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">8.0 Corrective Action Scenarios</h4><p>This section lists types of non-compliance and outlines corresponding  remedial solutions. It also provides information about the resources and  timelines associated with the corrective action, including, but not limited to: </p><ul><li>Type of non-compliance (e.g., excessive use of  bandwidth, disproportionate use of social media unrelated to work-related  duties, or disclosure of sensitive information);</li><li>Type of corrective action to be taken and how it  will be implemented;</li><li>Date of completion (e.g., duration, including  start and end dates);</li><li>Individual or functional unit responsible for  implementation;</li><li>Steps to validate the implementation of the  corrective action; and</li><li>Position responsible for verifying the  effectiveness of the remedial action.</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> This approach could also be used for reporting to the  champion and other executives on the status of issues related to  non-compliance.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">9.0 Communication</h4><p>This section describes who needs to be notified of non-compliance and the work being undertaken to rectify the problem. It also defines from whom the approval is required and how it will be obtained (only if approvals are required) to proceed with certain corrective action measures.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">10.0 Performance Monitoring and Evaluation</h4><p>This section summarizes how the department will monitor the effectiveness of the plan throughout implementation to determine whether the plan achieves the intended goals. It will also validate the corrective action process and determine whether improvements are required.</p><h4 class="lightgreyBG">11.0 Reporting</h4><p>This section outlines the information to be included in the management report and the frequency with which the Champion and other executives will be informed of issues of non-compliance with the Policy, including any incidents and corresponding resolutions to mitigate future risks.</p></div></section><section anchor="D.2" title="Options for Remedial Action"><p>Triggers initiating a corrective action process can be  determined by analyzing network performance reports linked to data about  unacceptable use or by investigating a complaint of unacceptable use received  by a manager or another employee. This can lead to informal and more formal  remedial action to address issues of non-compliance, depending on the  seriousness of the problem.</p><p>In less severe cases, departments may want to consider a  more informal approach to address non-compliance. For example, excessive  bandwidth use could trigger a system-generated message to confirm whether  Policy non-compliance is linked to a legitimate work-related activity or to  address a minor non-malicious breach of the Policy without formal action being  taken. The preliminary notification can also be used as an awareness  opportunity to restate departmental bandwidth usage limits.</p><p>Processes for repeated unacceptable use may include  secondary or subsequent e-mail warnings to the authorized user, his or her  immediate supervisor, the branch executive and human resources to rectify the  issue. As a best practice a progressive approach is recommended, such as the  following:</p><ul><li>The first notification is sent to the authorized  individual to confirm unacceptable use, to remind the recipient of the Policy  requirements and how to avoid the unacceptable behaviour in the future;</li><li>The second notification is sent to the  authorized individual and his or her manager;</li><li>The third notification is sent to the authorized  individual, his or her manager, the branch executive and human resources, for  further follow-up.</li></ul><p>More formal methods of corrective action could be applied  upon repeated minor abuses of Government of Canada networks and devices by  those who have been previously warned of their unacceptable use or when serious  cases of unacceptable use have been confirmed. These corrective actions can  include an oral or a written reprimand, revocation or limitation of network  access, or suspension or termination of employment. It may be required that  each case of unacceptable use be assessed on an individual basis and reviewed  by the relevant departmental subject matter experts noted in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B</a>. These actions  would be independent of any criminal or civil proceeding against an authorized  individual.</p><p><strong>Note:</strong> It is good practice to conduct a review of the  proposed Corrective Action Plan with appropriate departmental experts (refer to <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B</a>) to ensure  that privacy, security and information management requirements are considered.</p></section></appendix><appendix anchor="E" title="Appendix E: Sample Communications Statements"><p>This appendix provides sample statements that can be used to  communicate the expectations of acceptable use, departmental monitoring  practices and consequences of unacceptable use to authorized individuals who  use Government of Canada electronic networks and devices, and Web 2.0  tools and services.</p><p>These sample statements can be adapted and tailored by  departments as needed. Before using these statements, it is recommended that  they be reviewed by the departmental subject matter experts identified in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27907&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B</a> of this  guideline, to ensure consistency with other policies (e.g., human resources,  privacy and security) and other departmental requirements.</p><section anchor="E.1" title="Expectations of Acceptable Use"><ul><li>By using Government of Canada electronic  networks and devices, authorized individuals agree to the terms and conditions  set out by legislation, and relevant Treasury Board policies and departmental  documentation governing the use of Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices.</li><li>Authorized users of Government of Canada  electronic networks and devices are expected to:
            <ul><li>Use Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices in a responsible and informed way;</li><li>Understand the obligations of expected behaviour  outlined in the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> and the departmental code of conduct, which apply at all times when using  Government of Canada and external Web 2.0 tools and services;</li><li>Take precautions to protect electronic network  and device passwords and accounts from unauthorized access and other misuse;</li><li>Contact management when in doubt about proper  usage procedures and practices; and</li><li>Inform departmental security officials  immediately of any suspected security incidents related to the use of  electronic networks and devices.</li></ul></li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> Examples of  acceptable and unacceptable use in <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B of the Policy</a> and <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C of the Policy</a> can also support an understanding of expectations.</p></section><section anchor="E.2" title="Monitoring Practices"><ul><li>The  network is restricted to authorized individuals only and the department  reserves the right to monitor network activity. All blocking and monitoring  will be done in compliance with the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/"><em>Privacy Act</em></a> and the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/page-15.html#h-39"><em>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</em></a>.</li><li>Electronic network and device monitoring is  conducted for work-related purposes (e.g., assessing system or network  performance, protecting government resources or ensuring compliance with  Treasury Board and departmental policies and codes of conduct.</li><li>All information transmitted and stored on  Government of Canada networks and devices, whether professional or personal in  nature, may be accessible under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a> and the <em>Privacy Act</em>, subject to exclusions and exemptions under these  Acts.</li><li>Special monitoring may be permitted without  notice in instances when investigating potential cases of unacceptable use.</li><li>Special monitoring may include using any of the  regular monitoring practices of the organization in a user-specific manner to  find relevant information. It may also include additional investigation, such  as, reading the contents of individual e-mail, hard drives, shared drives,  document management systems, <abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr> drives, or other Government of Canada-provided  electronic network or storage systems. </li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> It is  recommended that regular monitoring practices be communicated in a privacy  notice, as outlined in Appendix  D of the Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use.</p></section><section anchor="E.3" title="Consequences of Unacceptable Use"><ul><li>Disciplinary measures or sanctions may be taken  as deemed appropriate as a result of unacceptable use of electronic networks or  devices by authorized individuals.</li><li>The measures taken will be assessed on a  case-by-case basis, and may include:
            <ul><li>Oral or written reprimand; </li><li>Revocation or limitation of network access;</li><li>Revocation of security clearance; or</li><li>Suspension or termination of employment.</li></ul></li><li>Disciplinary action shall be independent of any  criminal or civil proceeding against an authorized individual.</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> Further  information and guidance regarding disciplinary measures can be found in the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=17151"><em>Framework for the Management of Compliance</em></a> and the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=22370"><em>Guidelines for Discipline</em></a>.</p></section></appendix><appendix anchor="F" title="Appendix F: Sample Learning Tools"><p>Various tools may be used to support the development of  materials to generate awareness of the requirements of the <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> (the Policy) for  authorized individuals using Government of Canada networks and devices. The  topics of communication include:</p><ul class="noBullet"><li>1. Employee Use of Social Media;</li><li>2. Frequently Asked Questions Regarding the <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em>;</li><li>3. Use of External Storage Devices;</li><li>4. Security Reminder Bulletin; and</li><li>5. Smartphone Etiquette.</li></ul><section anchor="F.1" title="1. Employee Use of Social Media"><div class="borderSimple lightgreyBG"><h4 class="alignCenter">Types of Social Media Use:</h4><dl><dt><strong>Official use:</strong></dt><dd><p>Using  an official social media account for Government of Canada purposes such as  communication, service delivery, collaboration and other purposes within the  scope of a department's mandate, including as a designated spokesperson for the  department.</p></dd><dt><strong>Professional use:</strong></dt><dd><p>Using a personal social media account for purposes related to professional  activities, including professional associations and networking (e.g.,  participating in an online conference), knowledge gathering or sharing (e.g.,  using Twitter to stay up-to-date on trends; visiting government Facebook  pages), and career development (e.g., maintaining a LinkedIn profile).</p></dd><dt><strong>Personal  use:</strong></dt><dd><p>Using a personal social media account for  purposes unrelated to professional development or employment (e.g., blogging  about gardening tips; sharing family photos).</p></dd></dl></div><p>Social media and other Web 2.0 tools and services are rapidly changing the personal and professional lives of public servants. Opportunities that now exist for networking and collaborating on a global scale were unthinkable a generation ago. The majority of Canadians now use social media on a regular basis and employees of the Government of Canada are no exception.</p><p>As the citizens, communities and clients served by government increase their use of Web 2.0 tools and services to organize, share, and interact, government employees are becoming more active in these online spaces in their roles as public servants. Whether using a wiki to develop a new policy instrument collaboratively, following and engaging with experts and  thought-leaders on Twitter, or managing an official departmental Facebook page  to answer questions from citizens, Web 2.0 tools and services are becoming a  larger part of our professional lives. These same Web 2.0 tools and services  are often used in our personal lives, blurring the boundaries between online  interactions as public servants and as private citizens. As the <a href="http://www.clerk.gc.ca/eng/feature.asp?pageId=297"><em>Prime Minister's Advisory Committee on the Public Service</em></a> noted, "These tools are transformative and unstoppable and the Public Service  must take full advantage of these new ways of working."</p><div class="borderSimple lightgreyBG"><h4 class="alignCenter">What is Web 2.0?</h4><p>"Web 2.0" is a broad term that refers to Internet-based tools and services that allow for participatory, multi-way information sharing, as opposed to earlier uses of the web that were primarily characterized by one-directional publishing of information. The term "Web 2.0" is often used interchangeably with "social media," and includes popular platforms such as Twitter, Facebook, and YouTube, or blogging platforms like Tumblr. These platforms allow participants to have a distinct user profile which they use to create and share user-generated content such as text, pictures or videos, and to facilitate community interaction. "Web 2.0" can also include technologies such as wikis or Google Docs, which allow multiple users to create and edit content collaboratively.</p></div><p>These new online collaboration tools offer tremendous benefits. However, in an era of instant global communications, it is important to consider the special responsibilities that we have as employees of the Government of Canada, including for the use of Government of Canada networks and devices. The public service has a long and proud tradition of providing impartial advice to the government of the day. This is derived from the importance and necessity of an impartial and effective public service to achieve its mission of helping the duly elected government, under law, to serve the public interest.</p><p>The <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> applies whenever  using a Government of Canada network or a Government of Canada-issued device,  including a work computer while at the office, a work device (e.g., a  Government of Canada laptop or smartphone) on a home network, or a work or  personal device to remotely access a government network. When using the  Internet, social media and other Web 2.0 tools and services, it is important that Government of Canada employees consider the context of online activities and apply the same judgement that they would to a similar activity in the offline world.</p><div class="borderSimple lightgreyBG"><h4 class="alignCenter">Want to learn more about acceptable use of social media? </h4><p>For an engaging overview of important points to keep in mind  as an employee using social media, take a look at the online video “Social  Media at Work”, developed by Transport Canada and the Treasury Board of Canada  Secretariat.</p><ul><li><a href="http://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/wiki/Social_media_at_work_-_Les_m%C3%A9dias_sociaux_au_travail">GCpedia version</a></li><li><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JRvY1SzWhl0">YouTube version</a></li></ul></div><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><caption><strong>Whenever    Using Social Media:</strong></caption><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Do</th><th scope="col">Don’t</th></tr><tr><td>Use    good judgment and common sense in all you do; your obligations as a public    servant apply at all times.</td><td>Assume    that a post is private, even when using a pseudonym; treat online posts as if    they will be permanently and publicly available and attributable.</td></tr><tr><td>State    clearly in your social media profile (used for professional purposes) that    your views are your own, not those of your employer. <strong>Remember:</strong> This statement does not absolve you of your obligations    as a public servant or the expected behaviours described in the Values and    Ethics Code for the Public Sector and your departmental codes of conduct.</td><td>Disclose    any classified, confidential, sensitive, or third-party information, or    personal information about others.</td></tr><tr><td>Move    work-related conversations to official channels (e.g., e-mail) so that there    is a record of any guidance provided or decisions taken.</td><td>Use <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> corporate symbols or signatures inappropriately. They are only for    official use and their use is subject to the <em>Federal Identity Program Policy</em> and related standards. For more    information, visit the <a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/fip-pcim/index-eng.asp" class="underLine">Federal Identity Program website</a>.</td></tr><tr><td>Maintain    the impartiality and objectivity of the public service by not expressing    opinions that could impair your ability to be seen as performing your duties    in an objective or impartial manner.</td><td>Respond    to requests for media statements or interviews related to your work    (including from online media-like blogs) unless you are an authorized    spokesperson. Send all media requests to your departmental media relations    advisor.</td></tr><tr><td>Speak    with your manager or Values and Ethics advisor if you are uncertain or have    questions about any of your online activities.</td><td>Register    or associate a <abbr title="Government of Canada">GC</abbr> e-mail address to a social media account unless it will be    used explicitly for official or professional purposes.</td></tr></table></section><section anchor="F.2" title="2. Frequently Asked Questions about the Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use"><p>The following are examples of quick reference material that could be published on departmental intranets and wikis clarifying Policy requirements for authorized users of Government of Canada networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools and services.</p><h4>Are public servants allowed to use the Internet and Web 2.0 tools and services?</h4><p>Yes! The use of, and open access to, the Internet through  Government of Canada electronic networks and devices is essential to  transforming the way public servants work and serve Canadians. Open access to  the Internet, including Government of Canada and external Web 2.0 tools and  services, enhances communication, collaboration and productivity, and  encourages the sharing of knowledge and expertise to support innovation. Open  access to the Internet, including Government of Canada and external Web 2.0  tools and services, will be provided by departments by April 1, 2014, through a  phased implementation of the new <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> (the Policy). </p><h4>What is considered to be acceptable use?</h4><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appB">Appendix B of the Policy</a> provides examples of acceptable use of Government of Canada  networks and devices. Permitted use of Government of Canada electronic networks  and devices by authorized individuals includes:</p><ul><li>To perform activities as a part of their  official duties; </li><li>For career development and other professional  activities; and </li><li>For limited personal use that is conducted on  personal time; that is not for financial gain; that does not incur any  additional costs for the department; and that does not interfere with the  conduct of business. </li></ul><p>All use of Government of Canada electronic networks and  devices must be in compliance with the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> and all other  related Treasury Board policies and departmental codes of conduct and policies.  Use of Government of Canada electronic networks and devices must not give rise  to a real, potential or apparent conflict of interest or in any way undermine  the integrity of the department. </p><h4>What is considered to be unacceptable use?</h4><p><a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#appC">Appendix C of the Policy</a> provides examples of unacceptable use of Government of  Canada networks and devices. Unacceptable use refers to any activity that  violates Treasury Board or organizational policy instruments or other published  requirements, including, but not limited to, an activity or behaviour that:</p><ul><li>May give rise to criminal offences;</li><li>Violates federal or provincial statutes;</li><li>Impacts negatively on the performance of  Government of Canada electronic networks and devices;</li><li>Impedes departmental operations or the delivery  of services;</li><li>Breaches the “Duty of Loyalty” requirement for  public servants (e.g., impairing or seen to be impairing the objectivity and  impartiality of the public servant, the department or the Government of  Canada); or</li><li>Could result in liability.</li></ul><h4>What is a "Government of Canada electronic network or device?"</h4><p>Electronic networks are groups of computers and computer systems that can communicate with each other, including but not limited to, the Internet, Government of Canada electronic data networks, voice and video network infrastructures, and public and private networks external to a department. Networks include both wired and wireless components. Devices include anything approved for use to access these networks or network resources, such as a desktop, laptop or tablet computer, memory devices such as <abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr> flash drives, or a smartphone.</p><h4>How do the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> and my departmental code of conduct apply?</h4><p>It is important to remember that the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> and your  departmental code of conduct apply to online activities at all times, just as  they do to your offline activities, irrespective of whether they happen at work  or at home, or via a government or personally provided network or device.</p><p>Respecting the <em>Values  and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> and your departmental code of conduct  is a condition of employment in the public service. Violating them, including  through inappropriate online activities, can have consequences for employment  up to, and including, termination.</p><div class="borderSimple lightgreyBG"><h4 class="alignCenter">Respecting the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> in Online Activities</h4><p>The following are examples of how the values and  expected behaviours in the <em>Values and Ethics Code for the Public Sector</em> can be applied to public servants’ use of electronic networks, electronic  devices and social media, both officially and outside the office. These  examples are not exhaustive. Public servants must also consult their departmental  code of conduct and policy requirements.</p><dl><dt><strong>Respect for Democracy</strong></dt><dd><p>Public servants uphold Canadian parliamentary democracy and its institutions by ensuring that their online communications are non-partisan and impartial at all times, and do not engage in public discussion of departmental policies or elected officials that call into question their objectivity in carrying out their official duties.</p></dd><dt><strong>Respect for People</strong></dt><dd><p>Public servants demonstrate their respect for human dignity and the value of every person by ensuring their online communications are respectful of all individuals and groups of people, including colleagues, managers and members of the public.</p></dd><dt><strong>Integrity</strong></dt><dd><p>Public servants serve the public interest by ensuring, for example, that their official communications activities are not used for any inappropriate personal advantage and that government systems and equipment are not used to support personal businesses owned by them, their family or their friends.</p></dd><dt><strong>Stewardship</strong></dt><dd><p>Public servants demonstrate good stewardship by using electronic networks to share knowledge and information that will contribute to more effective program delivery, and by using network resources efficiently and effectively.</p></dd><dt><strong>Excellence</strong></dt><dd><p>Public servants demonstrate professionalism and excellence in the workplace by ensuring official communications respect Canada's official languages and by using social or other electronic media for team work, learning and innovation.</p></dd></dl></div></section><section anchor="F.3" title="3. Use of External Storage Devices"><p>The use of external storage devices can increase efficiency  and data mobility, as well as reduce the amount of physical space needed to  store information. However, these devices also present a risk for information  and IT security, privacy breaches and theft. It is important that departments  communicate to authorized individuals about the proper use of external storage  devices to minimize the risk involved.</p><p>An external storage device can include all <abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr> storage  devices (e.g., <abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr> drives, flash drives, thumb drives, jump drives, and memory  sticks), portable hard drives and any other device with storage capacity  connecting through a departmental corporate asset as well as other non-<abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr> based portable devices (e.g., <abbr title="Compact Disc">CD</abbr>/<abbr title="Digital Versatile Disc">DVD</abbr>s and SD cards). Note: It may be beneficial  to provide examples of things that might not be top of mind but connect through <abbr title="Universal Serial Bus">USB</abbr>-based and have storage capacity (e.g., cell and smartphones, and cameras).</p><p>When developing departmental guidance or direction on the  use of external storage devices, information provided may include:</p><ul><li>A description of the process for acquiring an  external storage device;</li><li>Departmental policy regarding unapproved or  unencrypted storage devices connecting to the network;</li><li>Requirements about the physical security of the  device since responsibility for the security of the device resides with the  user; </li><li>Risks associated with the use of the device and  the different security measures to minimize the risks including:
            <ul><li>Storing the device in a locked cabinet when not  in use;</li><li>Establishing strong passwords to protect  unauthorized access to the device; and</li><li>Ensuring that the device is not left unattended,  especially in a public area;</li></ul></li><li>Types/levels of encryption required for the  different work being performed;</li><li>Recordkeeping requirements of files stored on  the devices (e.g., files on the device are considered copies of the original  and they are not the primary record); </li><li>Backing up information since it may not be  recoverable if erased;</li><li>Requirements about personal information being  stored on external storage devices:
            <ul><li>Is it permitted? and</li><li>If so, what types of personal information are  permissible and should it be encrypted?</li></ul></li><li>Procedures to follow if a storage device will be  holding personal information (e.g., refer to the <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26154"><em>Guideline for Privacy Breaches</em></a>);</li><li>A disclaimer stating that the department is not  responsible for the loss or corruption of personal data stored on a device;</li><li>Who to contact in the event of damage, loss or  theft of a storage device or if users have questions regarding an external  storage device;</li><li>References to other Government of Canada or  departmental policies that support the acceptable use of devices; and</li><li>Consequences of unacceptable use.</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> The Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat <em>Information Technology Policy Implementation  Notice (ITPIN)</em> outlines the mandatory requirements for departmental use of  external storage devices.</p></section><section anchor="E.4" title="4. Security Reminder Bulletin"><p>The following is an example of reminder material that  departments could send to authorized individuals in order to meet the  requirements of <a href="/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27122&amp;section=text#cha6">Section  6.1.2 of the Policy</a>. This reminder can also serve to offer learning  opportunities for authorized individuals.</p><h4>Your Monthly Security Reminder: Handling Your BlackBerry</h4><p>A departmental BlackBerry device comes with many  responsibilities for its protection and the data that it contains. If you have  been issued a departmental BlackBerry device, please keep the following in  mind:</p><ul><li>BlackBerry voice communications are not considered  secure, and as such, the device must not be used to discuss sensitive  information when used in phone mode. Blackberries deployed with  Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions functionality enabled can be used  to transmit data through electronic messaging up to and including the level of  Protected B. Classified information cannot be transmitted, either by voice or  data on a BlackBerry device;</li><li><abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr>-to-<abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr> messaging, unlike BlackBerry e-mails,  is unencrypted, which means that the messages are not secure and should only be  used for unclassified and emergency communications; </li><li>If an employee no longer needs his or her  BlackBerry, it should not be used by another employee since its <abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr> number is a  unique identifier for the device. If your BlackBerry is “recycled,” a <abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr>-to-<abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr> message meant for you would unintentionally be sent to the employee  who now has the device; </li><li>BlackBerry <abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr>-to-<abbr title="Personal Identification Number">PIN</abbr> and text messages are  subject to Access to Information and Privacy (<abbr title="Access to Information and Privacy">ATIP</abbr>) requests; </li><li>BlackBerry e-mail messages are vulnerable to the  same threats as other e-mail programs; these threats can include viruses,  Trojans and phishing attacks. If you receive an e-mail and do not recognize the  sender, do not open it——simply delete it; </li><li>When using the camera feature of a BlackBerry,  be careful not to take photos of sensitive information or equipment; </li><li>Photos taken with a BlackBerry are subject to <abbr title="Access to Information and Privacy">ATIP</abbr> requests and to the same records  retention criteria as other documents and correspondence; </li><li>Photos of colleagues should not be taken with a  BlackBerry or posted on social media without their consent. In addition, you  should carefully consider the photos that you choose to store in your Outlook  mailbox or on departmental network drives, since they take up large amounts of  valuable disk space;</li><li>Some devices will save key metadata (i.e.,  geolocation) whenever a photo is taken. This information may have privacy or  operational security implications and should be carefully scrutinized before  the posting of photos; and </li><li>If your BlackBerry is lost or stolen, report it  immediately by using the Self-Service tool or by contacting [contact name]. </li></ul><div class="alignCenter"><p><strong>Security: It's everyone's responsibility!</strong></p></div></section><section anchor="E.5" title="5. Smartphone Etiquette"><p>The use of smartphones is prevalent  in a mobile workplace. Although smartphones can enable greater connectedness  with colleagues and support increased productivity, they can also be  disruptive. Expecting a common sense approach to using these devices is not a  guarantee. To ensure that they are used in the manner for which they were  intended, Shared Services Canada (<abbr title="Shared Services Canada">SSC</abbr>) has developed an <a href="http://extranet.ssc-spc.gc.ca/eng/forgovernment/it-infrastructure-services/cost-effective-telephone-services/ios-acd">Interim Operating Standard on the Acceptable Use of Cellular Devices</a>, which departments not receiving their  network services from <abbr title="Shared Services Canada">SSC</abbr> may find useful. Departments may also find it  worthwhile to promote awareness of smartphone etiquette. The following table of  key messages could be used to communicate information about this subject:</p><table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="3" class="widthFull"><tr class="lightgreyBG"><th scope="col">Work-related    Device</th><th scope="col">Personal    Device</th></tr><tr><td><ul><li>Do    not lend the phone or share the access password; </li><li>Limit    the presence and use of smartphones during meetings; </li><li>Choose    professional ringtone types and adjust volume settings to vibrate or low;</li><li>Keep    personal use of department-issued devices to a minimum;</li><li>Select    appropriate places when using cellphones to conduct business (e.g., private    area);</li><li>Do    not bring cellular phones into secure discussion areas;</li><li>Use    devices appropriately in public places (e.g., restaurants, theatres and    hospitals);</li><li>Refrain    from putting the phone on speaker mode when talking about work-related issues    in earshot of others;</li><li>Avoid    incurring new costs to the organization (e.g., downloading of personal    applications or new ringtones); </li><li>Know    the rules about using the camera (if activated) to avoid the risk of    potential security incidents or privacy breaches; and</li><li>Do    not disclose any classified, confidential, sensitive, or third-party    information, or personal information about others.</li></ul></td><td class="alignTop"><ul><li>Adjust    volume settings to vibrate or low while at work;</li><li>Avoid    bringing a personal device into a work-related meeting; and</li><li>Minimize    the use of personal devices at work (e.g., by taking personal calls on    scheduled breaks or at lunch).</li></ul></td></tr></table></section></appendix><appendix anchor="G" title="Appendix G: Sample Notifications"><p>This appendix provides examples of different types of  notifications that could be used to inform authorized individuals of the  requirements of the <em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em> (the Policy). </p><p>The notifications include alerts about monitoring  practices or user acknowledgement of the terms and conditions of the use of  Government of Canada networks and devices, including the use of Web 2.0  tools and services. Some of the examples below could be displayed daily upon  initial account sign-in or at scheduled intervals, or presented to new  employees during orientation, depending on departmental circumstances and  needs.</p><section anchor="G.1" title="1. Employees Network Sign-On Notification"><p>[This notification can be displayed on a regular basis when  employees sign on to the network. A best practice is to display the  notification on a daily basis.]</p><p><em>Access to this system  is restricted to authorized individuals only.</em></p><p><em>[Department name]  reserves the right to monitor all electronic resources and subsequently record  all forms of communication and transmission for work-related purposes to ensure  proper network performance and security, protection of government assets,  optimal use of network resources and compliance with relevant legislation and  policies. Monitoring to gather information to investigate and resolve suspected  cases of unacceptable use may occur at any time without further notification.</em></p><p><em>All blocking and  monitoring will be done in compliance with the Privacy Act and the Canadian  Charter of Rights and Freedoms.</em></p><p><em>The Policy on  Acceptable Network and Device Use is available on the Treasury Board of Canada  Secretariat website.</em></p></section><section anchor="G.2" title="2. Employee Reminder Notice about the Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use"><p>[This notification requires authorized individuals to acknowledge and accept that they have read and understood the Policy. Notification and acknowledgement could be monthly or quarterly to ensure that the expectations of acceptable use, the monitoring practices of the department, and the consequences of unacceptable use are communicated and acknowledged. The notification may be used in its entirety or in part, depending on departmental needs and strategy.]</p><h4><em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use</em></h4><p><em>I have read the  Policy and acknowledge that:</em></p><ul><li><em>I will use  departmental networks and devices for activities related to my official and  professional duties in compliance with the Policy;</em></li><li><em>I will  abide by the expectations of acceptable use of networks, devices, and Web 2.0  tools and services outlined in the Policy, the Values and Ethics Code for the  Public Sector and all other related Treasury Board policies and departmental  policies and code of conduct;</em></li><li><em>I am aware  that employee activities on Government of Canada networks and devices are  monitored for the purposes of assessing system performance, protecting  government assets and ensuring compliance with Treasury Board and departmental  policies and codes of conduct;</em></li><li><em>I  understand that special monitoring of departmental networks and devices to  investigate and resolve suspected cases of unacceptable use may be conducted  without notice; </em></li><li><em>I have  read the Policy and acknowledge that:</em><ul><li><em>If I  choose to use the network for limited personal use and store personal  information on the network or devices, it will be at my own risk; and</em></li><li><em>I  understand that all information that is transmitted and stored on departmental  electronic systems may be subject to public access requests under the Access to  Information Act and the Privacy Act; and</em></li></ul></li><li><em>I  understand that unacceptable use of electronic networks, devices and Web 2.0  tools and services can have employment consequences up to, and including,  termination.</em></li></ul></section><section anchor="G.3" title="3. Acknowledgement of Receipt and Understanding of the Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use"><p>[Another form of acknowledgement and understanding of  the Policy is through a form that could be included as part of a new employee  orientation package or when granting the use of Government of Canada networks  and devices. </p><p>This form may be useful to managers to help generate  awareness about the acceptable use of electronic networks, devices and Web 2.0  tools and services to authorized individuals who are new to the department.  Presenting the form during orientation sessions can confirm that the authorized  individual has received, read and understood the Policy. It is another potential  measure to ensure that the individual is aware of the expectations of  acceptable use, the departmental monitoring practices and the consequences of  unacceptable use.]</p><p><em>I [insert name] acknowledge that:</em></p><ol><li><em>I have been informed of the requirements of  the </em>Policy on Acceptable Network and Device Use<em> (the Policy);</em></li><li><em>I understand the terms of use of networks,  devices, and Web 2.0 tools and services;</em></li><li><em>I have been made aware of the expectations  of acceptable use and I agree to abide by them;</em></li><li><em>I realize that failure to comply can have  employment consequences up to, and including, termination;</em></li><li><em>I understand that all information that is  transmitted and stored on the departmental electronic systems may be subject to  public access requests under the </em>Access to Information Act<em> and the </em>Privacy Act<em>; </em></li><li><em>[Department name] reserves the right to gain  access to the systems and its contents to conduct routine and special  monitoring processes for acceptable use; and</em></li><li><em>I have been informed  of the procedures to follow when reporting suspected instances of unacceptable  use and who to contact if I have any further questions about the acceptable use  of networks and devices. </em></li></ol><div class="alignLeft"><table border="0" cellspacing="1" cellpadding="3" class="width30"><tr class="alignLeft"><td scope="row"><em>Name:</em></td><td scope="col"><em>Date:</em></td></tr><tr class="alignLeft"><td scope="row"><em>Supervisor:</em></td><td><em>Date:</em></td></tr><tr class="alignLeft"><td scope="row"><em>Witness:</em></td><td><em>Date:</em></td></tr></table></div></section></appendix></appendices><footnotes><footnote anchor="ftn1" reference="ftnref1" title="1">Under Section  6.2 of the Policy, for departments  that receive their network services from Shared Services Canada (<abbr title="Shared Services Canada">SSC</abbr>), the deputy  head of Shared Services Canada is responsible for managing tools to support  monitoring. <abbr title="Shared Services Canada">SSC</abbr> is also responsible for providing reports about the use of Government  of Canada electronic networks and devices, and Web 2.0 tools and services to  assist deputy heads in the identification, investigation and implementation of  corrective action on issues that arise regarding unacceptable use.</footnote></footnotes></doc>