<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?><doc title="Appendix I: Interim Standard on Enterprise Resource Planning Solutions" documentID="25687" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="Appendix I" title="Interim Standard on Enterprise Resource Planning Solutions"><chapter anchor="I.1" title="Effective Date"><clauses><clause anchor="I.1.1">This standard takes effect on December 6, 2021. </clause><clause anchor="I.1.2">This standard replaces the following Treasury  Board policy instrument:
<ul><li>Standard on Enterprise Resource Planning Systems  (2012-05-01)</li></ul></clause><clause anchor="I.1.3">This standard provides details on the  requirements set out in section 4.4.1.1 of the Policy on Service and Digital  and section 4.4.3.3 of the Directive on Service and Digital.</clause><clause anchor="I.1.4">This standard must be read in conjunction with  the Policy on Financial Management, the Policy on People Management, and the  Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="I.2" title="Standards"><clauses><clause anchor="I.2.1">ERP solutions will have a user experience that  includes end-to-end business processes supporting back-office functions. </clause><clause anchor="I.2.2">ERP solutions enabling common business practices  and requirements will be offered in clusters to organizations when appropriate  and possible.</clause><clause anchor="I.2.3">ERP solutions will be vertically integrated and  horizontally interoperable, across the enterprise, to the extent possible.</clause><clause anchor="I.2.4">Institutions must select from a set of  pre-approved ERP solutions, that will be developed and maintained by the CIO of  Canada, Comptroller General (CG), and the Chief Human Resources Officer (CHRO),  in consultation with institutions and users, to ensure the solution meets their  respective needs.</clause><clause anchor="I.2.5">ERP solutions will have limited customization. Requests  for exceptions and customizations must be presented to the Government of Canada  Enterprise Architecture Review Board and supported by the business owner prior  to seeking approval from the CIO of Canada. </clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="I.3" title="Responsibilities"><clauses><clause anchor="I.3.1">In consultation with key stakeholders, the  Office of the Comptroller General is responsible for oversight of enterprise  resource planning solutions in the areas of institutional finance; procurement;  real property; asset and materiel management; grants and contributions;  portfolio, investment, and project management; budgeting, forecasting, and  planning; and treasury and banking; as well as the corresponding business  capabilities, information, and data models. </clause><clause anchor="I.3.2">In consultation with key stakeholders, the  Office of the Chief Human Resources Officer is responsible for oversight of  enterprise resource planning solutions in the areas of institutional people  management, as well as the corresponding business capabilities, information,  and data models.</clause></clauses></chapter></chapter></chapters></doc>