<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Guidelines on Second Official Language Training" documentID="32788" versionID="9" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><chapters><chapter anchor="1" title="About these guidelines"><clauses><clause anchor="1.1">These  guidelines provide advice and guidance on second official language training  (SOLT) within the Government of Canada in the context of relevant policies and  legislation. </clause><clause anchor="1.2">These  guidelines support the <em>Official Languages Act</em> (OLA) and key elements in the  Government of Canada’s official languages reform document <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/corporate/publications/general-publications/equality-official-languages.html">English and French: Towards a  substantive equality of official languages in Canada</a>. </clause><clause anchor="1.3">These guidelines  are primarily intended for HR professionals as well as managers and supervisors  (hereafter referred to simply as managers) in departments that are subject to the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for  People Management</em></a>.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="2" title="Context"><clauses><clause anchor="2.1">The OLA defines the role of the President of the Treasury  Board and the responsibilities and duties of the Treasury Board of Canada in  relation to official languages. Treasury Board’s responsibilities include guiding  and coordinating policies and programs for the following parts of the OLA: 

    <ul><li>communications  with and services to the public</li><li>language  of work in federal institutions</li><li>the  equitable participation of English-speaking and French-speaking Canadians in government  institutions</li><li>the taking  of positive measures to implement the Government of Canada’s commitments to  enhancing the vitality of the English and French linguistic minority  communities, fostering the full recognition and use of both official languages  in Canadian society, protecting and promoting French, and advancing learning in  the minority official language; and</li><li>the taking  of measures to promote, when negotiating agreements with the provincial and  territorial governments, including funding agreements, that may contribute to  the implementation of the same commitments, the inclusion of linguistic  clauses.</li></ul></clause><clause anchor="2.2">The implementation  of the OLA requires institutions to ensure that they have the bilingual  capacity to serve and communicate with Canadians and employees in both official  languages. Senior management plays a leadership role in maintaining the  bilingual capacity within their institutions. As specified in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26160"><em>Policy on Official Languages</em></a>, a key element in achieving this is investing  in the language training and development of employees.</clause><clause anchor="2.3">These guidelines support requirements found in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32621"><em>Policy on People Management</em></a> and in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for People Management</em></a>.</clause></clauses></chapter><chapter anchor="3" title="Guidelines"><p>The  following guidelines are intended to support institutions in providing equitable  access to SOLT to employees who seek to develop or maintain their second  official language skills. </p><clauses><clause anchor="3.1"><strong>Establishing  a culture of bilingualism</strong><clauses><clause anchor="3.1.1">Under the OLA,  every federal institution has the duty to ensure that, in bilingual regions,  work environments are conducive to the effective use of both official  languages. In addition, the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official  Languages for People Management</em></a> indicates that  institutions are responsible for offering language training to employees (in  both bilingual and unilingual regions) who want to develop their  second-language skills for career development purposes. To achieve this, institutions  are strongly encouraged to support their employees in acquiring and maintaining  their second official language skills.</clause><clause anchor="3.1.2">Regardless of the linguistic identification of a position, it  is recommended that a discussion regarding the acquisition  and/or maintenance of second official language skills take place at least once  a year as part of an employee’s career and talent management discussions. It is  strongly encouraged that this discussion starts at the beginning of an  employee’s career and continues throughout their career.</clause><clause anchor="3.1.3">SOLT is a shared  responsibility of both the manager and the employee. </clause><clause anchor="3.1.4"><p>Under the OLA, federal  institutions are required to create and maintain a work environment that allows  employees to use the official language of their choice in bilingual  regions for both oral and written communication purposes.</p><p>Managers  play a key role in implementing this obligation and can therefore take the  following steps to ensure compliance: </p><ul><li>support and  promote the use, maintenance and enhancement of an employee’s second official  language in an environment of linguistic security, which is when a person feels  confident and at ease when using a language. Linguistic security can apply to  first- and second-language speakers. Here it is used primarily to refer to  second official language speakers</li><li>consult with the  person responsible for SOLT within their institution to explore available training  options</li><li>be broadly  familiar with various types of formal and informal language training so that  they can advise and direct employees to the appropriate tools and resource  persons</li><li>discuss the  development of second official language skills or maintenance needs on a  regular basis as well as part of performance and talent management discussions</li><li>review an  employee’s request to pursue informal language training, taking into  consideration an employee’s learning path, workload and schedule</li><li>review an employee’s  request for formal SOLT, taking into account considerations listed in section 3.4  when determining an employee’s SOLT </li></ul></clause><clause anchor="3.1.5"><p>With  support from management, employees are expected to use and maintain the second  official language skills required by the position.</p><p>Employees  and managers are also encouraged to:</p><ul><li>discuss SOLT  needs for career progression</li><li>establish  an agreement outlining respective responsibilities</li><li>include  the chosen formal or informal training in the learning and development plan </li></ul></clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="3.2"><strong>Selecting the type of SOLT that best  meets employee needs</strong><p>While selecting  the type of SOLT that best meets an employee’s needs, it is important to  consider both formal and informal learning methods. Both provide benefits and are  complementary. However, a focus on one method may be better suited for a given  employee’s learning style or preference, while other employees may use a  variety of methods. Institutions are encouraged to offer a variety of second  official language training options. </p><clauses><clause anchor="3.2.1"><strong>Informal SOLT</strong><clauses><clause anchor="3.2.1.1">Informal SOLT typically follows a more flexible  approach and usually takes place outside of a conventional learning setting. The  learning is less structured, more spontaneous and conveniently integrated into  daily or weekly routines. It includes the use of self-directed learning tools  which are usually free or available at a minimal cost.  </clause><clause anchor="3.2.1.2">This  type of training is recommended as a first step in any language learning  journey to allow for the acquisition of basic proficiency, while improving the  chance for success in subsequent formal training. </clause><clause anchor="3.2.1.3">Informal  SOLT may be provided to employees who want to acquire, maintain or improve their  second official language skills.</clause><clause anchor="3.2.1.4">Employees  are encouraged to choose the SOLT activities that are of interest to them and  enter their learning needs in their learning and development plan.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="3.2.2"><strong>Formal  SOLT</strong><clauses><clause anchor="3.2.2.1"><p>Formal  SOLT follows a more structured approach and often, but not exclusively, takes  place in a classroom setting. </p><p>Formal SOLT usually takes place during normal working hours and the  primary format is group training.</p><p>A language training activity,  whether virtual, in-person or hybrid, is considered formal when:</p><ul><li>it is provided by an in-house or third-party language  training service provider that is included in standing offers by the  institution or Public Services and  Procurement Canada (PSPC), or by another external service provider</li><li>it includes clear objectives,  learning outcomes and course length</li><li>it is established  based on the number of hours of training required and financial resources allocated</li></ul><p class="mrgn-tp-sm">Examples of types of formal SOLT that may be offered in an institution  are: </p><ul><li>annual user subscription  through a standing offer for an online self-study platform accompanied by  tutoring</li><li>part-time language training</li><li>full-time language  training</li><li>group language  training</li><li>individual language  training</li></ul><p class="mrgn-tp-sm">As indication only, a beginner learner will  need an average of 72 weeks to reach level C. The following represents an  average number of full-time SOLT weeks needed to reach each language  proficiency level, based on 35 hours/week (this does not apply to  part-time SOLT): </p><ul><li>48 weeks for  level B </li><li>24 additional weeks  for level C</li></ul><p class="mrgn-tp-sm">Note that hours may vary depending on the type of  training and needs. </p></clause><clause anchor="3.2.2.2">Before  considering formal SOLT, it is recommended that employees have achieved basic proficiency  in their second official language.</clause><clause anchor="3.2.2.3">Formal  SOLT should be provided to employees primarily to improve their second official  language skills.</clause></clauses></clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="3.3"><strong>Respecting the  duty to accommodate in SOLT</strong><clauses><clause anchor="3.3.1">Under the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32621"><em>Policy  on People Management</em></a>, deputy heads are responsible for creating and  maintaining a respectful, inclusive and fair workplace. </clause><clause anchor="3.3.2">The <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32634"><em>Directive on  the Duty to Accommodate</em></a> outlines the roles of managers and employees in  the accommodation process and includes <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32634#appA">Mandatory  Procedures</a>. The <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/government/publicservice/wellness-inclusion-diversity-public-service/diversity-inclusion-public-service/working-government-canada-duty-accommodate-right-non-discrimination/duty-accommodate-general-process-managers.html">Duty to Accommodate: A General Process for  Managers </a> outlines a step-by-step process to  accommodation and promotes a proactive, collaborative and informal approach. It  also includes the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/government/publicservice/wellness-inclusion-diversity-public-service/diversity-inclusion-public-service/accessibility-public-service/government-canada-workplace-accessibility-passport/gc-workplace-accessibility-passport-guidance-managers.html">Government  of Canada Workplace Accessibility Passport Guidance for Managers</a>. The Government  of Canada Workplace Accessibility Passport is a tool that can facilitate the  conversation between managers and employees about workplace barriers and  document agreed-upon solutions to support the employee’s success in meeting the  SOLT goals.</clause><clause anchor="3.3.3">The duty to accommodate applies wherever the  employee is performing work, whether on a temporary or permanent basis, which  includes SOLT. </clause><clause anchor="3.3.4"> Under the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32634"><em>Directive on  the Duty to Accommodate</em></a>, managers are responsible for
        <ul><li>proactively discussing  potential accommodation needs with their employees</li><li>ensuring that accommodation  requests are addressed in a timely manner</li><li>regularly following up with the  employee</li><li>modifying the accommodation as  needed and when an employee’s circumstances change </li></ul></clause><clause anchor="3.3.5">Managers  may seek guidance from their institution’s relevant  functional specialists on accommodation or exceptional staffing situations  when bilingual positions are staffed non-imperatively, according to the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SI-2005-118/page-1.html"><em>Public  Service Official Languages Exclusion Approval Order</em></a> and <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-2005-347/page-1.html">Public  Service Official Languages Appointment Regulations</a>.</clause><clause anchor="3.3.6">In accordance with the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32634"><em>Directive on the Duty to  Accommodate</em></a>, employees are responsible for informing their  manager if they require accommodation measures. Accommodation measures are put  in place to support employees’ full participation, including when participating  in SOLT.</clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="3.4"><strong>Planning  access to SOLT</strong><p>Institutions are strongly encouraged to:</p><clauses><clause anchor="3.4.1">Integrate SOLT in their organizational human resources plan to maintain  and enhance bilingual capacity in the public service.</clause><clause anchor="3.4.2"><p>Consider  taking the following into account when determining access  to SOLT; the OLA, the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/e-5.401/FullText.html"><em>Employment Equity Act</em></a>, <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-0.6/"><em>Accessible Canada Act</em></a> and the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/privy-council/corporate/clerk/call-to-action-anti-racism-equity-inclusion-federal-public-service.html">Clerk's Call to Action on  Anti-Racism, Equity, and Inclusion in the Federal Public Service</a>, as well as human resources management and  stewardship of public funds.</p><p>Respecting legislative and policy requirements by ensuring SOLT for:</p><ul><li>employees  who have been appointed to a non-imperative bilingual position after having  made an agreement to meet the official language proficiency requirements of  positions within two years in accordance with the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/public-service-commission/services/public-service-hiring-guides/public-service-official-languages-exclusion-approval-order.html"><em>Public Service Official Languages  Exclusion Approval Order</em></a></li><li>employees  whose position has become bilingual, or the language profile has been raised as  a result of a review and re-identification process in accordance with the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for  People Management</em></a> and the <a href="https://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d1/en"><em>Bilingualism Bonus Directive</em></a>.</li></ul><p class="mrgn-tp-sm">Respecting the employer’s obligations by offering SOLT to:</p><ul><li>eliminate  employment barriers for individuals in the designated groups under the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/e-5.401/FullText.html"><em>Employment Equity Act</em></a>, keeping in mind the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/employment-social-development/news/2023/12/minister-oregan-receives-task-force-report-on-employment-equity-act-modernization.html">government’s initial commitments to  modernize this Act</a> includes creating two new designated groups: Black people and 2SLGBTQI+ people;</li><li>take  concrete action to ensure the full representation of members of the designated  groups.</li></ul></clause><clause anchor="3.4.3">Ensuring  an equitable and balanced approach when planning and prioritizing language  training to maximize access for a wide variety of employees by taking into  account the following elements:
      <ul><li>Equity and  inclusion – To ensure a fair representation of designated groups enrolled in  SOLT. The management of data  should be done in accordance with the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/p-21/FullText.html"><em>Privacy  Act</em></a> and related Treasury Board policy suite. </li><li>Career  development – To integrate SOLT early in an employee’s career </li><li>Talent management and succession planning – To consider the future overall  bilingual capacity of the institution and the need to develop the bilingual  capacity of feeder groups </li></ul><p class="mrgn-tp-sm">Before making a decision to provide training, institutions should consider  the following factors:</p><ul><li>Cost – Assess  and plan for language training costs, including the cost associated with  replacing the employee</li><li>Operational  impact – Determine whether there is organizational capacity to absorb the employee’s  workload while they are on language training</li><li>Learner’s  efforts – Consider the willingness and initiatives taken by employees to learn  a second language</li><li>Types of  training – Consider the types of SOLT that would best meet the diverse learning  needs of employees and recognize and assess the need for accommodation, if  required</li></ul></clause></clauses></clause><clause anchor="3.5"><strong>Collecting  and tracking language training data </strong><clauses><clause anchor="3.5.1">Under  section 6.5.3 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for  People Management</em></a>,  heads of human resources are responsible for keeping files and information  systems current to provide reports to Office of the Chief Human Resources  Officer upon request, including the OL annual review exercise.</clause><clause anchor="3.5.2">Data contributes to effectively designing and  implementing the institution’s language training program to better meet the  needs of learners. </clause><clause anchor="3.5.3">To obtain meaningful information about the state of language training  within institutions, it is encouraged to track language training data. The management of  data should be done in accordance with the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/p-21/FullText.html"><em>Privacy Act</em></a> and related Treasury Board policy suite.
		<p>A sample of formal SOLT data is provided here for institutions. It is recommended that this  data be readily available for monitoring purposes. Note - This sample only  represents current employment equity groups, as per the <em>Employment Equity  Act</em>. This sample will be updated once the Act and the relevant systems have  been revised.</p></clause></clauses></clause></clauses><div class="table-responsive small"><div class="small"><div class="small"><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><tr><th scope="row" class="active">Population code </th><td class="active"> </td><td colspan="9"> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="active">Institution title </th><td class="active"> </td><td colspan="9"> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="active">Fiscal year </th><td class="active"> </td><td colspan="9"> </td></tr><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Sample of formal SOLT data</th><th scope="col">Total number </th><th scope="colgroup" colspan="4">Reasons for SOLT </th><th scope="col">% learners from the designated EE groups  </th><th scope="col">% of learners 
      identifying as a member of visible minority </th><th scope="col">% of learners identifying as a person with disabilities </th><th scope="col">% of learners identifying as an indigenous person </th><th scope="col">% of learners identifying as a woman </th></tr><tr class="active"><td colspan="2"></td><th scope="col">mandatory </th><th scope="col">career management </th><th scope="col">talent management </th><th scope="col">other </th><td colspan="5"></td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in French part-time group SOLT </th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in French part-time individual SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in French full-time group SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in French full-time individual SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in English part-time group SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in English part-time individual SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in English full-time group SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Number of persons enrolled in English full-time individual SOLT</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Annual user subscriptions for French online self-study platforms</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Annual user subscriptions for English online self-study platforms</th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="active">Total amount spent on formal SOLT </th><td> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td class="active"> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td><td> </td></tr></table></div></div></div></chapter><chapter anchor="4" title="References"><h3><strong>Relevant  legislation</strong></h3><ul><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/page-12.html"><em>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/"><em>Official Languages Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-33.01/"><em>Public Service Employment Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-2005-347/index.html"><em>Public Service Official Languages Appointment  Regulations</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SI-2005-118/index.html"><em>Public Service Official Languages Exclusion Approval  Order</em></a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-0.6/"><em>Accessible Canada Act</em></a></li></ul><h3><strong>Treasury  Board policy instruments</strong></h3><ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32621"><em>Policy on People Management</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26160"><em>Policy on Official Languages</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=26168"><em>Directive on Official Languages for People Management</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/staffing/qualification-standards/relation-official-languages.html"><em>Qualification Standards in Relation to Official  Languages</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32634"><em>Directive  on the Duty to Accommodate</em></a></li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="5" title="Enquiries"><clauses><clause anchor="5.1">For  questions, contact <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html#enquiries">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>.
  </clause></clauses></chapter></chapters></doc>