<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Guideline on the Directive on Transfer Payments" documentID="19421" versionID="8" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="G:\web\xml\pols\PolicySchema-renamed.xsd">
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="1" title="1. Introduction">
      <p>Transfer payments are one of the government’s
key instruments in furthering its broad policy objectives and
priorities. They are monetary payments, or transfers
of goods, services, or assets to third parties, including Crown corporations, made
by the Government of Canada on the basis of appropriations. These
payments do not result in the acquisition by the Government of
Canada of any goods, services, or assets.</p>
      <p>Transfer payments represent a large part of the
Government of Canada’s spending and support tangible results that touch the
lives of Canadians and others every day in all sectors of society.</p>
      <p>
        The 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13525">
          <em>Policy
on Transfer Payments</em>
        </a>
         (Policy) sets out broad roles and responsibilities
for Treasury Board, the President of the Treasury Board, the Secretary of the
Treasury Board, ministers and deputy heads in the design, delivery, and
management of transfer payment programs.
      </p>
      <p>
        The 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">
          <em>Directive on Transfer Payments</em>
        </a>
         (Directive) supports the objectives of the Policy
by establishing mandatory operational requirements for departmental managers
who have been assigned responsibilities for the management of transfer payment
programs and transfer payments. The distribution of these responsibilities
among managers in any department is for departmental management to determine. 
      </p>
      <p>Both the Policy and Directive came into effect on October 1, 2008.</p>
      <p>
        This guideline focuses on the 
        <em>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
        </em>
         by providing context, interpretation and more detailed
explanation of key requirements and specific topics. It is designed to support departmental
managers in their understanding and implementation of the Directive by providing
context and explanation of its key requirements. 
      </p>
      <p>Where appropriate, the guideline links requirements of
the Directive to the Policy to explain their intent. It brings together related
requirements to provide easier understanding of particular elements. It
highlights areas where careful interpretation is required and, by providing
background and context, facilitates comprehension.</p>
      <p>Readers will benefit most from the guideline if they
have read both the Directive and the Policy and are familiar with the
definitions in these documents.</p>
      <p>
        The guideline is one of a number of guidelines that replace
the 
        <em>Guide on Grants, Contributions and Other Transfer Payments</em>
         that accompanied
the former 
        <em>Policy on Transfer Payments</em>
         dated June 1, 2000. This version of the guideline incorporates updates effective April 1, 2022: to be consistent with Policy and provide context on timelines.
      </p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="2" title="2. Design of transfer payment programs">
      <p>
        The 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
         requires departmental managers to assess
a set of core design elements when they are engaged in the design of a new
transfer payment program or the redesign of an existing program (
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appB">Appendix
B of the Directive</a>
        ). Addressing these elements will ensure that strategic
design issues are considered, that key aspects of the policy are taken into
account at the design stage (harmonization, standardization, engagement of
stakeholders, administrative requirements on recipients, etc.), and that a sound framework
for the management, monitoring, and eventual evaluation of the program is
developed. 
      </p>
      <p>The Directive requires that departmental managers
document evidence of their assessment of the core design elements. This
documentation will support the development or amendment of terms and conditions
for the transfer payment program and any Treasury Board submission that may be
required for the approval of such terms and conditions. While there is no
requirement in the Policy or Directive that departments are to provide this
documentation to the Treasury Board Secretariat, some parts may be well suited
to respond to requests from program analysts reviewing Treasury Board
submissions. There are key elements of the core design documentation that are
important to maintain evergreen throughout the life of the transfer payment
program, e.g., risk analysis and risk management measures at the program level,
and results. </p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="3" title="3. Terms and conditions">
      <section anchor="3.1" title="3.1 Approval of terms and conditions">
        <p>
          The expression “terms and conditions” is given a
  specific meaning in the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13525">Policy on Transfer Payments</a>
           and 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
          . It refers to a document,
  approved by Treasury Board or a minister, that sets out the parameters under
  which transfer payments may be made for a given transfer payment program.
        </p>
        <p>Approved terms and conditions are
  normally a precondition for making a transfer payment. However, when a program
  of transfer payments is authorized by a statute or statutory instrument that sets
  out the parameters under which payments are to be made, terms and conditions within
  the meaning of the policy may not be necessary. Nevertheless, it is not
  uncommon in such cases for departments to amplify statutory rules with further
  terms and conditions approved by Treasury Board.</p>
        <p>Also where the approved estimates or
  a statute provide authority for a one-time transfer payment to a named
  recipient, it may not be necessary to develop terms and conditions within the
  meaning of the policy. The funding agreement may reflect all appropriate
  conditions. On the other hand, where it is anticipated that authority will be
  sought in the estimates on an annual basis to make payments to the same named
  recipient, then approved terms and conditions would normally be necessary.</p>
        <p>The Directive requires that the Treasury
  Board Secretariat is to be consulted in advance in all cases when it is
  proposed to make transfer payments without terms and conditions. </p>
        <p>Departmental managers are to ensure
  that terms and conditions address the elements in the appropriate appendices to
	  the Directive; i.e., Appendices:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appD">Appendix D of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Terms and Conditions for Grants</a>
            ,
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appE">Appendix E of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Terms and Conditions for Contributions</a>
            ,
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appI">Appendix I of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Transfer Payments to Other Orders of Government</a>
            ,
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appJ">Appendix J of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Transfer Payments to Foreign Recipients</a>
            ,
  and 
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appK">Appendix K of the Directive on Transfer Payments - Transfer Payments to Indigenous Recipients</a>
            .
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>These appendices distinguish between elements that are to be addressed in all
  terms and conditions and those that are to be addressed only where they are
  relevant. Where these latter elements are relevant, they are to be addressed;
  they are not discretionary. For example, if Cabinet has set a two-year life for
  a transfer payment program, the terms and conditions are to reflect this sunset
  requirement.</p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="3.2" title="3.2 Amendments to elements of terms and conditions">
        <p>From time to time, terms and conditions may require amendments. Depending on the type of amendment, either Treasury Board or ministerial approval will be required. 	 </p>
        <h4>3.2.1 Amendments: Treasury Board approval</h4>
        <p>The Policy articulates that Treasury Board approval is required to amend the following elements of terms and conditions:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>the program objectives;</li>
          <li>the repayment of a repayable contribution; and</li>
          <li>up-front multi-year funding. </li>
        </ul>
        <h4>3.2.2 Amendments: Ministerial approval following consultation with the Treasury Board Secretariat</h4>
        <p>Ministers are responsible for approving amendments to the following elements of terms and conditions:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>the eligible activities, initiatives or projects;</li>
          <li>the class of eligible recipients; </li>
          <li>the maximum amount payable to a recipient;</li>
          <li>the stacking limit; and</li>
          <li>amendments that give effect to a Cabinet decision or direction.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>The following process has been established:</p>
        <ol class="upper-alpha">
          <li>
            <strong>Consulting with the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat and the Privy Council Office</strong>
            <p>The department is required to consult with and obtain concurrence from the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat that proposed changes constitute an amendment 			under section 5.3.4 of the Policy prior to the minister’s approval of the amendments.</p>
            <p>When necessary, Secretariat officials will consult with officials of the Privy Council Office (PCO) to confirm the validity of policy coverage. On occasion, 			departments may consult with officials of PCO directly. </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <strong>Letter to the President of the Treasury Board</strong>
            <p>Following approval of the amendments, the minister is required to inform the President of the Treasury Board by way of a letter within 30 days after 		exercising his or her authority. A hardcopy of the updated terms and conditions is to be attached to the letter. </p>
            <p>The letter to the President of the Treasury Board will require the signature of the minister and the deputy head to attest that the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat and the Privy Council Office, where necessary, were consulted regarding the proposed amendments to the terms and conditions.</p>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <p class="indent1">The following is a template of the Letter to Inform.</p>
        <div class="borderSimple indent2">
          <p>Date</p>
          <p>
            The Honourable 
            <em>(name of Minister)</em>
            <br/>
            
      President of the Treasury Board
            <br/>
            
      House of Commons
            <br/>
            
      Ottawa, Ontario
            <br/>
            
      K1A 0A6
          </p>
          <p>(Salutation) :</p>
          <p>
            I am writing to inform you that, under Section 5.3.4 of the 
            <em>Policy on Transfer Payments</em>
            , I have approved the following amendments to the terms and conditions of (
            <em>insert name of transfer payment program</em>
            ):
          </p>
          <p>
            (
            <strong>Examples</strong>
            )
            <br/>
            
			The class of eligible recipients has been expanded to include…
            <br/>
            
			The maximum amount payable has been increased to…
            <br/>
            
			The eligible activities, initiatives or projects have been expanded to include…
            <br/>
            
			The stacking limit has been modified to…
          </p>
          <p>
            <strong>Briefly explain the transfer payment program and the situation that has given rise to the need to amend a specific element(s) of the terms and conditions.</strong>
          </p>
          <p>
            In accordance with Section 5.4.11 of the 
            <em>Policy on Transfer Payments</em>
            , my departmental officials have consulted with the Secretary of the Treasury Board (and with the Privy Council Office, insert when applicable) to ensure that the approval of the amendments to the terms and conditions are within my authority. I confirm that the amendment(s) are consistent with the program’s policy coverage and that the terms and conditions are compliant with the 
            <em>Policy on Transfer Payments</em>
            .
          </p>
          <p>
            A copy of the updated terms and conditions for the (
            <em>name of transfer payment program</em>
            ) transfer payment program is attached for your information.
          </p>
          <p>
            <span class="indent5"> Minister : _________________________________</span>
          </p>
          <p>
            <span class="indent5">Deputy Head : _____________________________</span>
          </p>
          <p>
                   
		c.c.: 	Secretary of the Treasury Board
            <br/>
            
				Assistant Comptroller General, Financial Management Sector
            <br/>
            
				Assistant Secretary (
            <em>as appropriate</em>
            ), Program Sector (
            <em>insert name of Program Sector</em>
            ) 
          </p>
        </div>
        <h4>3.2.3 Minor amendments: Ministerial or deputy head approval</h4>
        <p>Minor amendments, i.e. amendments to any elements of terms and conditions other than those that require Treasury Board approval or consultation and concurrence with the Secretary of the Treasury Board, may be approved by ministers or approval may be delegated to deputy heads at the discretion of the minister.</p>
        <p>Minor amendments include amendments that are, in respect of any of the elements listed in paragraphs 3.2.1 and 3.2.2, of a technical nature made solely for the purpose of correcting errors of wording or adding clarity.</p>
        <h4>3.2.4 The following table summarizes the approvals required for amendments to terms and conditions</h4>
        <table class="table table-bordered table-condensed">
          <thead>
            <tr class="active">
              <th id="C0" scope="col">
                <strong>Element of Terms and Conditions</strong>
              </th>
              <th id="C1" scope="col">
                <strong>Deputy Head</strong>
              </th>
              <th id="C2" scope="col">
                <strong>Minister</strong>
              </th>
              <th id="C3" scope="col">
                <strong>Treasury Board</strong>
              </th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tfoot>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="4">
                <div class="wb-fnote">
                  <h5 id="table1-fn" class="wb-inv">Table 1 Notes</h5>
                  <dl>
                    <dt>Table 1 Note 1</dt>
                    <dd id="table1-fn1">
                      <p>Authority to approve.</p>
                      <p class="fn-rtn">
                        <a href="#table1-fn1a-rf">
                          <span class="wb-inv">Return to table 1 note </span>
                          *
                          <span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span>
                        </a>
                      </p>
                    </dd>
                    <dt>Table 1 Note 2</dt>
                    <dd id="table1-fn2">
                      <p>Consultation with the Secretariat required before exercising authority to approve.</p>
                      <p class="fn-rtn">
                        <a href="#table1-fn2a-rf">
                          <span class="wb-inv">Return to table 1 note </span>
                          **
                          <span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span>
                        </a>
                      </p>
                    </dd>
                    <dt>Table 1 Note 3</dt>
                    <dd id="table1-fn3">
                      <p>Authority to approve when delegated by the minister.</p>
                      <p class="fn-rtn">
                        <a href="#table1-fn3a-rf">
                          <span class="wb-inv">Return to table 1 note </span>
                          ***
                          <span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span>
                        </a>
                      </p>
                    </dd>
                  </dl>
                </div>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tfoot>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Program objectives</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1a-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Repayment of a repayable contribution</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1b-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Upfront multi-year funding</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1c-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Eligible activities, initiatives or projects</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Consultation with the Secretariat required before exercising authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn2a-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    **
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1d-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Class of eligible recipients</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Consultation with the Secretariat required before exercising authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn2b-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    **
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1e-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Maximum amount payable to a recipient</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Consultation with the Secretariat required before exercising authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn2c-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    **
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1f-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Stacking limit</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Consultation with the Secretariat required before exercising authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn2d-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    **
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1g-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Amendments that give effect to a Cabinet decision or direction</td>
              <td class="text-center">
                <abbr title="Not applicable">N/A</abbr>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Consultation with the Secretariat required before exercising authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn2e-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn2">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    **
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1h-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Amendments to any other element of terms and conditions other than those listed above</td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C1">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve when delegated by the minister">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn3a-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn3">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    ***
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1i-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1j-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td headers="C0">Amendments, that are, in respect of any of the elements listed above, of a technical nature made solely for the purpose of correcting errors of wording or adding clarity to such elements</td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C1">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve when delegated by the minister">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn3b-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn3">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    ***
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C2">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1k-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
              <td class="text-center" headers="C3">
                <abbr title="Authority to approve">A</abbr>
                <sup id="table1-fn1l-rf">
                  <a class="fn-lnk" href="#table1-fn1">
                    <span class="wb-inv">table 1 note </span>
                    *
                  </a>
                </sup>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <h4>3.2.5 Approval of one-time exemptions and one-time exceptions</h4>
        <p>
          One-time exemptions to the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13525">
            <em>Policy on Transfer Payments</em>
          </a>
           and one-time exceptions to the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">
            <em>Directive on Transfer Payments</em>
          </a>
          , excluding those provided for under sections 5.3.7 and 5.3.8 of the Policy, require Treasury Board approval. In certain cases, as determined through consultation with the Secretariat, the President may approve exceptions to the Directive on Transfer Payments as provided for under section 3.8 of the Policy on Transfer Payments.
        </p>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="4" title="4. Funding levels">
      <p>
        The 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
         establishes a general requirement that
the level of funding to be provided by way of a grant or contribution is to be at
the minimum level required to further the attainment of the objectives of the
transfer payment program and the results expected of the recipient. Key
decisions that influence the level of funding are made at the design stage. Terms
and conditions for a transfer payment program establish a maximum that may be
paid to any applicant; they also set out the method to be used in determining
the amount of a grant or the maximum amount of a contribution to an individual
recipient (e.g., 60% of eligible expenditures). The stacking limit establishes
a maximum level of total Canadian government funding that is to be permitted
for any activity, project, or initiative of a recipient. In addition, for some
transfer payment programs, the amounts may be influenced by international trade
agreements to which Canada has subscribed.
      </p>
      <p>The Directive also requires that the amount of a
proposed transfer payment is appropriate when other sources of funding
available to the recipient are taken into account. How this is addressed will
vary with the nature and design of a transfer payment program. For some
programs, such as those that permit a fixed payment to an eligible applicant,
other available sources of funding are not relevant (e.g., language
training in the context of immigration, ecoAUTO Rebate Program).
The general rule, however, is that the level of funding to be provided is to be
at the minimum level required to further the attainment of the objectives of
the transfer payment program and the results expected of the recipient; for
many programs this will mean that consideration of other sources of funding
available to the recipient (including a recipient’s own resources) is a significant
factor in determining the amount of the government’s funding commitment.</p>
      <p>The determination of the level of funding is an
important consideration in designing the information to be requested from
applicants seeking transfer payments. For a grant, the application information
needs to be sufficient to determine the amount of the grant to be awarded to
the recipient; for a contribution, it needs to be at least sufficient to
determine the maximum amount that may be paid, with the actual amount subject
to accounting for the eligible expenditures eventually incurred by a recipient
and funding obtained from other sources.</p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="5" title="5. Funding agreements">
      <p>
        The 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
         requires that a funding agreement is executed with each recipient before any payment is
made; this includes any instalment or advance payment. An exception to this is
for an assessed contribution to an international organization that may be paid without
a funding agreement when due and requested by an international organization,
provided it is in compliance with approved terms and conditions.
      </p>
      <p>Departmental managers responsible for preparing
funding agreements are to ensure that the provisions of the agreements are
consistent with approved terms and conditions of the transfer payment programs and
	that the elements in the relevant appendix to the Directive; i.e., Appendices:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appF">Appendix F of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Funding Agreement Provisions for Grants</a>
          ,
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-ENG.aspx?id=14208#appG">Appendix G of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Funding Agreement Provisions for Contributions</a>
          ,
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-ENG.aspx?id=14208#appH">Appendix H of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Funding Agreement Provisions for Up-Front Multi-Year Funding</a>
          ,
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appI">Appendix I of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Transfer Payments to Other Orders of Government</a>
          ,
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appJ">Appendix J of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Transfer Payments to Foreign Recipients</a>
          ,
and
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appK">Appendix K of the Directive on Transfer Payments – Transfer Payments to Indigenous Recipients</a>
          .
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>are addressed. Where there is conflict between approved terms and conditions
and the requirements of the Directive, the terms and conditions are to prevail.</p>
      <p>
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appF">Appendix F of the Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
        
and 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appG">Appendix G of the Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
        ,
which deal with funding agreements for grants and contributions, stress that
these elements are to be addressed in a manner that balances the department’s
accountability and control requirements with the level of risk specific to the
transfer payment program, the value of the funding, and the risk profile of the
recipient. This reflects a key principle of the policy, that the
administrative requirements on recipients should be proportionate to
the risk level. The expectation is that each funding agreement should be
tailored to the risk involved in making that transfer payment to the particular
recipient. This will require departments to have tools in place to assess these
risks in a systematic and consistent manner, and to determine, based on this
assessment, the administrative requirements that are appropriate. The
transitional considerations of the policy recognize that it may take some time
to deliver on this expectation; consequently, the policy requirement will apply
only to new and continued transfer payment programs approved after March 31, 2010. Early implementation by departments will be beneficial.
      </p>
      <p>While the appendices identify elements that are to be addressed
in funding agreements, the statements of these elements are not meant to be
draft or model clauses for agreements. It is important that departmental managers
develop the wording of agreements in conjunction with departmental legal
advisors: they may also be guided by their legal advisors on whether it is
necessary to address particular elements to protect the government’s interests,
and on whether further elements not identified in the appendices may be
required. </p>
      <section anchor="5.1" title="5.1 Multi-Year Funding Agreements">
        <p>Consistent with the objective of reducing the administrative requirements on both recipients and the department, the Directive asks that departmental managers look at whether a multi-year agreement would be appropriate when the activities to be undertaken to achieve the objectives of a transfer payment program, or a funding agreement, may involve a relationship with a recipient over a number of years. In such circumstances, a multi-year funding agreement may best reflect the commitment of both the department and the recipient. Similarly, when a recipient is to receive transfer payments from multiple transfer payment programs, the Directive asks departmental managers to look at whether the use of a single agreement might be practical for the department and beneficial to the recipient.</p>
        <p>Periodic reassessment of risk, particularly in multi-year agreements, may influence funding agreement terms and conditions, and may enable reduction in recipient administrative activity should risks be re-assessed and subsequently found to have decreased over time. It is important that risk assessment strategies are accurate, appropriate and remain current. To this end, departments should have a strategy in place for periodically reassessing the risk ratings associated with multi-year contribution agreements.</p>
        <p>Most funding agreements will be in the form of a single document. However, the Directive recognizes that, for grants involving low risks or low materiality, the use of application forms and exchanges of correspondence with recipients may be sufficient, so long as this documentation, taken together, reflects the necessary agreement elements.</p>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="6" title="6. Cash management">
      <p>
        The 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
         provides departmental managers with considerable discretion in their
cash management practices. This discretion is necessary to allow managers to
tailor cash management arrangements to the assessed level of risks of
individual transfer payments. 
      </p>
      <p>A general requirement of the Directive is that
payments to recipients are to be made in a timely, prudent, and efficient
manner that supports the achievement of objectives and recognizes the risks
involved. Prudence in
making payments requires that departmental managers have sufficient basis for
making payments and that generally payments are not made in advance of need.
Efficiency requires that payment requests can be processed quickly and that the
documentation sought in support of payments is only that which is necessary and
sufficient.</p>
      <p>Within this general requirement, the Directive
provides departmental managers with considerable latitude in making payments. The
rules for grants are simple. For a grant up to $250,000, departmental managers
have full discretion on whether to pay the grant in a lump sum or to pay it in
instalments. A grant over $250,000 is to be paid in instalments unless the full
amount is required in a single payment to meet the objectives of the grant.
When any grant is to be paid in instalments, departmental managers have the
discretion to determine the amounts and timing of the instalment payments,
which could be based on cash flow projections obtained from the recipient.</p>
      <p>
        The rules for contribution payments are a little more
complex. First, it is necessary to distinguish between progress payments and
final payments on the one hand and advance payments on the other. Progress
payments and final payments are made 
        <strong>after</strong>
         the performance of part or
all of the obligations of the contribution agreement. Advance payments are made 
        <strong>before</strong>
         those performance
obligations of the funding agreement that would justify payment of the
contribution have been met.
      </p>
      <p>Before progress payments or final payments of a
contribution can be made, evidence is required that the obligations of the
funding agreement have been partially or fully met. The most common basis for
such payments is the reimbursement of eligible expenditures. However, the Directive
clearly indicates that such payments may be based on one or a combination of the
following, specified in the funding agreement: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>achievement of predetermined performance expectations or
milestones;</li>
        <li>reimbursement of eligible expenditures; or</li>
        <li>a costing formula. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Progress payments based on specified performance
expectations or milestones, or on a costing formula, do not necessarily need to
be supported by evidence of eligible expenditures to that time. That said, a
final accounting of eligible expenditures is always required; whatever basis is
adopted for making progress payments, the total amount of contribution funding
paid to a recipient under a funding agreement is not to exceed the eligible
expenditures actually incurred by the recipient or such portion of these
expenditures as was to be funded under the agreement. </p>
      <p>Advance payments are made to provide cash flow to a
recipient where this is necessary and are to be provided only when they are
essential to the achievement of objectives. The decision on whether advance
payments are to be provided to any recipient will be based on an assessment made
at the time of entering into the funding agreement. </p>
      <p>Departments have the discretion to determine the
frequency and amounts of advance payments subject to the following:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>the funding agreement should clearly indicate that advance
payments may be made;</li>
        <li>advance payments are to be made based on a recipient’s cash flow
requirements. Consequently, a funding agreement should not normally specify
that fixed sums will be advanced on an established schedule. Further, advance
payments should not be made to a recipient while the recipient has an
unexpended balance of earlier advance payments in hand that is sufficient to
meet cash flow requirements;</li>
        <li>the total advance payments made in a fiscal year are not to
exceed a recipient’s estimated cash flow requirements with respect to the
federal government’s share of eligible expenditures for that fiscal year; departments
are not to pay more than the recipient needs for a fiscal year, nor are advance
payments to be used to provide interim financing for funding due from other
sources;</li>
        <li>notwithstanding the above limit on advance payments in a fiscal
year, an additional advance payment may be made in a fiscal year to cover the
federal government’s share of expected eligible expenditures to be incurred by
the recipient during April of the following fiscal year. Such a payment should
be made only in circumstances where a department deems it essential to meet the
objectives of a funding agreement.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The Directive requires departmental managers to
monitor the use of advance payments and to obtain timely accounting from
recipients to ensure that they are being spent for authorized purposes and that
unexpended balances in the hands of recipients are reasonable. The
determination of what is a reasonable unexpended balance is left to
departmental discretion; however, it should be judged in relation to the
recipient’s near-term cash flow requirements for the project or initiative. </p>
      <p>The Directive also provides discretion to departmental
managers to assess, based on the risk of non-performance or overpayment, when to
retain a holdback of a portion of any payment to be made to a recipient. </p>
      <p>
        Departmental managers are to ensure that any amounts
repayable by or recoverable from recipients are recognized as debts due to the
Crown and that appropriate action is taken for recovery. Funding agreements
should specify that interest is to be charged on overdue repayments in
accordance with the 
        <em>
          <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-96-188/">Interest
and Administrative Charges Regulations</a>
        </em>
        <sup id="fn1-rf">
          <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn1">
            <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
            1
          </a>
        </sup>
        . However, reasonable unexpended balances of advance payments held by
a recipient at the end of any fiscal year within the term of a multi-year
funding agreement are not to be considered as repayable at that time. 
      </p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="7" title="7. Reporting, monitoring, and auditing">
      <p>
        Reflecting again one of the key principles of the 

        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13525">Policy on Transfer Payments</a>
        ,
the 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
         requires that departmental managers ensure that the level of
monitoring of recipients, and the reporting required from them, reflects an
assessment of the risks specific to the program, the value of the funding in
relation to administrative costs, and the risk profile of the recipients. 
      </p>
      <p>Since, by definition, grants are not subject to being
accounted for by recipients, reporting required on grants is often confined to
the collection of information that may be necessary to meet the department’s
performance measurement requirements and, where appropriate, provide assurance
on the ongoing eligibility of the recipient. </p>
      <p>Reporting required on contributions, on the other
hand, should be sufficient to:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>account for the use of the funding and provide adequate documentation
and support for making contribution payments;</li>
        <li>demonstrate whether the obligations and objectives set out in the
funding agreement are met; and</li>
        <li>support the department’s accountability and performance
measurement requirements.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>With respect to the reporting required from a
recipient, departmental managers should also determine if any specific
assurances on the validity of the information provided are necessary. Such
assurances can take a wide variety of forms; they may include, for example:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>a certification by a senior official in the recipient
organization as to the correctness and completeness of information provided
(e.g., chief financial officer, executive director);</li>
        <li>a certification or statement from the recipient’s independent
external auditor attesting to the correctness and completeness of information
provided; or</li>
        <li>independently audited annual financial statements.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>In requiring assurances from external auditors,
departmental managers should be clear as to the value they add and be cognizant
of the cost of providing such assurances.</p>
      <p>The Directive requires departmental managers to
monitor contribution funding agreements to ensure that recipients comply with
the obligations and performance objectives of the agreements. This will include
the timely assessment of reports from recipients and other monitoring
activities that are appropriate to ensure compliance. </p>
      <p>For any particular funding agreement, the level of
monitoring and the approach to monitoring should reflect the level of risk. But
the overall monitoring activities for any transfer payment program are to be
sufficient to allow managers to assess and report on the progress and
performance of the program.</p>
      <p>
        One monitoring tool at the level of the individual
recipient is a recipient audit. A recipient audit is an independent assessment
to provide assurance on a recipient’s compliance with a funding agreement, conducted
on behalf of departmental managers by a suitably qualified agent. When
departmental managers determine that recipient audits are a necessary part of
their monitoring regime to complement their other monitoring activities, the Directive
requires that a risk-based plan for such audits is to be prepared and executed.
The scope of individual recipient audits may address any or all financial and
non-financial aspects of a funding agreement; the guiding principles in
selecting which aspects are to be addressed in a recipient audit should be the
risks involved and the manager’s need for assurance or additional information
on those aspects of the funding agreement. More detailed guidance on recipient audits
is found in the 
        <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19061">Guideline on Recipient Audits Under the Policy on Transfer Payments and the Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
        .
      </p>
      <p>Contribution funding agreements are to include
provisions that will enable departmental managers to initiate recipient audits when
they determine that audits are necessary or appropriate, and provisions that
recipients are to retain records and make them available for this purpose. Note
that recipient audit provisions in contribution agreements with other orders of
government or with foreign recipients are not always required; departmental
managers have the discretion to determine when such provisions are appropriate
and necessary. Funding agreements for grants normally do not have recipient
audit provisions, but they may be included where departmental managers deem
them appropriate. </p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="8" title="8. Special topics">
      <section anchor="8.1" title="8.1 Requirements related to specific recipient groups">
        <p>
          The 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
           provides for tailoring general requirements
to reflect relationships with three specific groups of recipients: other orders
of government, foreign recipients, and Indigenous recipients.
        </p>
        <h4>8.1.1 Other orders of government</h4>
        <p>For the purposes of the Directive, other orders of government are Canada’s provincial and territorial governments and provincial and territorial government
entities. Other orders of government do not include municipal governments.</p>
        <p>The Government of Canada provides significant
financial support to provincial and territorial governments through four major
transfers: equalization, territorial formula financing, the Canada
Health Transfer, and the Canada Social Transfer. The equalization and territorial formula financing programs
provide unconditional transfers to the provinces and territories. Equalization
enables less prosperous provincial governments to provide their residents with
public services that are reasonably comparable to those in other provinces, at
reasonably comparable levels of taxation. Territorial formula financing provides
territorial governments with funding to support public services, in recognition
of the higher cost of providing programs and services in the North. The
Canada Health Transfer and Canada Social Transfer are federal transfers that support
specific policy areas such as health care, post-secondary education, social
assistance and social services, early childhood
development, and child care.</p>
        <p>In addition to these four major programs, there are
many other transfer payment programs under which payments are made to other
orders of government to support specific objectives. </p>
        <p>The Directive reflects the federal government’s
position of due recognition of the
jurisdiction of provinces and territories. As a guiding principle, therefore,
the Directive requires that arrangements for a transfer payment
to a province or territory should be based on respect for the jurisdiction and
responsibilities of that government. Moreover, these arrangements are to take
into account the accountability mechanisms to its citizens that a province or
territory may have in place.</p>
        <p>The Directive recognizes that, given the wide range of
transfer payments to other orders of government, there is a need for
considerable flexibility in constructing appropriate accountability mechanisms
for these payments. The Directive provides this flexibility in a number of
areas:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            First, with respect to terms and conditions, it recognizes that
there are circumstances where terms and conditions may not be appropriate or
required. This may occur, for example, with statutory transfer payments or
transfer payments arising out of a federal-provincial-territorial agreement.
Further, where terms and conditions are appropriate, the Directive sets out a
reduced set of mandatory elements, with other elements to be tailored to the
circumstances of the proposed transfers
            <sup id="fn2-rf">
              <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn2">
                <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
                2
              </a>
            </sup>
            .
          </li>
          <li>Similarly, with respect to funding agreements, the Directive
recognizes that both the federal government and a provincial or territorial
recipient may not always contemplate or intend that a particular funding
agreement should constitute a document that would be an enforceable contract.
Consequently, the Directive allows an agreement to be couched in terms that express
the degree of enforceability deemed appropriate in the circumstances, and that provide
sufficient commitment or obligation to ensure that the funding is used for the
intended purposes and that objectives are achieved. </li>
          <li>The Directive also provides considerable flexibility to tailor
the elements included in a funding agreement with a province or territory to
the circumstances of the transfer payment.</li>
          <li>The Directive also allows departmental managers to determine the
extent to which the general requirements of the Directive relating to determining
the level of funding, cash management, and recipient reporting, monitoring, and
auditing can be applied in managing transfer payments to other orders of
government. If managers determine that any of these requirements are not
appropriate in dealing with a transfer payment to an other order of government,
they do not have to apply these requirements nor do they have to seek an
exemption from the President of the Treasury Board to do this.</li>
          <li>Finally, the Directive recognizes that, when transfer payments to
provinces and territories are unconditional, accountability mechanisms are to
be appropriately limited.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Given the flexibility permitted by the Directive, the
accountability mechanisms put in place are to:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Identify the intended purposes, the expected outcomes, whether
leveraging or cost sharing applies, and the responsibilities of the parties
involved;</li>
          <li>Take into account and, to the greatest extent possible, rely on the
accountability regimes of these governments, including audit, evaluation, and
direct reporting to citizens; </li>
          <li>Identify the monitoring and reporting for the transfer payment
within the recipient government; </li>
          <li>Where direct reporting to the federal government is required,
provide for specific audit assurance from the recipient government only where
necessary; and</li>
          <li>
            Enable appropriate and timely monitoring and reporting by the
federal department on the use of the funds provided and the results achieved
            <sup id="fn3-rf">
              <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn3">
                <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
                3
              </a>
            </sup>
            .
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>In the development of terms and conditions or other
accountability mechanisms relating to proposed transfer payments to other
orders of government, departmental managers are to consult on strategic matters
with the Intergovernmental Affairs Secretariat of the Privy Council Office and
with the Department of Finance.</p>
        <h4>8.1.2 Foreign recipients</h4>
        <p>For the purposes of the Directive,
foreign recipients are foreign states and intergovernmental organizations of
which two or more states are members. International organizations that do not
have states as members are not foreign recipients for the purposes of the Directive.</p>
        <p>The Directive distinguishes between assessed contributions
payable to international organizations and all other grants and contributions
to foreign recipients. </p>
        <p>
          An assessed contribution is a transfer payment to fund
 Canada’s assessed share of the costs of operations of an international
organization of which Canada is a member as a result of an act of Parliament, a
Cabinet decision, an Order in Council, or an international treaty. The Directive
requires that departmental managers consult with both the Treasury Board
Secretariat and the Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade when
developing any Memorandum to Cabinet, Treasury Board submission, or terms and
conditions related to assessed contributions. Part 1 of 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appJ">Appendix
J of the Directive</a>
           sets out mandatory requirements for terms and conditions
for assessed contributions.
        </p>
        <p>As an assessed contribution is essentially a payment
that results directly from Canada’s membership in an international
organization, the Directive allows payment to be made without the need to have
a funding agreement, provided the payment is due and has been requested by the
international organization and is in compliance with the approved terms and
conditions. Moreover, the cash management and the recipient reporting,
monitoring, and auditing requirements of the Directive do not apply in dealing
with assessed contributions.</p>
        <p>
          Part 2 of 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appJ">Appendix J of the Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
          
deals with transfer payments to foreign recipients other than assessed
contributions, setting out the elements to be addressed in terms and conditions
for such transfer payments programs and in funding agreements with foreign
recipients. 
        </p>
        <p>The Directive recognizes that, in making a transfer
payment to a foreign recipient, the funding agreement may not be intended to
constitute an enforceable contract but rather may be intended as a statement of
the agreed intentions and commitments of both participants.</p>
        <p>The Directive also allows departmental managers to
determine the extent to which the general requirements of the Directive
relating to cash management and recipient reporting, monitoring, and auditing
can be applied in managing transfer payments to foreign recipients. If managers
determine that any of these requirements are not appropriate in dealing with a
transfer payment to a foreign recipient, they do not have to apply these
requirements, nor do they have to seek an exemption from the President of the
Treasury Board to do this.</p>
        <h4>8.1.3 Indigenous people and Indigenous recipients</h4>
        <p>The Directive introduces specific sets of
requirements related to transfer payments to Indigenous people. </p>
        <p>First, in recognition of the very wide range of
transfer payment programs targeted to Indigenous people, the number of
departments involved in delivering these programs, and the ongoing nature of
the relationships involved, the Directive requires departmental managers
involved in the management of these programs to ensure that there is focused
and sustained leadership in working toward consistent approaches that are more
reflective of the needs of Indigenous people. These efforts are to emphasize strategies
for engagement, the standardization of administrative processes, the
coordination of recipient audits, the reduction of administrative requirements,
the use of single funding agreements to cover transfer payments from multiple
programs, the use of multi-year funding agreements and the harmonization of
transfer payment programs targeted to Indigenous people. When applicable, the Treasury
Board Secretariat is to be consulted to facilitate collaboration among
departments on these issues.</p>
        <p>
          Second, the Directive makes available for use by any
department three additional contribution funding approaches for Indigenous
recipients that were originally developed and approved for use by specific
departments. These are the fixed, flexible, and block contribution funding
approaches, described in 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appK">Appendix K of the Directive</a>
          . The Directive requires that departmental managers promote and
support the use of these additional contribution funding approaches where
deemed appropriate. The flexible and block funding approaches involve
multi-year funding agreements designed to support and reflect stable ongoing
relationships and provide additional flexibilities to Indigenous recipients in
the use of funding. 
        </p>
        <p>These additional funding approaches are for Indigenous
recipients only; for the purposes of the Directive, an Indigenous recipient is
an Indigenous individual or entity that has received a transfer
payment, or has been authorized
to receive a transfer payment, under a transfer payment program that is
specifically targeted to Indigenous people or has a component specifically
targeted to Indigenous people. Terms and conditions for a transfer payment
program are to indicate whether the additional funding approaches may be used
for that program.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Directive specifically recognizes that
the terms and conditions for a transfer payment program that permits transfer
payments to Indigenous recipients may include an element that would authorize
advance payments to be made throughout the fiscal year to accommodate financial
reporting by a recipient on an annual basis only.</p>
        <p>
          More detailed information on the requirements of the Directive
related to Indigenous people and Indigenous recipients is included in the appendix
to this document, “
          <a href="#appA">Appendix A: Specific provisions with respect to Indigenous recipients</a>
          ”.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="8.2" title="8.2 Up-front multi-year funding">
        <p>Up-front multi-year funding is defined in the Directive as funding approved and payable to a
recipient to meet expenditures for more than one year and where an
appropriation for the full amount has been obtained. </p>
        <h4>8.2.1 Up-front multi-year funding specifically authorized by statute</h4>
        <p>
          Normally, up-front multi-year funding
is provided to a 
          <em>named recipient</em>
           under authority provided in an act of
Parliament—a budget implementation act, appropriation act, or other statute. Where this is so, terms and conditions are usually not necessary,
but the funding agreement is to be approved by Treasury Board before it is
executed. Funding agreements for up-front multi-year funding are to follow the
requirements of 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appH">Appendix H of the Directive</a>
          .
        </p>
        <p>When the funding agreement is
executed, the recipient is entitled to the full amount of the funding, subject
to the provisions of the funding agreement. The Directive requires, however, that
when the total amount provided is $50 million or more, the amount is to be paid
in annual payments, based on the recipient’s cash flow requirements. The
provision for annual payments is to be included in the funding agreement, which
would also establish the documentation to be provided by the recipient to
support its requisitions for payments. </p>
        <p>Named recipients of up-front
multi-year funding are usually not-for profit corporations. It is usually
appropriate to provide up-front multi-year funding only where the recipient needs
to be able to demonstrate its financial stability in order to meet objectives
involving the implementation of longer-term plans, undertaking multi-year
commitments, or matching leveraged funding from the public and private sectors.</p>
        <h4>8.2.2 Up-front multi-year funding authorized in terms and conditions</h4>
        <p>As noted above, most up-front
multi-year funding is provided to a named recipient under the specific authority
of an act of Parliament. The Directive, however, provides a second route for
providing up-front multi-year funding. Treasury Board may approve terms and
conditions that specifically permit up-front multi-year funding to a recipient
or category of recipients where the maximum amount payable to any recipient is
limited to $10 million. Under these circumstances, where Treasury Board
has approved terms and conditions, Treasury Board approval of individual
funding agreements is not required. However, an appropriation needs to be in place
in order for the full amount of the up-front multi-year funding to be provided
to a recipient.</p>
        <h4>8.2.3 Endowment funding</h4>
        <p>Endowment funding is a particular
type of up-front multi-year funding where a transfer
payment is provided to a recipient for the restricted purpose of being invested
by the recipient to produce an ongoing source of income to be used for purposes
specified in a funding agreement. Endowment funding may be appropriate
when there is an intention or requirement to fund a recipient on a long-term
basis and the recipient has the capacity to manage invested funds. </p>
        <p>When a decision has been made to provide endowment
funding, the choice of the transfer payment instrument to make the payment is
important. A grant may be most appropriate where sufficient assurance is
available at the time of providing the endowment that the funding will be used
for the purposes for which it is provided and where no ongoing accounting for
the use of the funding is deemed necessary. Where ongoing monitoring and reporting
on the use of the funds provided is required, endowment funding should be
provided on the same basis as other up-front multi-year funding. </p>
        <p>
          When a grant is to be used to provide endowment
funding, the funding agreement provisions of 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appH">Appendix H of the Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
           should be adapted as necessary; the recipient reporting and accounting
requirements are not appropriate to a funding agreement for a grant.
        </p>
        <p>In cases where endowment funding is provided other
than by way of a grant, the Directive requires that funding is not to be
provided as endowment funding in perpetuity, which would create perpetual
monitoring obligations for the funding department and perpetual reporting
obligations for the recipient. Rather, funding agreements are to contain
provisions for a review of the restrictions on the use of the endowment funding
within a period of 20 years and a subsequent determination by the minister if
such restrictions are to continue, be removed, or, with the agreement of the
recipient, amended. Where the minister decides that the restrictions are to be
continued for a further period, a date for a future review is to be
established. </p>
        <p>Again, in cases where endowment funding is provided
other than by way of a grant, funding agreements are to be specific about what
happens when investment losses occur. In particular, funding agreements are to
specify whether income from investment is to be used first to maintain the
capital amount of the endowment funding in the event of realized or unrealized
investment losses.</p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="8.3" title="8.3 Contributions that are repayable">
        <p>
          The terms and conditions of a
transfer payment program may provide that contributions made under the program
are to be repayable. A recipient’s obligation to repay may be conditional or
unconditional, and the amount to be repaid may be the full amount
          <sup id="fn4-rf">
            <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn4">
              <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
              4
            </a>
          </sup>
          
of the contribution or part of it. Whether contributions are to be repayable
and what factors influence repayment are key issues to be addressed at the design
stage of a transfer payment program. These decisions are clearly related to the
objectives of the program. It should be noted that there is nothing in the Policy
or the Directive that limits the use of repayable contributions to for-profit
recipients or that requires that all contributions to for-profit recipients are
to be fully or partially repayable. 
        </p>
        <p>Where contributions are to be
repayable, the Directive requires that the terms and conditions of the transfer
payment program set out:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The factors that determine whether repayment is to be made. If
the contributions are to be unconditionally repayable, this should be clear. If
repayment is to be conditional, the terms and conditions are to describe the
events or circumstances that will trigger repayment obligations;</li>
          <li>
            The factors that will determine the amount of the repayment if
repayment in full
            <sup id="fn5-rf">
              <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn5">
                <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
                5
              </a>
            </sup>
             is not always required; and
          </li>
          <li>The terms of repayment. These should address the timing of
repayments and any interest charges that apply to overdue payments.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          There is one set of circumstances
where, as a general rule, terms and conditions are to indicate that
contributions are to be repayable. This is where contributions are made
to for-profit businesses, 
          <em>and</em>
           these contributions are intended to allow
the businesses to generate profits or increase the value of the businesses. However,
even where these circumstances apply, 
          <strong>terms and conditions</strong>
           for the
program may permit non-repayable contributions when one or more of the
following apply:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>The contribution is less than $100,000 and the administrative
burden of repayable contributions is not justified;</li>
          <li>The benefits from the contribution accrue broadly rather than to
the recipient;</li>
          <li>The primary aim is income support and income stabilization for
individuals;</li>
          <li>The recipient is a Canadian business under the terms of the
Defence Production Sharing Agreement and the Defence Development Sharing
Agreement and governments are the sole financing bodies;</li>
          <li>The contribution is made with the primary aim of furthering basic
research and development, including a payment made through a granting council
or other government entity whose mandate is to promote research and
development;</li>
          <li>The recipient is an Indigenous-controlled business whose
articles of incorporation do not permit dividends to be paid or distributed to
shareholders; and</li>
          <li>The contribution is in support of a project funded under an
international agreement that is restrictive for recoveries.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>When terms and conditions are silent
and do not specifically provide for non-repayable contributions in any of these
situations, there is no discretion to permit non-repayable contributions when
the contributions are made to for-profit businesses and are intended to
allow the businesses to generate profits or increase the value of the
businesses (other than the case-by-case ministerial exception noted below).</p>
        <p>
          When a contribution is made to a for-profit business
and is intended to allow the business to generate profits or increase the value
of the business, then the expectation is that the contribution will be
unconditionally repayable in full
          <sup id="fn6-rf">
            <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn6">
              <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
              6
            </a>
          </sup>
          .
        </p>
        <p>Where a repayable contribution is to
be made, the Directive requires that the funding agreement address the
conditions that determine whether repayment is to be made and the amount to be
repaid, the timing of repayments, and interest charges.</p>
        <p>
          It should be noted that, where terms and conditions
require that recipients repay contributions, a minister has authority under the

          <em>
            <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13525">Policy on
Transfer Payments</a>
          </em>
           (Section 5.3.8) to approve an exception when the proposed
funding to a particular recipient is less than $250,000. This authority to allow
an exception to the terms and conditions is to be applied on a case-specific
basis; there is no authority for the minister to give a blanket exception for
all contributions under $250,000. The exception is to be approved by the
minister prior to execution of the funding agreement and the provision of the
funding. The deputy head is required to ensure that a minister’s exercise of
this authority is publicly disclosed on the department’s website within 30 days
of the approval of the exemption. Note that this policy authority to approve an
exception to terms and conditions does not authorize a minister to forgive or
write off any amount that is repayable under a funding agreement (see sections
23, 24, and 25 of the 
          <em>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/">Financial Administration Act</a>
          </em>
           and the 
          <em>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-94-602/">Debt
Write-off Regulations 1994</a>
          </em>
          ).
        </p>
        <p>
          Information on the accounting treatment of
contributions made that are conditionally or unconditionally repayable, and on
the accounting recognition of repayments due from the recipients, can be found
in 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32517">Directive on Accounting Standards: GC 3050 Loans Receivable</a>
          .
        </p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="8.4" title="8.4 Stacking limits">
        <p>In the Directive, “stacking limit” means the maximum limit
on the level of total Canadian government funding that is permitted under a
transfer payment program for any one activity, initiative or project of a
recipient. Total Canadian government funding is funding available to a
recipient from federal, provincial, territorial, and municipal governments for
that activity, initiative or project. The amount that may be paid to a
recipient who is receiving funding from provincial, municipal, or other federal
sources toward an activity, project, or initiative is limited to an amount that
would bring the total of all such government funding to the established
stacking limit.</p>
        <p>Departmental managers are responsible for establishing
a stacking limit in the terms and conditions for a transfer payment program.
The stacking limit is to be expressed either as a percentage of the total eligible
expenditures or alternatively as a percentage of total expenditures of an activity,
initiative or project to be funded under the terms and conditions, whichever is
most appropriate for the transfer payment program design. Setting a stacking
limit of less than 100% means that a recipient’s activity, initiative or
project will not be funded completely by Canadian governments; some portion
will have to be funded by the recipient or non-government sources. When a
stacking limit is set at 100%, there is no stacking restriction on funding from
Canadian government sources.</p>
        <p>
          The stacking limit is one of the factors
          <sup id="fn7-rf">
            <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn7">
              <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
              7
            </a>
          </sup>
           that may establish the maximum amount that may be paid to a recipient by way of
grant or contribution.
        </p>
        <table class="table table-bordered table-condensed mrgn-tp-lg">
          <tr>
            <td class="text-center">Maximum amount of transfer payment</td>
            <td class="text-center">
              <strong>Equals</strong>
            </td>
            <td class="text-center">
              Total eligible expenditures
              <br/>
              or
              <br/>
              total expenditures
            </td>
            <td class="text-center">
              <strong>Multiplied by</strong>
            </td>
            <td class="text-center">Stacking limit</td>
            <td class="text-center">
              <strong>Subtracted by</strong>
            </td>
            <td class="text-center">Funding from other Canadian government sources</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>Text description of above table: Total eligible expenditures or total expenditures, multiply by the stacking limit,  subtract the funds from the other Canadian government sources equals the maximum amount of transfer payment.</p>
        <p>
          This calculation requires that departmental managers
collect information at the time an application is made on funding received or
to be received from other Canadian governments (including funding from other
federal government departments) for an applicant’s activity, initiative or
project. The types of funding to be taken into account are set out in 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appC">Appendix C of the Directive - Total Canadian Government Funding and Stacking Limits</a>
          . All funding from Canadian governments for the
particular activity, initiative or project is to be taken into account, not
just funding for expenditures deemed eligible in the terms and conditions. Since
all funding from Canadian government sources is to be taken into account, it is
not necessary to establish whether funding from other governments is meant to
support eligible or ineligible expenditures as defined by terms and conditions.

        </p>
        <p>
          Where the amount of a contribution made is in excess
of $100,000, the Directive requires an end-of-project check on a recipient’s actual
funding; the funding agreement is to require that, upon completion of the
funded initiative, the recipient is to provide a statement of the total funding
that has been provided from all sources, including total government funding
received for the initiative. The funding agreement is also to set out the basis
of repayment of funding where the stacking limit has been exceeded (see 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208#appG">Appendix G of the Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
          ).
        </p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="8.5" title="8.5 Official languages">
        <p>
          The Policy and Directive
both underline the government’s and departments’ obligations under the 
          <em>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/">Official Languages
Act</a>
          </em>
          .
        </p>
        <p>The Policy requires
deputy heads to ensure that, when a transfer payment program supports
activities that benefit members of both official language communities, the
design and delivery of the program respect the obligations of the Government of
Canada as set out in Part VII of the Act in relation to the promotion of
linguistic duality and the development of official-language minority
communities, in addition to ensuring that services and benefits are made
available in both official languages in compliance with the Act. </p>
        <p>The Directive specifically
creates the expectation that departmental managers who have responsibility for
the design or redesign of a transfer payment program are to assess and document
the manner in which the obligations of the Government of Canada set out in the
Act are to be taken into account and, where relevant, how they are to be
applied in designing the transfer payment program. In cases where it is
determined that the program supports activities that may have an impact on
members of either official language community, the terms and conditions for the
program are to describe how these obligations are to be met. The Directive also
highlights that, where performance expectations with respect to official
languages are to be placed on a recipient, these have to be incorporated in the
funding agreement. </p>
        <p>
          The 
          <em>
            <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/O-3.01/">Official Languages
Act</a>
          </em>
           gives to the Department of Canadian Heritage the
mandate to promote a coordinated approach by federal institutions. As  such, an Information Note was developed collaboratively between the Department  of Canadian Heritage (PCH) and the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat (TBS).
        </p>
        <p>
          The primary objective of this information note is to provide clarity regarding official languages requirements as they relate to the design, delivery, and management of transfer payment programs. The note can be found here: 
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/services/official-languages-bilingualism/publications/ol-requirements-transfer-payment.html">Official Language Requirements for Transfer Payments</a>
          .
        </p>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="9" title="9. Acknowledgment">
      <p>The Office of the Comptroller General and the Treasury
Board Secretariat would like to acknowledge the contributions of the Technical
Committee formed to provide advice to the Office of the Comptroller General and
the Secretariat during the development of the Policy and the Directive
on matters relating to transfer payments to Indigenous recipients. </p>
      <p>This guidance will be updated periodically as required. Suggestions are welcome.</p>
      <p>
        <strong>Enquiries concerning this guideline should be directed as follows:</strong>
      </p>
      <p>
        Members of the public may contact 
        <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/corporate/contact.html">Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries</a>
         regarding any questions about this guideline.
      </p>
      <p>Individuals from departments should contact their chief financial officer or departmental transfer payment centre of expertise regarding any questions about this guideline.</p>
      <p>
        The chief financial officer or individuals from a departmental transfer payment centre of expertise may contact 
        <a href="mailto:fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca">Financial Management Enquiries</a>
         for interpretation of this guideline.
      </p>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
  <appendices>
    <appendix anchor="appA" title="Appendix A: Specific provisions with respect to Indigenous recipients">
      <h3>1. About this appendix</h3>
      <p>
        This appendix is designed to explain in more detail the specific
requirements in the 
        <em>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14208">Directive on Transfer Payments</a>
        </em>
         (the Directive) that deal with transfer payments to
Indigenous recipients. 
      </p>
      <h3>2. About transfer
payments to Indigenous recipients</h3>
      <p>The Government of Canada provides a
wide range of transfer payment programs specifically targeted to Indigenous
people. Many departments are involved in managing these programs. Very often, funding
relationships are long-term in nature and provide support for important community
programming. </p>
      <p>Responding to these unique circumstances, the directive introduces
specific provisions related to transfer payments to Indigenous recipients and transfer
payment programs that are specifically targeted to Indigenous people.</p>
      <h3>3. Leadership responsibilities</h3>
      <p>
        The Directive requires that departmental managers involved in the management of these programs are to ensure that there is 
        <strong>focused and sustained leadership</strong>
         in working toward consistent approaches that are more reflective of the needs of Indigenous people. These leadership efforts are to place emphasis on a number of issues where general responsibilities have been assigned by the policy and directive but where particular focus with respect to Indigenous recipients is essential. The issues are described below. 
      </p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.1 Recipient engagement</em>
      </h4>
      <p>
        The policy recognizes the importance of engaging
stakeholders in the design and delivery of transfer payment programs as a means
of creating innovative, cost-effective, and citizen- and recipient-focused
transfer payment programs and ensuring that such programs are accessible,
understandable and usable. Deputy heads have a general responsibility to engage
applicants and recipients, when appropriate
        <sup id="fn8-rf">
          <a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn8">
            <span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>
            8
          </a>
        </sup>
        . Engagement is particularly important with respect to Indigenous programs. Many
Indigenous recipients administer funding agreements on behalf of Indigenous
people and are knowledgeable and well positioned to contribute effectively toward
the design and delivery of these programs—to make them more reflective of the
needs of Indigenous people and to help identify improvements that can be made.
Frequently, Indigenous recipients receive funding under more than one transfer
payment program; in these cases, recipients can potentially provide insight and
information on any duplication that occurs and on opportunities for
harmonization of programs and standardization of administrative requirements
and processes. It is for these reasons that the Directive requires departmental
managers to ensure that there is focused and sustained leadership with
regard to the recipient engagement strategy. 
      </p>
      <p>Focus group discussions with stakeholders from departments
and Indigenous communities and organizations identified the following factors as
important in achieving effective engagement with Indigenous recipients:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Be up front on the purpose of the engagement and what it can
influence;</li>
        <li>Develop a protocol with clear parameters;</li>
        <li>Consider policy forums and technical groups that report to
advisory groups;</li>
        <li>Respect recipients’ position—engagement should not be viewed as
simply getting stakeholders on board;</li>
        <li>Accommodate interests of specific groups as appropriate—First
Nation, Inuit and Métis; and </li>
        <li>Provide feedback on the outcome of the engagement to those
involved.</li>
      </ul>
      <h4>
        <em>3.2 Reduction of administrative requirements</em>
      </h4>
      <p>
        The policy requires deputy heads to ensure that the administrative requirements on recipients are
proportionate to the risk level involved in making a particular transfer
payment. The Directive goes further with respect to transfer payments to
Indigenous recipients. Here, departmental managers are to ensure that there is
focused and sustained leadership in 
        <em>reducing</em>
         administrative
requirements. This requirement recognizes that, given the wide range of
programs targeted to Indigenous people offered by many departments,
administrative requirements under multiple funding agreements can become a
significant burden for Indigenous recipients, and efforts to reduce this burden
are necessary.
      </p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.3 Standardization of administrative processes</em>
      </h4>
      <p>Standardization is about the establishment of
common processes, systems, or procedures for the management and delivery of
transfer payments. Where an individual recipient receives funding under a
number of transfer payment programs, there are clearly increased
administrative requirements if the administrative processes for each of these
programs are significantly different, e.g., application processes, reporting
processes, or payment processes. To the extent that such processes can be
standardized, there is potential for the reduction in administrative requirements on
both recipients and departments. Moreover, standardization may reduce the
repetitive collection of the same base data from applicants. The policy
requires deputy heads to pursue opportunities to standardize the administration
of transfer payment processes, procedures, and requirements within their
departments and, to the extent possible, with other departments, to achieve
efficiencies in the administration of transfer payment programs for applicants,
recipients, and departments.</p>
      <p>Many Indigenous recipients receive funding
under a number of transfer payment programs. Leadership by departmental
managers on standardization of administrative processes for these programs,
where standardization is possible, is a necessary step towards the reduction
of administrative requirements. </p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.4 Coordination of recipient audits</em>
      </h4>
      <p>Departmental managers are responsible for ensuring that
recipients comply with the financial and performance obligations of funding
agreements. They do this through appropriate reporting and monitoring. One tool
that may be used to complement other monitoring activities is a recipient
audit. A recipient audit is an independent assessment directed by departmental
managers, and conducted by an independent auditor, to provide assurance to
departmental managers on a recipient’s compliance with a funding agreement.
Funding agreements for contributions normally contain provisions establishing
the minister’s right to undertake a recipient audit. Funding agreements for
grants do not normally contain such provisions, but these may be included where
departmental managers deem them necessary.</p>
      <p>When recipients receive funding under a number of transfer
payment programs, they are potentially subject to a recipient audit under each
funding agreement, particularly where funding is provided by way of
contributions. The Directive makes departmental managers responsible for
ensuring that recipient audits of a single recipient are to be coordinated
within the department and, to the extent possible, with other departments, and
a single recipient audit is to be organized whenever feasible.</p>
      <p>Given that many Indigenous recipients receive transfer
payments for various programs under funding agreements, the importance of leadership by departmental managers in coordinating any recipient
audits is significant. Multiple, uncoordinated recipient audits are to be
avoided. Coordination of audit planning to keep the number of separate
recipient audits for a recipient to a minimum will demand organization within a
department and, to some extent, with other departments that have funding
agreements with the same recipient.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.5 Use of single funding agreements to cover transfer payments from multiple
programs</em>
      </h4>
      <p>When a recipient is to receive transfer payments from multiple
transfer payment programs, the Directive requires departmental managers to
determine whether the use of a single agreement is practical for the department
and beneficial to the recipient. Again, given that many Indigenous recipients
receive transfer payments for various programs, it is important to consider whether
a single funding agreement is appropriate. A single agreement for a number of
transfer payments offers the potential of reduced administrative requirements
for the recipient, inherent standardization of processes, and easier coordination
of any recipient audits.</p>
      <p>Some departments (e.g., the Department of Indian and Northern Development
and the Department of Health) have been using single funding agreements with
Indigenous recipients for a number of years. These funding agreements are functioning
well. Some of these single funding agreements involve transfer payments from
more than one department. From time to time, other departments, such as the
Department of Fisheries and Oceans and the Department of Public Safety and
Emergency Preparedness, have made transfer payments to Indigenous recipients
under these funding agreements. Departmental managers may wish to contact these
departments for purposes of sharing a best practice on the use of a single
funding agreement to cover transfer payments from multiple programs within a
department and with other departments.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.6 Use of multi-year funding agreements</em>
      </h4>
      <p>When the achievement of the objectives of a transfer payment
program or a funding agreement may involve a relationship with a recipient over
a number of years, the Directive requires departmental managers to determine
whether multi-year funding agreements are appropriate. Many transfer payment
programs provide funding to Indigenous recipients on an ongoing basis. In these
circumstances, it is clearly appropriate to give consideration to the use of
multi-year funding agreements. The block and flexible contribution funding
approaches discussed below are multi-year funding approaches developed
specifically for Indigenous recipients. These can be used only when certain
preconditions are met. When these preconditions are not met, a multi-year
funding agreement may still be appropriate, albeit without the additional
flexibilities that the block and flexible contribution approaches provide.</p>
      <p>Leadership in consistently examining when multi-year funding
agreements are appropriate offers the potential to reduce the administrative
 requirements on recipients and departments and better reflect and strengthen ongoing
relationships.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.7 Harmonization of transfer payment programs</em>
      </h4>
      <p>Harmonization of transfer payment programs is the alignment or
integration of two or more transfer payment programs that contribute to similar
objectives or serve the same recipients. Harmonization is another approach to the
reduction of administrative requirements on recipients. It is
also a means of addressing overlap and duplication among transfer payment
programs. The policy makes deputy heads responsible for ensuring, when
appropriate, the harmonization of transfer payment
programs within their departments and ensuring collaboration
with other departments. </p>
      <p>Leadership by departmental
managers on harmonization should examine whether programs could be combined, or
eliminated with adjustments made to other existing programs, with the intention
of reducing administrative requirements on both recipients and departments. </p>
      <h4>
        <em>3.8 Treasury Board Secretariat support</em>
      </h4>
      <p>The Directive requires departmental managers, when
appropriate, to consult with the Treasury Board Secretariat to facilitate
collaboration among departments on the issues described above. This requirement
is consistent with the obligation placed on the Secretary of the Treasury Board
by the policy to provide leadership and support in promoting and facilitating
collaboration among departments for government-wide harmonization of transfer
payment programs, the standardization of administrative processes, procedures,
and requirements, and the sharing of best practices.</p>
      <h3>4. Additional contribution funding approaches</h3>
      <p>
        The Directive makes available for use by any department three
contribution funding approaches for Indigenous recipients that had been
developed and approved for use by specific departments. These are the fixed,
flexible, and block contribution funding approaches. These additional funding
approaches are for Indigenous recipients only; it should be noted that, for the
purposes of the Directive, an Indigenous recipient is an Indigenous individual
or entity that has received a transfer payment, or has been authorized to receive a transfer
payment, 
        <strong>under a transfer payment program that is specifically
targeted to Indigenous people or has a component specifically targeted to
Indigenous people</strong>
        . 
      </p>
      <p>The Directive requires that departmental managers promote and
support the use of these additional contribution funding approaches where
deemed appropriate. In designing or redesigning transfer payment programs, they
are to specifically look at opportunities to use these approaches. Terms and
conditions for transfer payment programs that permit transfer payment programs
to Indigenous recipients are to specifically address whether these approaches
will be used.</p>
      <p>These funding approaches provide additional flexibilities in
transfer payments to Indigenous recipients, and the flexible and block funding
approaches involve multi-year funding agreements designed to support and
reflect stable, ongoing relationships.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>4.1 Fixed contribution funding</em>
      </h4>
      <p>Fixed contribution funding is an option for providing transfer
payments to Indigenous recipients where a contribution can be based on a
predetermined annual estimate of the funding required by the recipient to
achieve the objectives of a transfer payment program. </p>
      <p>Under fixed contribution funding, the recipient may retain any
unexpended funding remaining at the expiry of the funding agreement, provided
that the obligations and objectives set out in the funding agreement are met
and the recipient agrees to use the unexpended funding for purposes consistent
with the program objectives or any other purpose agreed to by the funding department.
Reporting requirements for a funding agreement for fixed contribution should
enable identification of the amount of unexpended funding at the expiry of the
agreement. </p>
      <p>Given that unexpended funding may be retained, there has to be
a basis for establishing a reliable estimate of the amount of funding required
by the recipient. The Directive requires that, where fixed contribution funding
is to be used under a transfer payment program, the basis for establishing the
amounts of funding is one of the core design elements that are to be considered
and documented when the program is being designed or redesigned. </p>
      <p>When the fixed contribution funding approach is used, the
funding agreement is to make it clear that the recipient is responsible for assuming
any costs in excess of the funding provided to meet the obligations and
objectives set out in the funding agreement.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>4.2 Flexible contribution funding</em>
      </h4>
      <p>Flexible contribution funding is an option for providing
transfer payments to Indigenous recipients where the recipient has met certain
assessment criteria and where a transfer payment program that requires a relationship
of two or more years with a recipient to achieve objectives can be funded under
a multi-year funding agreement.</p>
      <p>The flexible funding approach reflects and strengthens stable
relationships with recipients. It is to be used only where the recipient has an
established track record in the management of transfer payments as evidenced by
having met the assessment criteria described below. </p>
      <p>The flexible funding approach is suitable where it is expected
that a relationship of two or more years with a recipient will be required to
achieve the objectives of the transfer payment program and a commensurate
multi-year funding agreement is appropriate. The approach recognizes that,
during the period of the agreement, providing the recipient flexibility in the
use of funding is likely to be positive in attaining the overall objectives of
the funding agreement. </p>
      <p>Under the flexible contribution funding approach, a recipient
may redirect funding among cost categories established in the funding agreement
(also referred to in some departments as budget or service codes). In addition,
during the period of the funding agreement, unexpended funding remaining at the
end of each fiscal year may be carried forward for use in the next fiscal year
to further achieve results toward the program objectives. However, at the
expiry of the funding agreement, any unexpended funding remaining is to be
repaid; it becomes a debt due to the Crown.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>4.3 Block contribution funding</em>
      </h4>
      <p>Block contribution funding is an option for providing transfer
payments to Indigenous recipients where the recipient has met certain
assessment criteria and where a number of transfer payment programs that
require a relationship of five or more years with the recipient to achieve
objectives can be funded under a single multi-year funding agreement.</p>
      <p>The block contribution funding approach is designed to
facilitate and support long-term, trusted relationships with recipients who are
receiving transfer payments from a number of programs. Again, as with the
flexible funding approach, it is to be used only where the recipient has an
established track record in the management of transfer payments as evidenced by
having met the assessment criteria described below.</p>
      <p>Under the block contribution funding approach, a single
multi-year funding agreement is used to provide funding for a block of
programs, where it is recognized that it will require a relationship of five or
more years with the recipient to achieve the objectives of the various
programs. It is a prerequisite that the funding for each program in the block
can be determined on an annual basis, and the basis for establishing the
amounts of funding is one of the core design elements that are to be considered
and documented when the program is being designed or redesigned. However, this
approach allows the recipient to adjust the relative priority of programs
within the block and redirect funding among the programs to address changing
circumstances and the recipient’s evolving priorities, so long as progress
toward all of the objectives is being maintained. Moreover, the recipient may
retain any unexpended funding, during the term and at the expiry of the funding
agreement, provided that the obligations and objectives set out in the funding
agreement are met and that the recipient agrees to use the unexpended funding
for purposes consistent with the multi-program objectives or any other
purpose reflecting the priorities of the recipient agreed to by the department.
It is also recognized that, with the block funding approach, annual reporting
on costs incurred and results achieved is sufficient. </p>
      <p>When the block contribution funding approach is used, the
funding agreement is to make it clear that the recipient is responsible for
assuming any costs in excess of the funding provided to meet the obligations
and objectives set out in the funding agreement.</p>
      <h4>
        <em>4.4 Assessment criteria</em>
      </h4>
      <p>The use of flexible and block contribution funding is
consistent with demonstrated capacity of the recipients to manage transfer
payments. The Directive requires departmental managers to assess this capacity
before using these approaches. In the assessment, departmental managers are to take
into account the recipient’s:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>governance structure;</li>
        <li>organization for purposes of program management, financial and
administrative experience, and capacity to deliver programs;</li>
        <li>processes and procedures for program management and financial control;</li>
        <li>accountability mechanisms for transparency, disclosure, responsibility, and redress; and</li>
        <li>financial position. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>More generally, under the Policy and Directive, it is
necessary to ensure that administrative requirements on recipients are tailored
to the risks involved in making a particular transfer payment to that
recipient. This will require that a department has the means to be able to identify
and assess not only risks specific to the program and materiality of funding,

but also the risk profile of the recipient. The particular assessment required
in relation to flexible and block contribution funding may be part of the
process of defining a risk profile for an Indigenous recipient.</p>
      <h3>5. Contribution payments and advance payments</h3>
      <p>There are two additional elements that may be addressed in
terms and conditions of transfer payment programs that permit transfer payments
to Indigenous recipients.</p>
      <p>The first concerns how contribution payments may be made. The general requirement is that terms and
conditions are to identify one or a combination of three bases on which
contribution final payments and any progress payments are to be made: achievement
of predetermined performance expectations or milestones, reimbursement of eligible
expenditures, or a costing formula. For terms and conditions that permit
transfer payments to Indigenous recipients, a fourth element is added: payments
may be based on a predetermined amount. </p>
      <p>While contribution payments to a recipient may be made on any
or a combination of these bases, the Directive requires that the total amount
of contribution funding paid to a recipient under a funding agreement is not to
exceed the eligible expenditures actually incurred by the recipient in
completing the recipient’s initiative or project, or such portion of these
expenditures as was to be funded under the agreement. The only exceptions to
this general rule are when funding is provided to an Indigenous recipient under
the fixed or block funding approaches described above, where a recipient may be
permitted to retain unexpended funding at the expiry of a funding agreement to
be used as specified in the agreement.</p>
      <p>The second element has
to do with advance payments and their relationship to annual reporting by
recipients. Where advance payments are made, the general requirement of the
Directive is that departmental managers are to obtain timely accounting from
recipients to ensure that advance payments are being spent for authorized
purposes and that unexpended balances in the hands of recipients are reasonable,
having regard to the recipient’s cash flow requirements. However, many funding
agreements with Indigenous recipients ask for financial reporting on an annual
basis only. Where a department has determined that annual financial reporting is
appropriate and is sufficient to support control and accountability
requirements, it is to be encouraged as a means of reducing the administrative
 requirements on recipients and departments. Annual financial reporting, however, does
not support ongoing monitoring of unexpended balances of advance payments, as
required by the Directive. Consequently, the Directive provides that terms and
conditions that permit transfer payments to Indigenous recipients may include
an element that would specifically allow advance payments to be made throughout
a fiscal year to accommodate financial reporting by a recipient on an annual
basis only.</p>
    </appendix>
  </appendices>
  <footnotes>
    <footnote anchor="fn1" reference="fn1-rf" title="1" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 1">Where a
department has an ongoing funding relationship with a recipient based on annual
funding agreements, the department may consider establishing a contractual
right in funding agreements to recover any amount repayable or recoverable from
the recipient by way of set-off against amounts payable under a subsequent
agreement. This may avoid overdue repayments and interest charges.</footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn2" reference="fn2-rf" title="2" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 2">A transfer
payment program may be targeted to a broad range of recipients that might
include other orders of government. In such cases, the terms and conditions are
to comply with Appendices D or E (or both) of the directive. Alternatively,
where other orders of government are a targeted category of recipients, terms
and conditions may include a separate section for other orders of government
following Appendix I of the directive, with a section for other categories of
recipients following Appendices D or E (or both) of the directive.</footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn3" reference="fn3-rf" title="3" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 3">
      For background,  see the December 2008 
      <em>Report of the Auditor General of Canada</em>
      ,  “
      <a href="https://www.oag-bvg.gc.ca/internet/docs/parl_oag_200812_01_e.pdf">Chapter 1—A Study of Federal Transfers to Provinces  and Territories</a>
      ”

    </footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn4" reference="fn4-rf" title="4" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 4">The terms and
conditions of some transfer payment programs permit the repayment of more than
the face amount of a contribution.</footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn5" reference="fn5-rf" title="5" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 5">Ibid.</footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn6" reference="fn6-rf" title="6" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 6">Ibid.</footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn7" reference="fn7-rf" title="7" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 7">Note that other factors, apart from the stacking limit, may act to establish
the maximum amount of a transfer payment. For example, terms and conditions of
a transfer payment program may state that the transfer payment is not to
exceed, say, 30% of eligible expenditures. Or a recipient may have 80% of
necessary funding from non-government sources and does not need more than 20%
from the federal government.</footnote>
    <footnote anchor="fn8" reference="fn8-rf" title="8" tooltip="Return to footnote reference 8">Under the
transition considerations of the policy, this requirement of the policy applies
only to new and continued transfer payment programs approved after March 31, 2010, with earlier adoption encouraged.</footnote>
  </footnotes>
</doc>
