<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Directive on Accounting Standards: GC 3450 Financial Instruments" documentID="32784" versionID="2" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="z:/PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><notetoreader><p>This  document is part of the Appendix A of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32499">Directive on  Accounting Standards</a>.</p></notetoreader><chapters><chapter anchor="A" title="Primary PSAS reference"><ul class="list-unstyled"><li>PS 3450 Financial Instruments</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="B" title="Effective date"><ul class="list-unstyled"><li>April 1,  2022</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="C" title="Government of Canada Consolidated Financial Statements"><ol><li>As stated in PS 3450.004,  not all financial assets meet the definition of a financial instrument. Only  those financial assets that arise from contracts and give rise to financial  liabilities or equity of the counterparty are financial instruments.</li><li>In accordance with PS 3450.003(p),  contracts to buy or sell non-financial items when quantities are in accordance  with a government’s expected purchase, sale or usage requirements are excluded from the scope of PS 3450. Such “own use” contracts provide  for settlement only through the receipt or delivery of goods or services and, therefore, are not financial  instruments.</li><li>However, as stated in PS 3450.005 and PS 3450.A13, contracts  in quantities in excess of a government’s expected purchase, sale or usage  requirements that can be settled net in cash or  another financial instrument in lieu of the receipt or delivery of the goods or  services, or in which the non-financial item is readily convertible to cash (for  example, a traded commodity), are in the scope of PS 3450.</li><li>PS 3450.007 requires  that loan guarantees accounted for under PS 3310 Loan Guarantees are also  within the scope of PS 3450 when the payments under the guarantee  fluctuate in response to changes in a financial variable (for example, interest  rate, financial instrument price, commodity price, foreign exchange rate, index  or prices or rates, credit rating or credit index) or a non-financial variable that is not specific  to a party to the contract. In such instances, the loan guarantee is a  derivative in its entirety and must be measured at fair value in accordance  with PS 3450.017. PS 3450 does not apply to guarantees  other than loan guarantees accounted for under PS 3310.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="D" title="Recognition"><ol start="5"><li>PS 3450.14 requires that derivatives embedded  in host contracts be identified and assessed to determine whether their economic  characteristics are closely related to the host contract. Only those host  contracts in the scope of PS 3450 must be reviewed for embedded  derivatives. When an embedded derivative is not closely related to the host  contract, it is accounted for separately as a stand-alone derivative.</li><li>PS 3450A.25-.26 provides further  examples of financial and non-financial contracts with embedded derivatives that are closely related and those  that are not closely related. Additional guidance is provided in <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-fra.aspx?id=32780">GC 3450 Guideline: Embedded Directives</a>.</li><li>The government may hold securities in deposit or trust accounts or as collateral support. To determine whether these  securities are recognized as financial assets of the government, departments  must assess whether the government has control of the resource and the  associated benefits by reviewing the relevant legal, contractual and regulatory requirements. In general, securities held  in trust would not be recognized as financial assets unless title to the  security passes to the government.</li><li>Also refer  to GC 4100 Specified Purpose Accounts, section C, subsection 4.b.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="E" title="Measurement"><ol start="9"><li>There are two measurement categories under PS 3450:
    <ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Fair value:
      <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>Derivatives; </li><li>Portfolio investments quoted in an active  market; and</li><li>Financial instruments designated to the fair value  category<sup id="fn1-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn1"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>1</a></sup> (optional); </li></ol></li><li>Cost or amortized cost:
        <ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>All  other financial instruments of the Government of Canada.  </li></ol></li></ol></li><li>The  effective interest method, defined in the glossary to PS 3450, is applied  to determine the carrying value of financial instruments measured at amortized  cost according to PS 3450.033. Guidance  on applying the effective interest  method is provided  in PS 3450.A41-.A45.</li><li>All  cash flows arising from the contractual terms of the financial instrument are  included in the effective interest  rate calculation. These cash  flows include interest payments, any fees, points paid  or received, transaction costs and other premiums or discounts (PS 3450.A41).</li><li>When applying  the effective interest  method to a variable rate loan, the amortization period reflects the next date at which  the interest rate is reset. For example, the terms of the loan may state that the loan rate is reset  annually to the prime rate plus a  fixed percentage (PS 3450.A42).</li><li>When  it is not possible to reliably estimate either the cash flows or the expected  life of a variable rate loan,  the contractual cash flows over the full contractual term of the financial  instrument would be used (PS 3450.A41).</li><li>When  applying the effective interest method to variable rate concessionary loans  that are not reset on specific dates (for example, the interest rate changes on  the date the prime rate changes),  the interest payments  and loan discount  would be considered separately as follows:
    <ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>The loan discount would be calculated in  accordance with GC 3050 at inception of the loan and amortized based on the  effective interest method over the contractual term. The loan discount is not  affected by future changes in the interest rate; and</li><li>The floating interest revenue would be accrued  annually based on the current interest rate according to the contractual terms  of the loan.  </li></ol></li><li>The original  effective interest rate continues to be applied to the gross  carrying amount of the  financial asset for which a valuation allowance has been recognized unless  collection of the principal or interest is not reasonably assured (PS 3450.A41).</li><li>When an impairment loss has been recognized, the effective interest  rate is adjusted  to the rate of interest used  to discount the future cash flows for the purpose of measuring the impairment  loss (PS 3450.A45).</li><li>The effective  interest method is not required  for financial assets and liabilities  where balances are not material or where they have a short  period to maturity, such as:
    <ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Accounts  payable and accrued  liabilities; or</li><li>Accounts  receivable. </li></ol></li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="F" title="Foreign reserves (Department of Finance Canada)"><ol start="18"><li>The assets  and related non-derivative liabilities of the Exchange Fund Account are managed on a fair value basis. These financial  instruments are measured at cost or amortized cost, and not designated to the  fair value category as permitted by PS 3450.23.</li><li>Balances with the International Monetary Fund (IMF), whether  in the form of subscriptions, notes, or special drawing rights, are excluded from the scope  of PS 3450 (PS 3450.003(i)).</li><li>The accounting policies that apply to balances with the IMF are set out in the following  table.</li></ol><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr class="active"><th scope="col">IMF balance type</th><th scope="col">Applicable accounting policy</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="colgroup" class="text-left">Recognition</th></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">All IMF balances</th><td>PS 3450.009-.014</td></tr><tr><th scope="colgroup" class="text-left">Measurement</th></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">Subscriptions to the IMF (quota)</th><td>Asset measured at cost</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">Special drawing rights (SDR) allocations</th><td>Asset measured at cost</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">SDR holdings</th><td>Liability measured at cost</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">Loans receivable</th><td>Asset measured at cost with valuation allowance</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">Notes payable</th><td>Liability measured at cost no less than the amount payable on demand</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">Interest on loans receivable</th><td>Effective interest method</td></tr><tr><th scope="colgroup" class="text-left">Presentation</th></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">Unrealized and realized foreign exchange gains and losses</th><td>Statement of Operations</td></tr><tr><th scope="row" class="fnt-nrml">IMF assets and liabilities</th><td>Statement of Financial Position</td></tr></tbody></table></chapter><chapter anchor="G" title="Departmental Financial Statements"><ol start="13"><li>Applies  without additional policy choices or interpretation for Departmental Financial  Statements.</li></ol></chapter></chapters><footnotes><footnote anchor="fn1" reference="fn1-rf" title="1" tooltip="Return to footnote 1 referrer"><p>Designation of financial instruments to the fair value category,  as permitted by PS 3450.23, requires the approval of  the Comptroller General of Canada.</p></footnote></footnotes></doc>