<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<doc xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" title="Directive on Accounting Standards: GC 3260 Liability for Contaminated Sites" documentID="32782" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd">
  <notetoreader>
    <p>
      This  document is part of the Appendix A of the 
      <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32499">Directive on Accounting  Standards</a>
      .
    </p>
  </notetoreader>
  <chapters>
    <chapter anchor="A" title="Primary PSAS reference">
      <ul class="list-unstyled">
        <li>PS 3260 Liability for  contaminated sites</li>
      </ul>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="B" title="Effective date">
      <ul class="list-unstyled">
        <li>April 1, 2017</li>
      </ul>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="C" title="Government of Canada  Consolidated Financial Statements">
      <ol>
        <li>
          All contaminated sites must be reported in the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/fcsi-rscf/home-accueil-eng.aspx">Federal  Contaminated Sites Inventory (FCSI)</a>
          , which is  maintained by     the Acquired Services and Assets Sector at the Office of the  Comptroller General. 
        </li>
        <li>For sites with liabilities associated with asset retirement  obligations, refer to GC 3280 Asset Retirement Obligations.</li>
      </ol>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="D" title="Recognition">
      <ol start="3">
        <li>
          The Government of Canada determines whether contamination  is above the environmental standard, in accordance with subsection 4.2.17 of the 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32691">Directive on the Management of Real Property</a>
          . 
        </li>
        <li>If a liability is not being recorded because a reasonable estimate cannot be  made, future economic benefits are not expected to be given up,  or the government is not responsible or is not accepting responsibility, the  reason or reasons must be provided, by site, to the Office of the Comptroller  General.</li>
        <li>
          Further to PS 3260.36-.39, if there is uncertainty  regarding the government’s responsibility, the government may have a contingent  liability. Refer to  
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32520">GC 3300-3310 Contingent Liabilities and Loan  Guarantees</a>
           for the accounting treatment of contingent liabilities. All  contingent liabilities related to the costs to remediate a contaminated site  must be recorded in the FCSI.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="E" title="Measurement">
      <ol start="6">
        <li>
          Remediation liabilities include:
    
          <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
            <li>Care, maintenance, and monitoring costs that are a part of the  remediation strategy and that are completed during the remediation phase;</li>
            <li>Final confirmatory sampling and the final report;</li>
            <li>Short-term (that is, two to five years) monitoring costs included in the remediation  strategy; and</li>
            <li>Risk management costs only if directly related to reducing,  removing, or containing the contaminant in order to prevent, minimize or  mitigate damage to human health or the environment.</li>
          </ol>
        </li>
        <li>
          Remediation liabilities exclude:  
    
          <ol class="lst-lwr-alph">
            <li>Costs related to research and development of technologies (that is, bench-scale  testing or demonstration on a small scale at field sites) or a skill  development program;</li>
            <li>Costs relating to surveying areas in order to find archaeological sites,  excavating sites in order to recover cultural remains, and the subsequent  classification, analysis, and preservation of these sites; and</li>
            <li>Costs incurred once the site has been brought to a level that is  considered acceptable such as sampling, maintenance, and monitoring performed  after the site has been remediated and confirmed to be successfully remediated.</li>
          </ol>
        </li>
        <li>
          Costs in excess of the amount required to bring the site to the current  minimum standard should be classified as a betterment. Refer to 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32518">GC 3150  Tangible Capital Assets</a>
           for the accounting treatment of betterments.
        </li>
        <li>When the planned use of a site is expected to cause  contamination that must be cleaned-up on a regular basis, for example firing  ranges, these costs do not meet the definition of a remediation liability and  should be expensed. </li>
      </ol>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="F" title="Recoveries">
      <ol start="10">
        <li>Further to PS 3260.62, the accounting treatment of recoveries will  depend on the nature of the event. Further analysis should be done to determine  if the recoveries are related to an asset or a contingent asset.</li>
        <li>
          Refer to 
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32521">GC 3320 Contingent Assets</a>
           for the accounting treatment of contingent recoveries. 
        </li>
      </ol>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="G" title="Disclosure">
      <ol start="12">
        <li>
          Pursuant  to PS 3260.66, the following nature and source categories are used for  disclosure in the Public Accounts of Canada and reporting in FCSI:
    
          <ul class="lst-none">
            <li>01: Radioactive Material</li>
            <li>02: Former Mineral Exploration  Sites</li>
            <li>03: Military and Former Military  Sites</li>
            <li>04: Fuel Related Practices</li>
            <li>05: Landfill/Waste Sites</li>
            <li>06: Engineered Assets/Air and  Land Transportation</li>
            <li>07: Marine Facilities/Aquatic  Sites</li>
            <li>08: Parks and Protected Areas</li>
            <li>09: Office/Commercial/Industrial  Operations</li>
            <li>10: Other </li>
          </ul>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="H" title="Departmental Financial  Statements">
      <ol start="13">
        <li>Applies without additional policy choices or interpretation  for Departmental Financial Statements. </li>
      </ol>
    </chapter>
    <chapter anchor="I" title="Other related references">
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593">Policy on the  Planning and Management of Investments</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/gcwiki/images/0/02/QA_Environmental_Liabilities_-_February_2013.pdf">Question and Answer (Q&amp;A) Environmental Liabilities </a>
          (accessible only on  the Government of Canada network) 
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/fcsi-rscf/home-accueil-eng.aspx">Federal  Contaminated Sites Inventory</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/environment-climate-change/services/federal-contaminated-sites/federal-approach.html">Federal Approach to Contaminated Sites</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          Receiver General Manual – 
          <a href="https://gcintranet.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/fp-gf/pcpc-paci/index-eng.html">Public Accounts of  Canada instructions</a>
           (formerly chapter 15) (accessible only on the Government of Canada network) 
        </li>
      </ul>
    </chapter>
  </chapters>
</doc>
