<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><doc title="Directive on Accounting Standards: GC 3280 Asset Retirement Obligations" documentID="32783" versionID="1" language="en" space="preserve" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PolicyInstrumentSchema.HTML5.xsd"><notetoreader><p>This  document is part of the Appendix A of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32499">Directive on Accounting Standards</a>.</p></notetoreader><chapters><chapter anchor="A" title="Primary PSAS reference"><ul class="list-unstyled"><li>PS 3280  Asset Retirement Obligations</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="B" title="Effective date"><ul><li>April 1,  2022</li></ul></chapter><chapter anchor="C" title="Government of Canada Consolidated Financial Statements"><ol><li>The Government of Canada (GC) has chosen to apply  the modified retroactive transitional approach in accordance with  PS 3280.68(b).</li><li>Further to PS 3280.69-.71, in a case where a  new law or regulation was put in place after an asset is constructed or bought,  the retroactive treatment would only start at the point at which the law  exists. Accordingly, the obligation is recognized, and any amortization begins  at that point in time.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="D" title="Recognition"><ol start="3"><li>Further to PS 3280.08(b), the asset retirement  obligations include, but are not limited to:
    <ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Removal of  asbestos and other similar hazardous material in buildings;</li><li>Decommissioning of nuclear facilities;</li><li>Decommissioning of underground storage tanks; </li><li>Closure and post-closure obligations associated  with mining activities; </li><li>Closure and post-closure obligations associated  with landfills;</li><li>Closure and post-closure obligations associated  with other works and infrastructure;</li><li>Closure and post-closure obligations associated  with waste storage facilities;</li><li>Closure and post-closure obligations associated  with oil and gas production facilities; </li><li>Removal of leasehold improvements, notably costs  associated in the restoration of the leased premises to their original state;</li><li>Activities related to demilitarization or  disarmament for all asset categories;</li><li>Retirement activities linked to ships, boats,  aircraft and other vehicles;</li><li>Retirement activities linked to machinery and  equipment; and</li><li>Retirement activities linked to informatics.</li></ol></li><li>Further to PS 3280.23, if there is uncertainty  regarding the existence of an asset retirement obligation, the government may  have a contingent liability. Refer to <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32520">GC 3300-3310 Contingent Liabilities and Loan Guarantees</a> for the  accounting treatment of contingent liabilities.</li><li>Further to PS 3280.30, asset retirement  obligations related to fully amortized assets in productive use should be  capitalized at the time of initial recognition. This incremental asset is to be  amortized and the related asset retirement obligation is to be accreted over the  revised useful life of the asset. </li><li>In accordance with PS 3280.31-.32, the asset  retirement obligations associated with unrecognized tangible capital assets or  those no longer in productive use would be expensed.</li><li>The estimate of the liability should not be based  on a future event, that is, whether the site will be divested. The retirement  plan should be the action required under existing agreements, contracts,  legislation or legally enforceable obligations. One should not record an  obligation that arises solely from a plan to sell or otherwise dispose of a  tangible capital asset.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="E" title="Measurement"><ol start="8"><li>Asset retirement obligations include: 
    <ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Post-retirement operation, maintenance and monitoring that  are an integral part of the retirement of the tangible capital asset;</li><li>Payroll and benefits, equipment and facilities, materials,  legal and other professional fees, and overhead costs directly attributable to  the asset retirement activity;</li><li>Costs related to the nature and extent of the asset  retirement obligation in accordance with the agreement, contract, legislation,  or a legally enforceable obligation; and</li><li>Construction of other tangible capital assets to perform  retirement activities.</li></ol></li><li>Asset retirement obligations exclude:
    <ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Costs related to the obligation created by waste or  by-products; </li><li>Routine replacement of a tangible capital asset;</li><li>Renovations and other betterment costs; and</li><li>Costs associated with assets under construction.</li></ol></li><li>In  accordance with PS 3280.46-.48, present value is often the best technique  with which to estimate a liability when the liability is expected to occur over  future periods. Judgment will be required to determine if present value  adjustments are significant, and therefore required. If required, the asset  retirement obligation must be discounted to reflect its present value using the  rate on the actual yield curve for zero-coupon Government of Canada bonds. This  rate is published by the Bank of Canada. The undiscounted liabilities should  also be adjusted for inflation. Subsequent to initial measurement, these  estimates will need to be updated as new information is obtained.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="F" title="Recoveries"><ol start="11"><li>Further to PS 3280.60, the accounting  treatment of recoveries will depend on the nature of the event. Further  analysis should be done to determine if the recoveries are related to an asset  or a contingent asset.</li><li>Refer to <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32521">GC 3320  Contingent Assets</a> for the accounting treatment of contingent  recoveries.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="G" title="Disclosure"><ol start="13"><li>Further to PS 3280.66, it may be required to  disclose the nature of the liability and information about the potential effect  on financial statements when a previous undisclosed liability becomes  measurable.</li><li>Information about the nature of liabilities that  cannot be recognized may have to be disclosed in the notes together with the reason  or reasons why a reasonable estimate cannot be made of the amount involved.</li><li>The Office of the Comptroller General should be  consulted when an amount cannot be reasonably estimated.</li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="H" title="Departmental Financial Statements"><ol start="16"><li>When a tangible capital asset is transferred to another  government department, it is necessary to also transfer the related asset  retirement obligation. In addition to the transfer of the asset’s historical  cost and accumulated amortization in accordance with <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32518">GC 3150 Tangible Capital Assets</a>, the transferring department  must transfer the balance of the asset retirement obligation to the receiving  department. The resulting accounting treatment will not produce a gain or loss  and there will be no impact at the government-wide level. Refer to <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32663">GC 3420 Inter-entity Transactions</a> for  additional guidance on inter-entity transactions.</li><li>When lease agreements are signed between Public  Services and Procurement Canada (PSPC) and the landlord (third party), it is  established that the related asset retirement obligation liability and  associated asset would be recorded by PSPC.</li><li>In a case where a department has a material  leasehold improvement, the Office of the Comptroller General should be  consulted if an off-book entry is required for Departmental Financial Statement  purposes. This is anticipated to only be a concern for departments that have  entity-level audited financial statements. </li></ol></chapter><chapter anchor="I" title="Other related references"><ul><li><a href="https://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/gcwiki/images/a/a3/Draft_FAQ-EN.pdf">Asset Retirement Obligation Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)</a> (accessible  only on the Government of Canada network) </li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593">Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments</a></li><li>Receiver General Manual – <a href="https://gcintranet.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/fp-gf/pcpc-paci/index-eng.html">Public Accounts of  Canada instructions</a> (formerly chapter 15)</li></ul></chapter></chapters></doc>