<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Guide to Costing</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=32600", title: "Guide to Costing"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=32600&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2023-05-10",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Guide to Costing</h1><section class="alert alert-info"><h2>Note to reader</h2><p>The Guide to Costing takes effect on May 10, 2023 and replaces the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32751"><em>Guide to Cost Estimating</em></a>. </p></section><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guide  was published on May 10, 2023, and it replaces the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32751"><em>Guide to Cost Estimating</em></a> (June 10, 2019).</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Objectives and expected results</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guide explains costing in the Government of Canada (GC) and  outlines the principles and process, along with the corresponding approaches  and techniques, used to develop costing information that is credible.</p><p>This guide sets out how to develop credible  costing information that:</p><ul><li>provides  contextual insight that supports decision-making</li><li>improves  the understanding of cost uncertainty, cost risk and cost drivers</li><li>aligns with the objectives and expected  government-wide results identified  in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495"><em>Policy on Financial Management</em></a> and supports the assertions and  conclusions of the chief financial officer, as required by the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27256"><em>Guideline on Chief Financial Officer  Attestation for Cabinet Submissions</em></a></li><li>supports the obligations and requirements for external charging (fees)  and internal charging identified in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32502"><em>Directive on Charging and Special Financial  Authorities</em></a> and  the obligations and requirements for fees prescribed under the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/S-8.4/"><em>Service Fees Act</em></a></li><li>supports assessing life-cycle costs for investment decisions, as identified  in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593"><em>Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments</em></a></li><li>assists in the development of rough order of magnitude (ROM), indicative  and substantive estimates that are required when seeking Treasury Board  approvals or expenditure authorities for projects or programmes, as detailed in  the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32594"><em>Directive on the Management of Projects and Programmes</em></a></li><li>supports the life-cycle management  of real property, as described in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32691"><em>Directive on the Management of Real Property</em></a></li><li>supports the management of  procurements, as described in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32692"><em>Directive on the Management of  Procurement</em></a></li></ul><p>Costing has a role  to play in many different policy areas in the GC, and the costing principles  and process in this guide can be applied to inform decision-making in many different  fields.</p><p>  This guide can be used:</p><ul><li>as a  resource to understand the credibility of recipient costing information under  the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13525"><em>Policy  on Transfer Payments</em></a></li><li>when analyzing the cost impacts of procurements  that contribute to economic growth in Canada </li><li>to  analyze the life-cycle costs of investments when considering commitments made  in the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/innovation/greening-government/strategy.html"><em>Greening  Government Strategy</em></a></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Context</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Costing in the GC includes: </p><ul><li>cost accounting, which emphasizes the allocation  of costs (for example, direct and indirect)</li><li>cost estimating, which emphasizes forecasting  costs and the associated level of uncertainty and risk</li></ul><p>Credible costing information, as outlined in this guide, supports  decision-making that is based on evidence and data. Developing costing  information that is credible requires time and effort; there are several  challenges to developing such information, including:</p><ul><li>data availability and quality limitations</li><li>limited information about associated cost uncertainties  and risks</li><li>limited interaction between stakeholder groups (for  example, project managers, financial officers, subject matter experts)</li><li>resource constraints (for example, people, tools  and time)</li></ul><p>Despite  these challenges, credible costing information can be produced if a  standardized process that is rooted in internationally recognized best practice  is followed. <strong>The principles and process described in this guide can be applied  to all costing exercises in the GC.</strong></p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Common applications</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Decision-making in the GC requires credible costing  information. </p><p>Costing exercises that apply the principles and process  described in this guide produce credible costing information to support  decisions in the GC. These decisions range from those made by Cabinet to those  made internally within an organization. Some of the ways costing information  can be applied to support various types of decisions are outlined in <a href="#appA">Appendix A</a>.</p><p>Costing information supports:</p><ul><li>decisions between different courses of action</li><li>legislative or policy changes</li><li>decisions about offering a new initiative or  activity</li><li>level-of-service decisions</li><li>charging and cost-recovery decisions</li><li>investment decisions</li><li>contracting and procurement decisions</li><li>decisions about reorganizations</li><li>assessments of results</li></ul><p>While some  common applications are described, the guide does not focus on how costing  information can be used. These requirements are outlined in other legislation  and policy instruments.</p><p>  For  example, the costing process in this guide can be used to develop credible  costing information to support charging. However, the requirements for how the  costing information is used in external charging (fees) and internal charging are  identified in the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/S-8.4/"><em>Service Fees Act</em></a> and the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32502"><em>Directive on Charging and Special Financial  Authorities</em></a>.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. Roles and responsibilities</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Costing is a collaborative effort that involves multiple  stakeholders who have a range of knowledge and expertise. This section outlines  roles and responsibilities that may be assigned to stakeholders in order to enable  the development of credible costing information.</p><p>The roles and responsibilities listed in this section are  not exhaustive; the structure may vary by organization and additional responsibilities  are outlined in the associated policy instruments.</p><section><header><h3>Deputy heads</h3></header><p>Deputy heads may support the following:</p><ul><li>establishing and maintaining appropriate  governance and oversight structures to enable the production of credible  costing information and support engagement with key stakeholders</li><li>ensuring that costing exercises apply the GC’s  costing process, that resulting costing information is credible, and that relevant  costing information is disclosed for decision-making</li></ul><p>Refer to relevant policy instruments for a  complete list of deputy head responsibilities, such as subsection 4.1 of  the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495"><em>Policy  on Financial Management</em></a> and subsection 4.1 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593"><em>Policy  on the Planning and Management of Investments</em></a>.</p></section><section><header><h3>Chief financial officers</h3></header><p>Chief financial  officers may support the following:</p><ul><li>ensuring that their organization’s costing  capacity is aligned with the level of complexity, risk and materiality of the  initiatives</li><li>coordinating the collection and retention of costing  information and the provision of tools required to develop credible costing  information</li><li>ensuring due diligence in the application of the  costing process and challenging the credibility of the costing information  where necessary</li><li>ensuring that key costing information, including  the cost impact of key assumptions and the level of uncertainty and risk  associated with the initiative, is disclosed by way of a chief financial  officer attestation</li></ul><p>Refer to relevant  policy instruments for a complete list of chief financial officer responsibilities,  such as subsection 4.2 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495"><em>Policy on Financial Management</em></a> and section 3 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27256"><em>Guideline on Chief Financial Officer  Attestation for Cabinet Submissions</em></a>.</p></section><section><header><h3>Senior  departmental managers</h3></header><p>Senior departmental  managers may support the following: </p><ul><li>ensuring that the appropriate resources (for  example, people, tools, time) are assigned to develop and deliver credible costing  information in a manner that is consistent with the level of complexity, risk  and materiality associated with the initiatives</li><li>encouraging collaboration with stakeholders  throughout the development of the costing exercise</li><li>ensuring that the key costing information (for  example, quality of the data, impact of key assumptions and cost drivers, level  of uncertainty and risk, quality assurance and validation efforts) is disclosed  to the deputy head and chief financial officer, when applicable, to support obligations  for accountability and strategic decision-making</li></ul><p>Refer to relevant  policy instruments for a complete list of the responsibilities of senior  departmental managers, such as subsection 4.3 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32495"><em>Policy on Financial Management</em></a>.</p><p>  In certain  circumstances these responsibilities could apply to the roles of senior  designated officials, as outlined in subsection 4.1 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32692"><em>Directive on the Management of Procurement</em></a>.</p></section><section><header><h3>Manager of  a program or investment</h3></header><p>The manager of a  program or investment (that is, the director or manager) may support senior  departmental managers by:</p><ul><li>ensuring that costing practitioners have the information  needed to develop credible costing information (for example, documentation,  data and evidence, ground rules)</li><li>engaging departmental costing expertise, costing  practitioners and other stakeholders early and often throughout the initiative,  so that costing practitioners have sufficient time to develop credible costing  information</li><li>ensuring that the development of costing  information is clearly assigned in alignment with delivering results and includes  establishing a work plan and schedule</li><li>ensuring that key costing information is  documented and communicated, including the quality of the data, impact of key  assumptions and cost drivers, level of uncertainty and risk, and quality  assurance and validation efforts</li></ul><p>In certain  circumstances these responsibilities may apply to the role of project and  programme sponsors, as outlined in subsection 4.1.12 of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593"><em>Policy on the Planning and Management of  Investments</em></a>.</p></section><section><header><h3>Costing  practitioners</h3></header><p>Costing  practitioners may support the manager of a program or investment by:</p><ul><li>ensuring that the roles and responsibilities and  work plan for costing exercises are outlined in a manner that supports the  delivery of results</li><li>identifying and engaging stakeholders, including  subject matter experts, early and often to establish assumptions, gather data  and identify risks</li><li>applying the costing process to produce credible  costing information that supports the transparent disclosure of financial risk  for decision-making</li><li>clearly and concisely documenting the steps that  were taken to develop the costing information</li><li>ensuring that key costing information and  detailed costing information are communicated</li></ul><p>Since costing practitioners operate out of many different  areas and may have different roles, they are defined as any individual who  performs work related to costing. For example, the manager of a program or  investment may also be a costing practitioner.</p></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Credible costing information</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Credible costing information supports informed  decision-making in the GC by assessing the costs related to a decision. <strong>Credible costing information is the result of applying the <a href="#cha7">costing process</a> described below</strong>.</p><p>Credible costing information is defined by the following criteria.</p><section><header><h3>Process-driven</h3></header><p>Credible costing information is the result of a rigorous and  repeatable process that includes the participation of a wide range of  stakeholders. </p><p>Process-driven costing information ensures that:</p><ul><li>the purpose and deliverables of the costing  exercise are well defined</li><li>there is agreement on ground rules, assumptions  and data sources</li><li>stakeholders are engaged throughout the costing  exercise</li><li>errors are identified and corrected throughout  the costing exercise</li><li>the results of the costing exercise are clearly  communicated to stakeholders</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Comprehensive</h3></header><p>Credible costing information has a defined scope that  considers all cost elements related to the decision that the costing  information supports. Costing exercises should include clearly defined  boundaries in terms of time and scope and all related costs, such as inflation,  internal services and life-cycle costs.</p><p>Comprehensive costing information ensures that:</p><ul><li>the boundaries of the costing exercise can be  communicated to decision-makers and stakeholders</li><li>all relevant cost elements are included in the  costing exercise</li></ul><p>Figure 1 shows the evolution of costs over the life cycle  of a project or programme.</p><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 1: life-cycle  costs for each phase of a project or programme </strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol-cont/32600-fig1-eng.png" alt="life-cycle  costs for each phase of a project or programme. Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary class="wb-toggle">Figure 1 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 1 is a line graph. Time  is indicated on the X-axis and cost is indicated on the Y-axis. The four lines  on the graph represent the following phases: planning, acquisition, operations  and sustainment, and disposal. The lines show when the costs for each phase  occur and how they grow and decline over time.</p></details></figure></section><section><header><h3>Evidence-based</h3></header><p>Credible costing information is supported by evidence and  uses data as the basis for costs. Actual or historical data, which can include information  in an organization’s financial system of record, is the foundation of evidence-based  costing.</p><p>Evidence-based costing information ensures that:</p><ul><li>subjectivity in a costing exercise is reduced</li><li>the costing information has a traceable source  that can be examined and assessed by stakeholders and reviewers</li><li>data analysis can be used to improve the application  of costing techniques</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Risk-assessed</h3></header><p>Credible costing information considers the cost impacts of uncertainty  and risk. </p><p>  Risk-assessed costing information ensures that:</p><ul><li>costing exercises are more reliable as the  uncertainty associated with the underlying data and assumptions has been  considered</li><li>contingency amounts:
     <ul><li>provide confidence that the estimate or budget  is sufficient for the initiative or activity</li><li>are based on an uncertainty and risk assessment</li></ul></li><li>financial risk is transparently disclosed  to stakeholders and decision-makers </li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Validated</h3></header><p>Credible costing information is comparable to past  performance, similar initiatives or activities, or recognized benchmarks. Validated  costing information ensures that decision-makers and other stakeholders have  confidence that the costing information is reasonable.</p></section><section><header><h3>Documented</h3></header><p>Credible costing information is chronicled in sufficient  detail such that an independent party could reproduce the results of the  costing exercise.</p><p>Documented costing information ensures that:</p><ul><li>reviewers can understand how the costing  information was produced</li><li>the details of the costing exercise are  transparent and traceable, including costs that were not included in the  costing exercise</li><li>the costing information can support scrutiny and  audits</li><li>information (for example, assumptions, ground  rules and data sources) is stored in a location that is accessible to current  and future costing practitioners</li><li>lessons learned are recorded and used to inform  best practices for future exercises</li></ul><p>These criteria for credible costing relate to various policy  areas in the GC.</p><p>For example, the criteria support the development of rough  order of magnitude (ROM), indicative, and substantive cost estimates for programme  or project approvals and expenditure authorities, as outlined in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32594"><em>Directive on the Management of Projects and  Programmes</em></a>. Moreover, ensuring costing information is credible  supports other policy objectives, such as:</p><ul><li>ensuring oversight and sound stewardship of  public resources, as identified in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=16484"><em>Policy on  Internal Audit</em></a></li><li>making risk disclosure assertions, as  explained in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27256"><em>Guideline on Chief Financial Officer  Attestation for Cabinet Submissions</em></a></li><li>using costing  information to identify indicators, collect data and conduct evaluations, as  outlined in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=31306"><em>Directive on Results</em></a></li></ul></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. Costing process</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>The costing process outlined below applies to all costing  exercises in the GC. The level  of effort associated with the development of costing information should be  consistent with the purpose, complexity, risk and  materiality of the costing exercise. The application of the costing process  in organizations should be periodically reviewed to continually implement  lessons learned.</p><p>Some actions may be required throughout the  costing process, including stakeholder engagement, documentation and the  collection of lessons learned. While the steps are presented in a logical order, they are not always sequential.  Some steps may need to be executed simultaneously or iteratively. Additionally,  early steps in the process may need to be revisited as the costing exercise  progresses or more information is obtained about the initiative or activity. For  example, ground  rules, assumptions, uncertainties and risks are assessed as they relate to  prior initiatives or activities and as the current initiative or activity  evolves.</p><p>Figure 2 illustrates the steps in the costing process.</p><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 2: the  steps in the costing process </strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol-cont/32600-fig2-eng.png" alt="the  steps in the costing process. Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary class="wb-toggle">Figure 2 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 2 is cycle graph. The  seven steps of the costing process are shown:</p><ol><li>Establish a purpose and a plan</li><li>Employ a cost breakdown structure</li><li>Identify ground rules and assumptions</li><li>Gather data and evidence</li><li>Determine uncertainty, risk and cost </li><li>Assure and validate the exercise</li><li>Communicate the results*</li></ol><p>Arrows indicate which steps might  need to be revisited. At step 3, it may be necessary to go back to step 2.  At steps 4, 5 or 6, it may be necessary to go back to step 3.</p><p>* In some cases, the costing  process ends at step 7. In other cases, the process may occur more than  once and step 7 may lead back to step 1 as indicated in Figure 2.</p></details></figure><section><header><h3>Step 1: establish a purpose and a plan</h3></header><p>The purpose of the costing exercise is influenced by the  decision that the costing information will support. Establishing a purpose and  plan helps determine:</p><ul><li>which stakeholders to engage</li><li>the cost elements to be established by the  costing exercise</li><li>the time frame covered by the costing exercise</li><li>how to deliver the costing information </li></ul><p>The plan for the costing exercise should include:</p><ul><li>reviewing lessons learned from previous costing  exercises</li><li>completing a work plan for each step of the  costing process</li><li>establishing a schedule to meet deadlines and  communicate progress and delays</li><li>specifying which stakeholders will be consulted  and agreeing on how they will be engaged</li><li>specifying and assigning responsibilities  (stakeholders may need to be consulted)</li></ul><section><header><h4>Stakeholders who  should be consulted</h4></header><p>The chief financial officer should always be identified as a  key stakeholder when a costing exercise is prepared for a Cabinet submission. </p><p>Other stakeholders may include:</p><ul><li>representatives from internal service groups</li><li>managers who are responsible for the initiative  or activity or are otherwise impacted</li><li>employees engaged in the costing work, such as  financial management advisors or other functional specialists</li><li>employees who are responsible for data</li><li>other departments, agencies or governmental  organizations for cross-departmental initiatives or activities</li></ul></section></section><section><header><h3>Step 2: employ a cost breakdown structure</h3></header><p>The scope of activities that are included in the costing  exercise should be defined in consultation with stakeholders. </p><p>A cost breakdown structure (CBS) defines the scope by  breaking down an initiative or activity into cost elements that will need to be  assessed. A CBS should be selected or developed at the outset of a costing  exercise.</p><p>A CBS is a hierarchical structure in which overarching or “parent” cost elements are subdivided into independent “children” cost  elements. The sum of the children cost elements should amount to the value of  the parent cost element. In this way, a costing exercise can capture costs comprehensively  and prevent double counting. The subdivision should stop at the lowest level  that adds value for the purpose of comparison or data analysis.</p><p>A CBS should be consistent across similar initiatives or  activities. A consistent CBS organizes the gathered data and allows comparison,  even if the initiatives or activities have different sizes or complexities. In  instances where an initiative or activity already has a work breakdown  structure (WBS) used for project management, the CBS is usually developed in  conjunction with the WBS so that the breakdown of cost elements aligns with the  planned tasks.</p></section><section><header><h3>Step 3: identify ground rules and assumptions</h3></header><p>Ground rules and assumptions establish the baseline  conditions of a costing exercise. Ground rules and assumptions are necessary  components of every costing exercise.</p><p><strong>Ground rules</strong> are a prescribed set of conditions that  provide guidance to the direction of a costing exercise. They often become constraints  that define the boundaries and scope of the costing exercise. For example, a  ground rule for a construction project may be that all materials are to be procured  in Canada, which means that a costing exercise is limited to forecasting costs  for domestic materials.</p><p><strong>Assumptions </strong>are  the underpinning hypotheses upon which a costing exercise is built and  from which the costing requirements are drawn. Assumptions use evidence to make  judgments to fill the gaps between input data and the results of the costing  exercise. Assumptions are deemed to be true in the absence of facts and  supported by data when possible.  An example of an assumption might be that a new digital service can be  delivered using existing information technology infrastructure.</p><p>Ground rules and assumptions enable the determination of  costs when evidence and data may not be available for all cost elements. Ground  rules and assumptions should be documented so that the basis of a costing  exercise can be clearly demonstrated. Furthermore, documentation helps costing  practitioners ascertain when the ground rules, assumptions and subsequent results  are no longer valid, and provides a clear rationale for revisiting a costing  exercise.</p></section><section><header><h3>Step 4: gather evidence and data</h3></header><p>Evidence and data are required to determine costs. The data  used in a costing exercise should be the best available. In the absence of actual  or historical data, qualitative evidence from subject matter experts can be  transformed into data by using robust qualitative and quantitative research  techniques, as described in <a href="#furtherconsiderations">Further considerations</a>.</p><p>After data is collected, it should be normalized for  consistency and comparability. Normalization adjusts for differences between  the historical data and the initiative or activity that is the subject of the  costing exercise. Some common forms of normalization are adjustments to the  value of money over time (for example, inflation) and differences in purchase  location (for example, foreign exchange or regional price differences).</p><p>Data that is collected and normalized should be stored in an  accessible location for future use. Contextual information associated with the  data should also be saved so that the data can be interpreted correctly in the  future.</p></section><section><header><h3 id="step5">Step 5: determine uncertainty, risk and cost</h3></header><p>This step applies <a href="#costingapproaches">costing approaches</a> to the gathered data and evidence to determine costs.</p><p>A deterministic estimate, sometimes known as a point estimate,  should be established using one of the costing approaches.</p><p>A deterministic estimate is a single value that:</p><ul><li>represents the total expected cost of an initiative  or activity within a range of potential outcomes</li><li>does not consider the uncertainty and risk  associated with the cost elements</li></ul><p>The uncertainty and risk associated with the cost elements  should also be determined to identify the range of cost impacts and their  associated likelihood. </p><p><strong>Cost uncertainty</strong> stems from fluctuations in costs  that <strong>will occur</strong>. The exact impact of cost uncertainty is unknown due to imperfect  information. An example of cost uncertainty is the future foreign exchange rate  for materials or services procured in foreign currency. </p><p><strong>Cost risk</strong> is something that <strong>may or may not occur</strong> and that may increase or decrease cost. An example of cost risk is the cost  impact of a potential mechanical breakdown in a manufacturing environment.</p><p>A cost uncertainty and risk analysis helps assess whether an  estimate for an initiative or activity is realistic. The analysis quantifies  the cost impact of the uncertainty and risk associated with the initiative or  activity. The results of this analysis are more useful to decision-makers than  a deterministic estimate alone because the results communicate the range of potential costs and the likelihood and impact  of cost fluctuations.</p><p>Sensitivity analysis is a related tool that can be applied  to show how individual cost elements or assumptions influence the overall cost.</p><p>In general, an initiative or activity has greater cost  uncertainty during the early stages when there is less information available.  As the initiative or activity matures, the uncertainty associated with the  estimated costs decreases. For example, an initiative at the Memorandum to  Cabinet stage will have many more unknowns than an initiative at the Treasury Board  submission stage.</p><p>Figure 3 illustrates this concept for a project or programme using the cone of uncertainty, where over time, two distinct costing trends are noted:</p><ol><li>uncertainty decreases (represented by the  narrowing boundaries) as requirements become more concrete and risks either  materialize or are mitigated</li><li>estimates change (represented by points A through E)  as the level of effort to achieve objectives is better understood and some risks  materialize</li></ol><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 3: cone of uncertainty</strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol-cont/32600-fig3-eng.png" alt="Figure 3: cone of uncertainty. Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary class="wb-toggle">Figure 3 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 3 is a graph. Time is  indicated on the X-axis and cost is indicated on the Y-axis. There are two  bands: one that represents the upper cost-estimate boundary and another that  represents the lower cost-estimate boundary. Cost estimates at different phases  are labelled as follows:</p><ul><li>A: cost estimate at conception phase</li><li>B: cost estimate at identification phase</li><li>C: cost estimate at definition phase</li><li>D: cost estimate at implementation phase</li><li>E: cost estimate at close-out phase</li></ul><p>Over time, the space between the  bands narrows. The upper and lower cost-estimate boundaries practically meet at  E, the cost estimate at close-out phase.</p></details></figure><p>Uncertainty and risk can be assessed qualitatively or  quantitatively according to the complexity of the costing exercise and the  availability of data and evidence. For complex cost estimates, quantitative  statistical methods, such as Monte Carlo or methods of moments analysis, should  be used to determine cost uncertainty and risk.</p><p>Cost uncertainty and risk should be considered for every  costing exercise. The level of effort associated with assessing cost  uncertainty and risk should be proportional to the complexity, risk, and  materiality of an initiative or activity. Costing exercises should present a  range of potential cost outcomes based on an uncertainty and risk analysis, as  well as on a deterministic estimate, unless the range is insignificant. If the  range is insignificant, the rationale for not assessing cost uncertainty and  risk should be documented.</p><p>For example, in many cost accounting applications, the data  and evidence used to determine costs is very reliable and provides confidence  that there is little uncertainty or risk in the results.</p><p>One response to a cost uncertainty and risk assessment is contingency,  which is sometimes included in a cost estimate. Contingency should be based on a  cost uncertainty and risk analysis, as well as on the risk tolerance of  decision-makers, which can vary by initiative or activity. As a response to cost  uncertainty and risk, contingency may not reduce the residual risk completely,  but it should provide confidence to decision-makers that the initiative or  activity can be implemented.</p><p>Figure 4 is an S-curve that demonstrates the estimated  cost range of a project or programme at a specific point in time. A point along  the S-curve identifies a confidence level that describes the probability that a  project or programme will finish at or below a given  cost. The range of potential cost outcomes is  based on the uncertainty and risk faced by the project or programme. This information  can be used to inform a given risk-adjusted cost estimate and contingency and  help make decisions about trade-offs.</p><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 4: S-curve</strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol-cont/32600-fig4-eng.png" alt="Figure 4: S-curve. Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary class="wb-toggle">Figure 4 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 4 is a graph. Cost is  indicated on the X-axis and confidence level is indicated on the Y-axis. The  confidence level refers to the likelihood that the actual cost will be equal to or less than the cost estimate.</p><p>There are two points indicated on  the S-curve:</p><ul><li>deterministic estimate</li><li>risk-adjusted cost estimate</li></ul><p>The space between the deterministic estimate and the risk-adjusted cost estimate along  the X-axis represents the risk-adjusted contingency. The space along the X-axis  after the risk-adjusted cost estimate represents the potential financial impact  if the actual cost exceeds the risk-adjusted cost estimate.</p><p>The space along the  Y-axis above the risk-adjusted cost estimate represents the likelihood that the  actual cost will exceed the risk-adjusted cost estimate.</p></details></figure></section><section><header><h3>Step 6: assure and validate the exercise</h3></header><p>Assuring and validating a costing exercise provides  confidence in the rigour of the application of the costing process and the quality  of the results. The level of effort employed in this step should be consistent  with the level of effort required for the costing exercise.</p><p><strong>Quality assurance</strong> provides  confidence that:</p><ul><li>the results are trustworthy in that they reflect  the ground rules, assumptions and requirements of the costing exercise</li><li>there are no calculation errors</li></ul><p><strong>Validation</strong> ensures that the results reflect the real  world by demonstrating that the results are reasonable when compared to past  performance, comparable or historical examples, independent estimates, or  recognized benchmarks.</p><p>Some activities that can form part of this step are:</p><ul><li>checking for calculation errors and  inconsistencies</li><li>assessing whether the costing process was applied  appropriately</li><li>reviewing and challenging the assumptions used  to generate the results</li><li>comparing the data and results from similar  initiatives, activities or data sources</li><li>cross-checking the costing exercise against  recognized benchmarks or authoritative sources and explaining material  differences</li><li>performing an independent estimate</li></ul><p>For Cabinet submissions, the chief financial officer attestation,  as outlined in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27256"><em>Guideline on Chief Financial Officer  Attestation for Cabinet Submissions</em></a>, forms an important part of this  step.</p></section><section><header><h3>Step 7: communicate the results</h3></header><p>Effective communication is crucial to the success of a  costing exercise as it explains the results to audiences unfamiliar with the  initiative or activity, thereby promoting informed decision-making and the  transparent disclosure of financial risk. Communication tools may include  briefing notes and slide decks that incorporate visuals, such as figures 1, 3, and 4 of this guide.</p><p>The costing process and results should be documented. One  common form of documentation is a cost report. A cost report describes the costing  process, ground rules, assumptions, data sources and results. Its audience may  include future costing practitioners and those responsible for challenge  functions, evaluations, and audits.</p><p>A cost report also ensures that lessons learned can be  captured and retained to improve future costing exercises, as well as periodic  reviews of the implementation of the costing process across an organization.</p><p>The documentation should communicate any limitations of the  analysis and uncertainty or subjectivity about source data and assumptions. </p></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. Costing approaches and techniques</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>When considering how to determine uncertainty, risk and cost  in <a href="#step5">step 5</a> of the costing process, it is  important to weigh the benefits of the costing information against the time and  effort required to produce this information.</p><p>The tools used to calculate costs can range from a simple  table of expected annual costs to a complex computer model that uses cost estimating relationships to assess the results of  thousands of scenarios. Data availability and the maturity of an initiative or  activity can influence the costing approach or technique selected. </p><p>Costing approaches describe different ways that costing  techniques are applied to determine costs. Costing techniques describe the  basic methods that are used to determine the value of a single cost element. A  single costing exercise may use multiple approaches and multiple techniques.</p><section><header><h3 id="costingapproaches">Costing approaches</h3></header><p>The following are three types of costing approaches, which  apply costing techniques to produce credible costing information.</p><section><header><h4>Top-down</h4></header><p>A top-down approach assesses the total costs of an initiative  or activity and divides the assessed costs into smaller cost elements. A  top-down approach is often used when costing information is most appropriately assessed  at the highest level compared to lower levels. For instance, at the early  stages of an initiative or activity, it may be difficult to gather the data and  evidence required to calculate the value of cost elements in more detail. Furthermore,  a top-down approach may require less effort and be just as credible.</p><p>An example of a top-down approach is estimating the cost of a  project management office at an early stage of a project, where it is assumed  to be a percentage of total project cost based on other analogous data.</p></section><section><header><h4>Bottom-up</h4></header><p>A bottom-up approach determines  the cost of each cost element, the sum of which is the total cost of the initiative  or activity. This approach involves using costing techniques to determine a cost for each cost element based on actual data. Bottom-up approaches are best  employed when determining the costs at later stages of an initiative or  activity when detailed information is available.</p><p>An engineering build-up approach  may sometimes be considered a bottom-up approach.</p><p>An example of a bottom-up approach  could be estimating the cost of a project management office by determining all  the individual salary and non-salary cost elements and estimating a cost for  each of them.</p></section><section><header><h4>Activity-based costing</h4></header><p>An activity-based costing (ABC) approach uses actual  or historical data and applies costing techniques to allocate costs. An ABC  approach captures all costs related to an initiative by breaking down costs by activity  and related resources consumed to produce costing information. Once the  relevant breakdown is determined, costs may be described as direct, indirect,  variable, fixed and/or step.</p><p>ABC supports decision-making by organizing and improving the  visibility of costs, which identifies the resource requirements of a given  activity and links them to a department’s overarching objectives and results. Another  benefit of the approach is that activities are linked to cost drivers, so the  impact on resources due to changes to activities can be readily assessed.</p></section><section><header><h4>How approaches can be combined</h4></header><p>Multiple approaches may be combined in a costing exercise to  determine the costs of an initiative or activity.</p><p>For example, a new initiative to deliver a capital asset (such  as a bridge) may use:</p><ul><li>a top-down approach to determine design and  construction costs</li><li>a bottom-up approach to determine detailed  project management requirements (for example, full-time equivalent costs and  non-salary costs)</li><li>an activity-based costing approach to determine  the internal services required to enable successful delivery</li></ul></section></section><section><header><h3>Costing techniques</h3></header><p>There are two primary techniques used  to determine the cost of a cost element.</p><section><header><h4>Analogous  technique </h4></header><p>An analogous technique uses data  from a comparable initiative, activity or cost element as the basis for  determining costs. Adjustments are then made using scaling parameters that  represent differences in size, performance, technology, complexity and other  factors.</p><p>An analogous technique is best used  when historical data is available and is closely aligned to cost elements. It  is often used during the early stages of an initiative or activity when there  is little data and evidence to inform the use of more advanced techniques. It  is best to use a parametric technique for complex initiatives, activities or  cost elements that do not have straightforward analogies.</p><p>An analogous technique often relies  on expert opinion to adjust historical costs so that they approximate the total  cost of an initiative or activity. If possible, the adjustments should be quantitative  rather than qualitative to avoid subjective judgments.</p><p>The costing practitioner should  document the assumptions and data sources used with this technique.</p></section><section><header><h4>Parametric  technique</h4></header><p>A parametric technique applies  statistical analysis to data from similar initiatives and activities to develop  a cost estimating relationship (CER) that is used to generate costing  information. A CER is an equation that determines the numerical value of a  given cost element using an established relationship with one or more independent  cost drivers. The relationship may be mathematically simple, such as a proportion,  ratio or rate, or it may involve a complex equation or method, such as a  regression analysis. CERs should be applicable to the cost element and appropriate  for the range of data being considered.</p><p>A parametric technique in costing relies  on data from many initiatives or activities. In general, a parametric technique  should be applied when there is data available from several historical initiatives,  activities or cost elements that have relationships based on cost drivers. A parametric  technique is often used when an initiative or activity has progressed beyond  the early stages and detailed information is known about cost drivers.</p><p>The costing practitioner should  document the related mathematical methods, statistics, assumptions,  normalization processes and data sources used for this technique.</p><p>Figure 5 shows the cost  estimating relationship between a cost driver and cost. The graph shows that  the cost driver has a direct influence on cost such that an increase in the  quantity of the cost driver results in an increase in cost.</p><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 5: representation of a cost estimating relationship</strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol-cont/32600-fig5-eng.png" alt="Figure 5: representation of a cost estimating relationship. Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary class="wb-toggle">Figure 5 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 5 is a scatter plot graph.  A cost driver is indicated on the X-axis and cost is indicated on the Y-axis.</p><p>The scatter plot is populated  with dots that represent data points and a line of best fit. The line is positively  and strongly correlated with the data points, which tightly surround the line  of best fit in an upward fashion.</p></details></figure></section></section><section><header><h3 id="furtherconsiderations">Further considerations</h3></header><p>Costing practitioners often use data from other initiatives  and activities and apply analogous or parametric techniques in order to  determine cost. However, at times, actual data about costs or trends can be  used to determine future costs for the same initiative or activity. In these  cases, the analogous or parametric technique may also be known as <strong>extrapolation  from actuals.</strong></p><p>An example of extrapolation from actuals using an analogous  technique is an assumption that the cost to perform an activity in the future will  be the same as the cost of the activity in the past. An example of extrapolation  from actuals using a parametric technique is an “estimate at completion” from earned  value management.</p><section><header><h4>Expert opinion</h4></header><p>Expert opinion uses an expert or group of experts to determine  costs without a basis in an identifiable data source. Expert opinion tends to  produce subjective costing information and produces results that are less  reliable than other costing techniques due to an increased risk of cognitive bias.  When possible, costing practitioners should favour techniques that use actual  or historical data instead of expert opinion.</p><p>Expert opinion can be useful in the absence of other viable  alternatives. The subjectivity of expert opinion can be mitigated through  comparisons to other initiatives or activities, independent estimates, or an uncertainty  analysis. Qualitative evidence from subject matter experts can be transformed  into data by using robust qualitative and quantitative research techniques.</p><p>When expert opinion is used to determine costs, the costing  practitioner should document the method used to obtain the expert opinion (for example,  interviews) along with the credentials, experience, and position titles of the  experts consulted.</p><p>The use of experts to interpret and provide context to data  can improve the quality of the analogous or parametric technique used. It is  good practice to engage experts when using costing techniques. When experts  inform the use of data-driven techniques, consulting experts is not considered using  an expert opinion.</p></section></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha9">9. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Costing is an essential component of many GC activities and,  consequently, is related in some way to most policy instruments in the GC. The  following sets out key references that should be read in conjunction with this  guide:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32502"><em>Directive on Charging and Special Financial Authorities</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32690"><em>Directive on the Management of Materiel</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32692"><em>Directive on the Management of Procurement</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32594"><em>Directive on the Management of Projects and Programmes</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32691"><em>Directive on the Management of Real Property</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/innovation/greening-government/strategy.html"><em>Greening  Government Strategy</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27256"><em>Guideline on Chief Financial Officer Attestation for Cabinet  Submissions</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593"><em>Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=31300"><em>Policy on Results</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=19422"><em>Framework for the Management of Risk</em></a></li><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/S-8.4/index.html"><em>Service Fees Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/treasury-board-submissions.html">Treasury  Board Submissions</a></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha10">10. Community of practice</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>The <a href="https://www.gcpedia.gc.ca/wiki/Costing_Community_of_Practice_(CCoP)_/_Communaut%C3%A9_de_pratique_sur_l%27%C3%A9tablissement_des_co%C3%BBts_(CPEC)">Costing  Community of Practice</a> GCpedia page (accessible  only on the Government of Canada network) exists to connect, support and engage  costing practitioners across the GC.</p><p>Additional  guidance, tools, templates and training that expand on the concepts presented  in this guide are available:</p><ul><li>on the  Costing Community of Practice GCpedia page</li><li>through  professional associations, academic institutions and other GC publications</li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha11">11. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Members of the public may contact the Treasury Board of  Canada Secretariat (TBS) Public Enquiries at <a href="mailto:questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca">questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> if they have  questions about this guide.</p><p>Individuals from departments, agencies, or other  governmental organizations should direct enquiries about this guide to the relevant  unit in their organization.</p><p>For interpretation of this guide, relevant units should  contact the Costing Centre of Expertise at <a href="mailto:CCE-CEEC@tbs-sct.gc.ca">CCE-CEEC@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a>.</p></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix A: common applications</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>The following are some of the ways that costing information  can be applied to support various types of decisions and assessments.</p><section><header><h3>Decisions about different courses of action</h3></header><p>Costing information can support decisions about whether to:</p><ul><li>purchase, develop, subcontract, or lease an  asset or service</li><li>retain, dispose or divest of an asset</li><li>retain or replace an existing service provider</li><li>purchase an asset off-the-shelf, engage in a  contract with the supplier to modify an off-the-shelf asset, or design a new asset</li><li>continue (status quo), adjust, or terminate an initiative  or activity</li></ul><p>For example, a costing exercise could support an options  analysis in a Memorandum to Cabinet that compares the cost of developing a new  case management system with the cost of customizing and maintaining an existing  commercial off-the-shelf asset.</p></section><section><header><h3>A legislative or policy change</h3></header><p>When decision-makers are considering a change in legislation  or policy, they can use costing information to:</p><ul><li>assess different delivery, design and  implementation options</li><li>understand the cost impact of the change</li><li>consider whether adequate resources are  available to implement and sustain the change</li></ul><p>For example, a costing exercise could be used to estimate  the cost of changing the eligibility criteria for a social program or benefit.</p></section><section><header><h3>Decisions about offering a new initiative or  activity</h3></header><p>When decision-makers  consider whether to offer a new initiative or activity, they can use costing  information to:</p><ul><li>identify  new costs</li><li>identify  existing costs that would be impacted</li><li>identify  the life-cycle costs of supporting assets and services</li><li>inform  affordability and cost effectiveness analyses</li></ul><p>For example, a costing exercise could be used to estimate  how offering a new service might increase the cost of internal services, such  as communications and legal services.</p></section><section><header><h3>Level-of-service decisions</h3></header><p>When decision-makers  consider what level of service to provide or whether to discontinue a service, they  can use costing information to:</p><ul><li>understand  the cost implications of a new service, changes to an existing service or of  maintaining the same level of service (status quo)</li><li>inform  cost-benefit analyses</li></ul><p>For example, a costing exercise could be used to estimate  the cost of reducing wait times at border crossings.</p></section><section><header><h3>Charging and cost-recovery decisions</h3></header><p>Decision-makers can  use costing information to help identify the full cost of delivery. The full  cost of delivery informs how much to charge.</p><p>When decision-makers  must make determinations about cost recovery, they should consider the costs  involved in the:</p><ul><li>provision  of a service</li><li>use of  a facility</li><li>conferral, by means of a  licence, permit or other authorization, of a right or privilege </li><li>provision of a product </li><li>recovery,  in whole or in part, of costs that are incurred in relation to a regulatory  scheme</li></ul><p>For example, a  costing exercise could inform the amounts to charge for:</p><ul><li>interdepartmental  enterprise services</li><li>patent  application processing and patent administration</li></ul></section><section><header><h3>Investment decisions</h3></header><p>When decision-makers consider whether to undertake an  investment, they can use costing information to understand the long-term  financial implications of their decision. Costing information also supports the  understanding of the financial obligations imposed by the investment and the  cost variances that are incurred over the entire life cycle of an asset or  service.</p><p>For example, a costing exercise could be used to estimate  the cost of a building that is constructed and maintained by the Government of  Canada.</p></section><section><header><h3>Contracting and procurement decisions</h3></header><p>When decision-makers must decide which option represents best  value, they can use costing information to inform contract negotiations and the  contracting authority required.</p><p>For example, a costing exercise could be used to estimate  the cost uncertainty and risk associated with a particular initiative or  activity, which would subsequently inform price negotiations and risk-sharing  considerations.</p></section><section><header><h3>Decisions about reorganizations</h3></header><p>When decision-makers consider a reorganization that impacts  existing organizations or the creation of a new organization, they can use  costing information to inform the:</p><ul><li>parties involved about the cost implications</li><li>resulting reference levels</li></ul><p>For example, a costing exercise could be used to estimate  the cost of transferring responsibility for a program, including the costs of a  program, as well as the indirect costs of internal services that support the  program.</p></section><section><header><h3>Assessments of results</h3></header><p>When assessing the  impacts of an initiative or activity, both financial and non-financial elements  should be considered. As part of the assessment, costing information can  inform:</p><ul><li>evaluations that assess the efficiency of an  initiative or activity</li><li>ongoing monitoring of an initiative or activity</li></ul></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix B: definitions</h2><div class="pol-content"><dl class="dl-horizontal"><dt class="small"><strong>assumptions</strong></dt><dd>The underpinning hypotheses upon which a costing exercise is  built and from which the costing requirements are drawn. Assumptions use  evidence to make judgments to fill the gaps between input data and the results  of the costing exercise. They are deemed to be true in the absence of facts and  supported by data when possible. An  example of an assumption might be the size of the team required to manage a  program before an organizational chart is approved.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>complexity</strong></dt><dd>The degree to which an initiative or activity is difficult  to understand, analyze, verify and assess, or the degree to which it consists  of many different and connected parts.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>contingency</strong></dt><dd>An amount that is established in a costing exercise to allow  for items, conditions, or events for which the state, occurrence, or effects  are uncertain, and that experience has shown would most likely result in  additional costs. The objective of establishing a contingency is to inform  realistic budgets based on the risk assessment and the risk tolerance of  decision-makers, which can vary by initiative or activity.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost</strong></dt><dd>The monetary value of the resources (for example, human, physical)  consumed to achieve a certain end.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost breakdown structure (CBS)</strong></dt><dd>A hierarchical structure that is used to break down costs  into lower levels of detail so that the total cost related to an initiative or  activity can be produced. To construct a CBS, overarching cost elements are  subdivided into smaller cost elements to produce multiple levels of hierarchy.  The subdivided cost elements are called “children” and they should be equal to  the sum of the related cost elements at the next level up, which is called the  “parent.”</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost driver</strong></dt><dd>A variable that has a significant influence on the cost of  an initiative or activity. From a cost-modelling perspective, cost drivers  represent the input variables that have the greatest impact on the output cost.  When applicable, cost drivers are used as the input parameters for cost  estimating relationships.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost estimating relationship (CER)</strong></dt><dd>A mathematical relationship that defines cost as a function  of one or more parameters, such as performance, operating characteristics and  physical characteristics. A CER uses cost drivers as input parameters to  predict a future cost.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost report</strong></dt><dd>A report that describes the costing process, ground rules,  assumptions, data sources, results, and lessons learned for future costing  practitioners, challenge functions, evaluators, performance measurement  practitioners and auditors. Cost reports should be prepared for all costing  exercises.
<p>A cost report should:</p><ul><li>provide a thorough understanding of how the  costing information was produced</li><li>allow readers to assess the credibility and  maturity of the costing information</li><li>be able to withstand scrutiny and an audit</li><li>allow a third party to reproduce the results</li></ul></dd><dt class="small"><strong>costing</strong></dt><dd>Costing consists of the calculation of resources (for  example, human, physical, financial) consumed to achieve a certain end. Costing  is used to support decision-making, such as determining the cost of providing a  service or the cost of acquiring capital equipment. Costing in the Government  of Canada includes: 
<ul><li>cost accounting, which emphasizes the allocation  of costs (for example, direct and indirect)</li><li>cost estimating, which emphasizes forecasting  costs and the associated uncertainty and risk</li></ul></dd><dt class="small"><strong>costing exercise</strong></dt><dd>The use of a standardized process and the application of  costing approaches and techniques to determine costs.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>costing information</strong></dt><dd>The value of the resources (human, physical or financial)  consumed to serve a specific purpose. The most useful costing information is  credible, as defined in <a href="#cha6">Credible costing information</a> in this guide.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>costing practitioner</strong></dt><dd>A person who performs work related to costing.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost risk</strong></dt><dd>Cost risk is something that may or may not occur and that  may increase or decrease cost. Considering cost risk involves assessing the  probability of a risk materializing and the impact on cost if it does. An  example of cost risk is a potential mechanical breakdown in a manufacturing  environment.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>cost uncertainty</strong></dt><dd>Cost uncertainty stems from  fluctuations in costs. The exact impact of cost  uncertainty is unknown due to imperfect information. However,  uncertainty can be estimated using data. An example of cost uncertainty is  the future foreign exchange rate for materials or services procured in foreign  currency.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>deterministic estimate (point estimate)</strong></dt><dd>A single value that represents the proposed cost of an  initiative or activity selected from within a range of potential outcomes. A  deterministic estimate can be adjusted for cost uncertainty and risk by adding  a contingency based on a cost uncertainty and risk analysis. A deterministic  estimate is also known as a point estimate.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>expert opinion</strong></dt><dd>A claim, made by an individual or group asserted to be  sufficiently knowledgeable in a subject, that provides reliable testimony on  the issue at hand. Expert opinion as a costing technique tends to produce subjective  costing information, but it may be useful in the absence of other viable  alternatives. Expert opinion may also be referred to as subject matter expert  opinion.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>ground rules</strong></dt><dd>A prescribed set of conditions that provide guidance to the  direction of a costing exercise. Ground rules often become constraints that  define the boundaries and scope of the costing exercise. For example, a ground  rule for a construction project may be that all materials are to be procured in  Canada</dd><dt class="small"><strong>independent estimate</strong></dt><dd>A costing exercise conducted by a third-party reviewer who  uses different methods and sources of data to develop an estimate and compare  it to the primary estimate. An independent estimate is prepared by an entity  that is not under the supervision, direction, advocacy or control of the people  responsible for developing or acquiring the initiative or activity. An  independent estimate is conducted with objectivity, and such an estimate should  preserve the integrity of a costing exercise by prioritizing the credibility.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>life-cycle costs</strong></dt><dd>All the costs associated with an initiative or activity over  its life cycle, which includes the costs from initial conception and during any  operational periods (for example, operations and maintenance) until the end of  the initiative or activity or the disposal of any assets.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>materiality</strong></dt><dd>The degree to which something is important, relevant or  significant. From a decision-making perspective, an item of information or an  aggregate of items is material if it is probable that the item’s omission or  misstatement could influence or change a decision. For example, a component  that costs $1,000 and is part of a $1 million initiative is not likely to  be considered material. However, a $1 million initiative would be material  for an organization that has a budget of $20 million.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>normalization</strong></dt><dd>The process of removing the effects of external influences  from a set of data to improve consistency and comparability. For example,  adjusting data for inflation or the value of money over time.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>quality assurance</strong></dt><dd>  An action that includes a verification of the ground rules,  assumptions and requirements of the costing exercise, as well as a quality  check on the calculations in the costing exercise. Quality assurance is focused  on the integrity and appropriateness of the process used to develop the costing  information.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>sensitivity analysis</strong></dt><dd>The repetition of an analysis with different quantitative  values for selected assumptions or cost drivers for the purpose of comparing  the results with the basic analysis. If a small change in the value of an  assumption or cost driver results in a large change in the results, the results  are sensitive to that assumption or cost driver. Sensitivity analysis provides  an analysis of the impact that a change in the most influential cost drivers or  assumptions will have on the overall costs of an initiative or activity.</dd><dt class="small"><strong>validation</strong></dt><dd>An action to ensure that the results of an analysis reflect  the real world by demonstrating that the results are reasonable when compared  to past performance, comparable or historical examples, independent estimates  or recognized benchmarks. Validation is focused on the appropriateness and  accuracy of the result.</dd></dl></div></section></div><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small"></p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>