<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Guide to the Proactive Publication of Contracts</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=32763", title: "Guide to the Proactive Publication of Contracts"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=32763&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2023-06-21",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Guide to the Proactive Publication of Contracts</h1><section class="alert alert-info"><h2>Note to reader</h2><p>The <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14676"><em>Guidelines on the Proactive Disclosure of Contracts</em></a> has been updated and renamed the <em>Guide to the Proactive Publication of Contracts</em>, effective June 30, 2023.</p><p>This guide builds on the requirements for reporting on proactive publication of contracts under Appendix C of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32692"><em>Directive on the Management of Procurement</em></a>. The guide includes additional requirements to strengthen guidance on the following:</p><ul><li>updated requirements for monitoring of proactive publication of contract information under subsection 4.5 of this guide in accordance with:
    <ul><li>subsections 4.1.2.13 and 4.1.2.16 of the <em>Directive on the Management of Procurement,</em></li><li>subsection C.2 of Appendix C of the <em>Directive on the Management of Procurement;</em></li></ul></li><li>additional guidance on reporting considerations for proactive publication of contract information subject to a National Security Exception under subsection 4.4.9 and Appendix E of this guide;</li><li>amended guidance on Appendix A data elements numbered 37 to 40 in accordance with subsection 4.4.9 and Appendix E of this guide;</li><li>effective October 1, 2023, additional reporting requirements under Appendix D of this guide for contract descriptions of certain service contracts valued at $1 million or more.</li></ul></section><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Effective date</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.1</span><p>This version of the guide takes effect on  <time datetime="2023-06-30" class="nowrap">June  30, 2023</time>.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">1.2</span><p>This guide replaces the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=14676"><em>Guidelines on  the Proactive Disclosure of Contracts</em></a> dated <time datetime="2022-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2022</time>.</p></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Purpose</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">2.1</span><p>To provide guidance to managers and functional  specialists on the identification, collection, reporting and proactive publication  of contract information.</p></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Context</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.1</span><p>As part of Canada’s second Action Plan on Open  Government, the Government of Canada has committed to the disclosure of  contracting data via a centralized, machine-readable database available to the  public. This commitment reinforces the proactive publication of contracts, which  reflects broader government commitments to transparency and strengthened  accountability within the public sector originally announced in Budget 2004.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.2</span><p>Contracting data is gathered for the purposes of:</p><ul><li>Strengthening transparency of the procurement  process for Canadians to hold their government to account;</li><li>Meeting trade agreement procurement reporting  obligations; and</li><li>Evaluating policy instruments.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.3</span><p>This guide supports the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32692"><em>Directive on  the Management of Procurement</em></a>. Subsection C.2.1 of Appendix C  of the directive requires the senior designated officials for the management of  procurement to proactively publish contract information in accordance with Part 2  of the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>. Subsection C.2.3  also requires departments to report on the contract data elements in the data  format prescribed by the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat (TBS). </p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla3.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">3.4</span><p>This guide also supports the proactive publication of  contract information requirements for government entities and Ministers’  offices under the <em>Access to Information Act</em> and any  associated policies, directives or guidelines. Sections 77 and 86  of the Act requires Ministers’ offices and government entities to proactively  publish information on contracts with a value of over $10,000, a contract  amendment when it modifies the contract value to exceed $10,000, and amendments  to contracts that increase or decrease the value of the contract by more than  $10,000.</p></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Reporting guidance</h2><div class="pol-content"><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="sec4.1">4.1 Identification of contracts to be  included for proactive publication</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.1</span><p>Subsection C.2.4.1 of Appendix C of the <em>Directive  on the Management of Procurement</em> requires quarterly proactive  publication of information on the following:</p><ul><li>A  contract when its value is over $10,000; </li><li>A  positive or negative amendment when its value is over $10,000; and</li><li>A positive  amendment when it modifies the initial value of a contract to an amended  contract value that is over $10,000.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.2</span><p>Subsection C.2.5 of Appendix C of the <em>Directive on the Management of Procurement</em> requires annual reporting, on a calendar year basis, to Public Services and  Procurement Canada (PSPC) at <a href="mailto:ncr.gwprs@pwgsc.gc.ca">ncr.gwprs@pwgsc.gc.ca</a> and cc: <a href="mailto:ZZPDCDC@tbs-sct.gc.ca">ZZPDCDC@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> on the following:</p><ul><li>A contract when its value is $10,000 and under;  and</li><li>A positive or negative amendment when its value  is $10,000 and under.</li></ul></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.3</span><p>Subsection C.2.5.2 of Appendix C of the <em>Directive on the Management of Procurement</em> requires annual proactive publication, on a calendar year basis, on the volume  and cumulative dollar value of a contract or positive or negative amendment  when its value is $10,000 or less. In addition, the proactive publication of  information on the volume and cumulative dollar value of all acquisition card  transactions regardless of dollar value is required.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.4</span><p>A series of amendments to a contract made in one  reporting period may be reported as one amendment. Alternatively, an amendment  may be reported separately if this is the standard practice in the department.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.5</span><p>Non-financial amendments do not need to be reported,  except when it is in the public interest to do so.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.6</span><p>A contract option, when exercised, may be reported as  an amendment. Alternatively, the full value of a contract, including options,  may be reported at the time of contract award.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.7</span><p>A call-up against a standing offer or supply  arrangement should be reported as a contract. </p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.8</span><p>A standing offer agreement and a supply arrangement  agreement are not procurement contracts but are to be reported for the purpose  of transparency. Such agreements must be reported either on the Open Government  Portal or on a public website. </p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.1.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.1.9</span><p>For contracts with task authorizations,<sup id="fn1-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn1"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>1</a></sup> the full potential value of the contract may be reported upon contract award  unless the full value is not expected to be used. In the latter situation, each  task authorization may be reported individually. When a contract includes a  fixed deliverable and another deliverable that requires a task authorization,  the department may report the contract and task authorizations in any manner  that is transparent.</p></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="sec4.2">4.2 Reporting considerations for proactive publication of contract information</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.1</span><p>In accordance with Part 2 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, departments  are required to proactively publish information on contracts or positive and  negative amendments valued at over $10,000 with only very limited exceptions. A  department is not required, and in some instances is not permitted, pursuant to  section 80 and section 90 of the Act, to proactively publish information  about contracts that would properly be withheld in response to a request under  Part 1 of the <em>Access to Information  Act</em>.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.2</span><p>When a department determines that information about  a contract should not be proactively published under subsection 4.2.1 of this  guide, the department is still required, according to Part 2 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, to proactively  publish those portions of contract information that do not contain or can reasonably  be severed from information that would be withheld in response to a request  under Part 1 of the Act.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.3</span><p>The following would usually be excluded from  reporting, unless they constitute contracts under the <em>Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments</em>: </p><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Information  pertaining to memoranda of understanding with other levels of government and  foreign governments; or</li><li>Information  pertaining to service level agreements between federal departments or with  Crown corporations.</li></ol></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.2.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.2.4</span><p>When a department excludes a contract from  obligations that pertain to government procurement in Canada’s trade agreements  by invoking a national security exception, information about the contract may  still be subject to the proactive publication of contract requirements under  the <em>Access to Information Act</em>. Departments are to consider the  underlying rationale for invoking the national security exception as part of  the determination of whether the publication of the contract information, in  whole or in part, would properly be withheld in response to a request under  Part 1 of the Act, pursuant to section 80 and section 90 of the  Act. An example of this subsection is:</p><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>If a national security exception is invoked to exempt a contract from competitive solicitation requirements, as permitted by Canada’s trade agreements, but information on the procurement was published, such as a public tendering notice on the Government Electronic Tendering System. Departments would be expected to proactively publish information on the contract, unless there is another underlying rationale that would preclude information on the contract from being reported. If there are questions about whether information on a contract should be reported, departments should consult with departmental legal services and departmental officials responsible for the <em>Access to Information Act</em> for guidance before making the appropriate decision.</li></ol></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="sec4.3">4.3 Collection of contracting data  elements</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.3.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.3.1</span><p>The data elements in appendices A and B  were developed to provide consistency to the public. In accordance with  subsection C.2.4 of Appendix C of the <em>Directive on the Management  of Procurement</em>, departments are to follow the recommended approach identified  in appendices A and B for each data element if possible. If use  of the recommended approach is not possible, a department may use a standard  practice in the department for reporting. To provide consistency to the public,  it is recommended that departments move away from departmental standards and  move toward the recommended reporting standard over time. </p></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="sec4.4">4.4 Publication and reporting of  contracts</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.1</span><p>Starting for calendar year 2017, departments must  report their contracting data on the Open Government Portal. When PSPC, Shared  Services Canada (SSC) or another department or Crown corporation issues a  contract on a department’s behalf, the client department should report the  contract. PSPC and SSC will assist client organizations by providing any  information that they have about such contracts through the Procurement Policy  Division’s GCpedia page within five business days after the end of the quarter.  In addition, the PSPC or SSC contracting authority is to provide a copy of each  contract or amendment to the client department at the time of award.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.2</span><p>For PSPC or SSC multi-departmental contracts,  departments are to report on their portion only as either a contract or  amendment based on how it was recorded in their departmental procurement or  financial systems. For a standing offer agreement or supply arrangement  agreement, it is recommended that the agreement be reported by the department  that authorizes the agreement.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.3"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.3</span><p>Reporting is to occur for:</p><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Quarterly proactive publication of contract data  elements as detailed in Appendix A for contracts and positive and negative  amendments over $10,000, within 30 days after the end of each of the first  three quarters of a fiscal year (April to June, July to September and October  to December) and within 60 days after the end of the fourth quarter; </li><li>Annual proactive publication of aggregate contract data  elements as detailed in Appendix B for contracts and positive and negative  amendments $10,000 and under, by May 30 of the following calendar year;  and</li><li>Annual reporting to PSPC of contract data elements as  detailed in Appendix A for contracts and positive and negative amendments  $10,000 and under, by May 30 of the following calendar year.</li></ol></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.4"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.4</span><p>When the above dates for posting fall on a weekend  or statutory holiday, departments may proactively publish information by the  last business day before the weekend or holiday in question. </p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.5"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.5</span><p>A contract or amendment not reported in the  reporting period in which it was awarded may be reported in the subsequent  reporting period, or as soon as practicable. Any contract or amendment included  in a reporting period after its publication, should clearly indicate the  omission within the comments data element (refer to Appendix C).</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.6"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.6</span><p>Information proactively published in one reporting  period can be modified for that reporting period only when a material error was  made in the originally published data. Any modified information is recommended  to be clearly indicated as such within the <em>comments</em> data (refer to Appendix C).</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.7"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.7</span><p>Departments are to provide a nil report for any  quarter or calendar year in which no contract or amendment is reported.  Departments are to populate the reporting period and the nil report data  elements within the reporting template. </p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.8"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.8</span><p>Departments are to report using the data format  under the new and revised Appendix A data fields as soon as  administratively possible, but no later than the fourth quarter of fiscal year  2021–22 for contracts and amendments awarded starting January 1, 2022. In  the interim, departments are to continue to use the previous data format to  report on the existing data fields until they are able to change to the new  data format.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.4.9"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.4.9</span><p>Departments and agencies listed in Appendix E  are to include the data elements 37 to 40 identified in Appendix A in  the proactive publication of contract information reports when migrating to a  new or upgraded departmental procurement or financial system, if not already included.</p></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sub"><header><h3 id="sec4.5">4.5 Monitoring of proactive publication  of contract information</h3></header><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.5.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.5.1</span><p>In accordance with subsections 4.1.2.13 and  4.1.2.16 and section C.2 of Appendix C of the <em>Directive on the  Management of Procurement</em>, senior designated officials responsible for the  management of procurement are responsible for establishing risk-based internal  controls to ensure that the data included in the proactive publication of  contracts is materially accurate, complete, and proactively published in a  timely manner in accordance with Part 2 of the <em>Access to Information  Act </em>and any associated policies, directives or guidelines, including this  guide.</p></li><li class="pol-cla" id="cla4.5.2"><span class="pol-cla-id">4.5.2</span><p>Consideration  should be given to including the following elements as part of the risk-based internal  controls for proactive publication:</p><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Documenting  the procedures for proactive publication and the associated risk-based internal  controls as part of the Departmental Procurement Management Framework;</li><li>Ensuring  periodical risk-based reviews (such as sampling) of proactively published  contract information to assess whether the published information is accurate  and complete; and</li><li>Requiring  approval of the senior designated official for the management of procurement (or  a higher authority) of the data prior to proactive publication.</li></ol></li></ul></div></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><p><strong>Relevant legislation:</strong></p><ul><li><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/a-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-5.5/"><em>Federal Accountability Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/f-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/sor-87-402/FullText.html"><em>Government Contracts Regulations</em></a></li></ul><p><strong>Treasury Board policy instruments:</strong></p><ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32593"><em>Policy on the Planning and Management of Investments</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32692"><em>Directive on the Management of Procurement</em></a> (which replaced the rescinded <em>Contracting Policy</em> as of May 13, 2022) </li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32499"><em>Directive on Accounting Standards</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32529"><em>Directive on Accounting Standards</em>: GC 5000 Recording Financial Transactions in the Accounts of Canada</a></li></ul><p><strong>Treasury Board standards:</strong></p><ul><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=23601&amp;section=text"><em>Standard on Web Accessibility</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=25845"><em>Standard on Vendor Record</em></a></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><ul class="pol-cla list-unstyled"><li class="pol-cla" id="cla6.1"><span class="pol-cla-id">6.1</span><p>For interpretation of this guide, contact <a href="mailto:questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca">TBS Public Enquiries</a>.</p></li></ul></div></section></div><hr /><div class="pol-app mrgn-tp-md"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appA">Appendix A – data elements for annual reporting to Public  Services and Procurement Canada (PSPC) and quarterly proactive publication on  the Open Government Portal</h2><div class="pol-content"><section><header><h3>1. Reference Number / Numéro de référence</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>A unique identifier given to each line item in the reporting template.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>When publishing  quarterly: C-YYYY‑YYYY‑Q#‑#####. <br />
  For  example,  C-2016-2017‑Q4‑00001. This sequence will  continue for each line item (that  is, C-2016‑2017‑Q4‑00001, C‑2016‑2017‑Q4‑00002, C‑2016‑2017‑Q4‑00003…). </li><li>When reporting to  Public Services and Procurement Canada: C-YYYY‑#####. <br />
  For  example, C‑2017‑00001. This  sequence will continue for each line item (that is,  C‑2017‑00001,  C-2017‑00002,  C‑2017-00003…).</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for  all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>2. Procurement Identification Number / Numéro  d’identification d’approvisionnement</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that the procurement identification number be the contract number. Alternatively,  the procurement identification number may be the commitment number or requisition  number if this is the standard practice in the department.</dd><dt><strong>Data format:</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>3. Vendor Name / Nom du fournisseur</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that the vendor name be the legal name of the contractor, as  indicated on the contract. Alternatively, the vendor name may be the name in  the financial system if this is the standard practice in the department.</dd><dt><strong>Data format:</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>4. Vendor Postal Code / Code postal du fournisseur</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that this field be populated with the first three digits of the postal code for the vendor identified in the contract. </li><li>Alternatively, the vendor postal code may be the first three digits of the postal code identified in the procurement or financial system if this is the standard practice in the department. </li><li>This field is to be populated with “NA” if the vendor is located outside of Canada, as the value “NA” for this field indicates not applicable.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. For example, A1A for Canadian postal code.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>5. Buyer Name / Nom de l’acheteur</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that the field be  populated with the name of the buyer, as indicated on the original contract or,  alternatively, the individual responsible for the procurement at the  department.</li><li>For the establishment of a standing offer  or supply arrangement agreement, it is recommended that this field be populated  with the name of the buyer that issued the original standing offer or supply  arrangement agreement.</li><li>For a call-up contract against a  standing offer or supply arrangement, this field should be the name of the  buyer identified in the original call-up contract.</li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, this field may be populated with the name of the buyer  indicated in the original contract or in the individual task authorization.</li><li>For amendments, it is recommended that  this field be populated with the value “NA,” as the value “NA” for this field  indicates not applicable.</li><li>For contracts awarded by PSPC or Shared  Services Canada (SSC) on behalf of the client department, it is recommended  that this field be populated with the name of the PSPC or SSC contracting  authority. If this is not available, indicate the values, “PSPC-SPAC” or “SSC-SPC” as applicable.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphabetical  characters; free text. Include the buyer name and use the following format:  last name, first name. Alternatively, departments may use the following format:  first name last name.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>6. Contract Date / Date du marché</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that the contract  date be the date the contract is awarded by the government. Alternatively, the  contract date may be the hard commitment date (the date that the financial  commitment is recorded in the departmental financial system) if this is the  standard practice in the department.</li><li>It is recommended that the contract  date for a contract with task authorizations be the date that the contract is  awarded (or the hard commitment date) for the contract. When the full value of  the contract with task authorizations is likely not to be used, the contract  date for each task authorization may be the date that each task authorization  is issued (or the hard commitment date).</li><li>It is recommended that the contract  date for an amended contract or the exercising of an option be the date that  the contract is awarded (or the hard commitment date).</li><li>It is recommended that the contract  date for a confirming order be the date of the verbal contract for goods,  services or an amendment. If the date of the verbal contract cannot be  determined, the contract date may be the date that the confirming order is issued.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>YYYY-MM-DD</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>7. Economic Object Code / Code d’article économique</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that this field be  populated with the contract’s numeric economic object code. Economic object  codes are listed in the <a href="http://www.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/recgen/pceaf-gwcoa/index-eng.html">government-wide  chart of accounts</a>. The use of accurate economic object codes is important for  maintaining the integrity of the Public Accounts of Canada. Departments are to  ensure that all expenditures are coded appropriately in accordance with the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32529"><em>Directive  on Accounting Standards</em>: GC 5000 Recording Financial  Transactions in the Accounts of Canada</a>. </li><li>For standing  offers and supply arrangement agreements, this field may be populated with the  data value “NA” as the value “NA” for this field means not applicable. </li><li>When a contract  involves more than one economic object, it is recommended that the economic  object associated with the largest dollar value be used. A department may use a  different approach if this is the standard practice in the department. </li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>8. Description of Work English / Description du travail Anglais</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this field be populated with the economic object code’s text  description as listed in the <a href="http://www.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/recgen/pceaf-gwcoa/index-eng.html">government-wide  chart of accounts</a>. For standing  offers and supply arrangement agreements, this field may be populated with the  commodity code’s text description used by the federal government for  procurement activities.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>9. Description of Work French / Description du travail Français</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this field be populated with the economic object code’s text  description as listed in the <a href="http://www.tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca/recgen/pceaf-gwcoa/index-eng.html">government-wide  chart of accounts</a>. For standing  offers and supply arrangement agreements, this field may be populated with the  commodity code’s text description used by the federal government for  procurement activities.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>10. Contract Period Start Date / Date de début du marché</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>For a services or construction services  contract, it is recommended that the contract period start date be the starting  date for the period of time over which the services are provided. </li><li>For a standing offer or supply  arrangement agreement, it is recommended that this field be populated with the  starting date for the period of time over which a call-up may be entered into.</li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, it is recommended that this field be populated with the  starting date for the period of time over the entire contract. For a contract  with task authorizations where the full value of a contract with task  authorizations is likely not to be used, it is recommended for this field to be  populated with the starting date for each task authorization.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>YYYY-MM-DD </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>11. Contract Period End Date or Delivery Date / Date de clôture du marché ou date de livraison</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>For a goods contract, it is recommended  that this field be the date when goods are to be delivered, which may be the  contract period end date. The department may use the last delivery date if the  contract involves multiple items on multiple dates.</li><li>For a services or construction services  contract, it is recommended that this field be the end date for the period of  time over which the services are provided. </li><li>For a standing offer or supply  arrangement agreement, it is recommended that this field be the end date for  the period of time over which a call-up may be entered into.</li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, it is recommended that this field be populated with the end  date for the period of time over the entire contract. For a contract with task  authorizations where the full value of a contract with task authorizations is  likely not to be used, it is recommended for this field to be populated with  the end date for each task authorization.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>YYYY-MM-DD </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>12. Total Contract Value / Valeur totale du marché</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that the total  contract value be the amount of the hard commitment recorded in the  departmental financial system for the contract and all subsequent amendments  regardless of dollar value. It is recommended for this field to be in Canadian  currency and for it to include all applicable taxes. </li><li>For a multi-year contract, it is  recommended for this field to be the total amount of the contract for all  years. </li><li>For a contract amendment, it is  recommended for this field to be the amended contract value. </li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, the full potential value of the contract may be reported upon  contract award unless the full value is not expected to be used. In the latter situation,  each task authorization may be reported individually or cumulatively. When a  contract includes a fixed deliverable, and another deliverable that requires a  task authorization, the department may report the contract and task authorization  in any manner that is transparent.</li><li>The value of this field for the reporting  of a standing offer agreement or supply arrangement agreement is $0.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas are not to be used to populate this data  field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>13. Original Contract Value / Valeur d’origine du marché</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that the original  contract value be the amount of the hard commitment recorded in the  departmental financial system at the time of contract award for a contract or  amended contract. It is recommended for this field to be in Canadian currency  and for it to include all applicable taxes.</li><li>For a multi-year contract, it is  recommended for this field to be the amount at the time of contract award for  the multi-year contract period.</li><li>For a contract option, it is  recommended for this field to be excluded from the original contract value and for  it to be reported at a later date as an amendment when the contract option is  exercised. Alternatively, the full value of a contract including options, may  be reported at the time of contract award.</li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, it is recommended that the original contract value be for the  full amount of the contract rather than the amount specified within the minimum  work guarantee clause. The full potential value of the contract may be reported  in the original contract value unless the full value is not expected to be  used. In the latter situation, each task authorization may be reported  individually or cumulatively. When a contract includes a fixed deliverable and  another deliverable that requires a task authorization, the department may report  the contract and task authorizations in any manner that is transparent.</li><li>The value of this field for the reporting  of a standing offer agreement or supply arrangement agreement should be $0.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example: 23000.23. Formulas are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>14. Contract Amendment Value / Valeur de modification</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>For an amendment, it is recommended  that the contract amendment value be the value of the contract amendment.  Negative amendments should include a minus sign in front of the value. It is  recommended for this field to be in Canadian currency and for it to include all  applicable taxes.</li><li>Multiple amendments to a contract that  takes place in the same fiscal quarter may be reported either individually or  combined. Positive or negative amendments over $10,000 are to be reported  quarterly in accordance with Appendix A. Positive or negative amendments  of $10,000 and under are to be reported annually via email to PSPC in  accordance with Appendix A, and to be reported annually on the Open  Government Portal in accordance with Appendix B. An amendment should be reported  either quarterly or annually. Reporting an amendment both quarterly and  annually would result in double counting of the amendment’s value when  calculating the total contracting activity of an organization.</li><li>When a contract is entered into and  subsequently amended in the same fiscal quarter, the two transactions should be  reported separately. Entry into the contract should be reported as a separate  entry with the value at contract entry in the original contract value and  should not include the value of the contract amendment. The contract amendment  should also be reported as a separate entry with the value of the amendment in  the contract amendment value and the contract entry value in the original  contract value. </li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, when the full value is likely not to be used, the value of any  subsequent task authorization may be reported as an amendment with its value  reported in the contract amendment value.</li><li>A ‘0’ value should be included if there  are no amendments associated with the contract.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas are not to be used to populate this data  field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>15. Comments English / Commentaires en anglais</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>Standardized comments are recommended  to be used (refer to Appendix C). Avoid the use of acronyms within this  field.</li><li>Departments  are to provide a brief description of each contract.</li><li>When a contract involves an economic  object code specified in Appendix D, departments are to fulfill the  reporting requirements specified in Appendix D. </li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>16. Comments French / Commentaires en français</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>Standardized comments are recommended  to be used (refer to Appendix C). Avoid the use of acronyms within this  field.</li><li>Departments are to provide a  brief description of each contract.</li><li>When a contract involves an economic  object code specified in Appendix D, departments are to fulfill the  reporting requirements specified in Appendix D. </li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>17. Additional Comments English / Commentaires  additionnels en anglais</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>The additional comments English field may be populated with additional comments when an organization needs additional capacity to fulfill the reporting requirements under the comments English data field.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>As required, for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments  over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>18. Additional Comments French / <span lang="fr">Commentaires  additionnels en français</span></h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>The  additional comments French field may be populated with additional comments when  an organization needs additional capacity to fulfill the reporting requirements  under the comments French data field.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement</strong></dt><dd>As required, for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments  over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>19. Agreement Type / Type d’accord (information provided for historical purposes  only)</h3></header><p>Departments  are to continue to report under this data field on an interim basis until they  are able to report under the new Appendix A data fields for Trade  Agreement, Comprehensive Land Claims Agreement, and Procurement Strategy for  Aboriginal Business.</p><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended for the agreement  type to identify whether a trade agreement applies to the contract.</li><li>The data values containing the  Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership should  only be used once this trade agreement comes into force and the contract is  covered by the agreement.</li><li>If a procurement is a mandatory or  voluntary set aside under the Procurement Strategy for Aboriginal Business  (PSAB), the value of “A” should be used.</li><li>If the contract is under a  Comprehensive Land Claims Agreement (CLCA), the value of “R” should be used.</li><li>If both CLCA and PSAB applies to the  contract, the value of “BA” should be used.</li><li>Effective July 1, 2020, the North  American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) will no longer be in force. Departments  are to no longer use the data values associated with NAFTA for new procurements  that commence on or after July 1, 2020. </li><li>For existing contracts covered by  NAFTA, it is recommended that departments no longer report on the data value  associated with NAFTA when reporting on an amendment to the contract.  Alternatively, departments may continue to indicate the data value associated  with NAFTA for amendments to existing contracts covered by NAFTA until such  time that the data value is removed from departmental procurement or financial  reporting systems.</li><li>Departments have until January 1,  2022, to migrate to the new method of reporting under the new Trade Agreement  data field. Until migration, it is recommended that departments report on  procurements covered by the Agreement on Trade Continuity between Canada and  the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (TCA) by selecting the  applicable agreement type data values associated with the TCA.</li><li>Note: As the TCA has identical  government procurement obligations as the Canada-European Union Comprehensive  Economic and Trade Agreement (CETA), no additional data values are added to  this data field to address the implementation of the TCA. For the purpose of  proactive publication of contract reporting, if the contract was awarded prior  to the implementation of TCA, then the agreement type data values referencing  CETA and TCA (for example, AG: CETA /  TCA / CFTA /  CHFTA)  should be interpreted as indicating the contract or amendment is covered by  CETA. If the contract date occurs on or after the implementation of the TCA,  then the agreement type data values referencing CETA and TCA should be  interpreted as indicating the contract or amendment is covered by both CETA and  TCA. </li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>This  field must be populated with one of the following values (letters only;  everything after the letters,  including the colon, is for information purposes only): 
					
					<ul><li>0:  None</li><li>Y:  WTO-AGP / NAFTA / CFTA /  CCFTA / CCoFTA /  CHFTA / CPaFTA /  CPFTA / CKFTA (World Trade Organization –  Agreement on Government Procurement /  North  American Free Trade Agreement /  Canadian  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>X:  WTO-AGP / CFTA / CCFTA /  CKFTA  (World Trade Organization – Agreement on Government Procurement / Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>C:  NAFTA / CFTA  (North American Free Trade Agreement /  Canadian  Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>W:  WTO-AGP / CFTA / CCFTA /  CCoFTA / CHFTA /  CPaFTA / CPFTA /  CKFTA  (World Trade Organization – Agreement on Government Procurement / Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>I:  CFTA (Canadian Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>A:  ABSA (PSAB) (Aboriginal Business Set Aside – Procurement Strategy for  Aboriginal Business)</li><li>R:  LCSA (CLCA) (Land Claim Set Aside – Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement)</li><li>S:  NAFTA / CFTA / CCFTA /  CCoFTA / CHFTA /  CPaFTA / CKFTA (North American Free Trade  Agreement / Canadian  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>T:  NAFTA / CFTA / CCFTA /  CCoFTA / CHFTA /  CPaFTA / CPFTA /  CKFTA  (North American Free Trade Agreement /  Canadian  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>V:  CFTA / CCFTA / CKFTA (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>D:  CETA / TCA / CFTA (Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement / Canadian  Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>E:  CETA / TCA / WTO-AGP /  CFTA / CCFTA /  CCoFTA / CHFTA /  CPaFTA / CPFTA /  CKFTA  (Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement /  Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  World  Trade Organization – Agreement on Government Procurement / Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>F:  CETA / TCA / WTO-AGP /  NAFTA / CFTA /  CCFTA / CCoFTA /  CHFTA / CPaFTA / CPFTA / CKFTA (Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement / World Trade Organization – Agreement  on Government Procurement /  North  American Free Trade Agreement /  Canadian  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>AB:  CFTA / CCFTA / CCoFTA /  CHFTA / CPaFTA /  CKFTA  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement) </li><li>AC:  CFTA / CCFTA / CCoFTA /  CHFTA / CPaFTA /  CPFTA / CKFTA  (Canadian  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>AD:  CETA / TCA / WTO-AGP / CFTA / CCFTA /  CKFTA (Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement / Canada-United Kingdom Trade Continuity  Agreement / World  Trade Organization – Agreement on Government Procurement / Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>AF:  CFTA / CHFTA (Canadian Free Trade  Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement) </li><li>AG:  CETA / TCA / CFTA /  CHFTA  (Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement /  Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  Canadian  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>AH:  CKFTA (Canada-South Korea Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>AI:  CFTA / CKFTA (Canadian Free Trade  Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement) </li><li>AJ: CFTA /  NAFTA / CKFTA (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / North American Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>AK: CPTPP (Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for  Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AL: CFTA /  CPTPP  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific  Partnership)</li><li>AM: CFTA /  CETA / TCA /  CPTPP  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  Comprehensive  Economic and Trade Agreement /  Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AN: CFTA /  CHFTA / CETA /  TCA / CPTPP (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras Free Trade Agreement / Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement / Canada-United Kingdom Trade  Continuity Agreement / Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AO: CFTA /  CCFTA / CKFTA /  WTO-AGP / CPTPP (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade Agreement / World Trade Organization – Agreement on  Government Procurement / Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement  for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AP: CFTA /  NAFTA / CCFTA /  CCoFTA / CHFTA /  CPaFTA / CPFTA /  CKFTA / WTO-AGP /  CETA / TCA /  CPTPP  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  North  American Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement /  World  Trade Organization – Agreement on Government  Procurement / Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AQ: CFTA /  CCFTA / CCoFTA /  CHFTA / CPaFTA /  CPFTA / CKFTA /  WTO-AGP / CETA /  TCA / CPTPP (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade Agreement / World Trade Organization – Agreement on  Government Procurement / Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for  Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AR: CFTA /  NAFTA / CCFTA /  CCoFTA / CHFTA /  CPaFTA / CPFTA /  CKFTA / WTO-AGP /  CPTPP  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  North  American Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru  Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement /  World  Trade Organization – Agreement on Government  Procurement / Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement  for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AS: CFTA /  CCFTA / CCoFTA /  CHFTA / CPaFTA /  CPFTA / CKFTA /  WTO-AGP / CPTPP (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Colombia Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Honduras Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Panama Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Peru Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade Agreement / World Trade Organization – Agreement on  Government Procurement / Comprehensive and Progressive  Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AT: CFTA /  CCFTA / CKFTA (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade  Agreement)</li><li>AU: CFTA /  CCFTA / CKFTA /  WTO-AGP / CETA /  TCA / CPTPP (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade Agreement / World Trade Organization – Agreement on  Government Procurement / Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AV: CFTA /  CCFTA  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-Chile  Free Trade Agreement)</li><li>AW: CFTA /  CCFTA / CPTPP (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-Chile Free Trade Agreement / Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for  Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AX: CFTA /  CKFTA / WTO-AGP /  CETA / TCA (Canadian Free Trade Agreement / Canada-South Korea Free Trade Agreement / World Trade Organization – Agreement on  Government Procurement / Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement)</li><li>AY: CFTA /  CKFTA / WTO-AGP /  CETA / TCA /  CPTPP  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement /  World  Trade Organization – Agreement on Government  Procurement / Comprehensive Economic and Trade  Agreement / Canada-United  Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement /  Comprehensive  and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>AZ: CFTA /  CKFTA / WTO-AGP /  CPTPP  (Canadian Free Trade Agreement /  Canada-South  Korea Free Trade Agreement /  World  Trade Organization – Agreement on Government Procurement / Comprehensive and Progressive  Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership)</li><li>BA: ABSA (PSAB) /  LCSA  (CLCA) (Aboriginal Business Set Aside – Procurement Strategy for Aboriginal Business / Land Claim Set Aside – Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement)</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>20. Trade Agreement / Accord commercial</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that this field  indicate whether the procurement is covered by each of the applicable trade agreements. </li><li>Effective July 1, 2020, the North American Free Trade  Agreement (NAFTA) will no longer be in force. Departments are to no longer use  the data value associated with NAFTA for new procurements that commence on or  after July 1,  2020.</li><li>For existing contracts covered by  NAFTA, it is recommended that  departments no longer report on the data value associated with NAFTA when  reporting on an amendment to the contract. Alternatively, departments may  continue to indicate the data value associated with NAFTA for amendments to  existing contracts covered by NAFTA until such time that the data value is  removed from departmental procurement or financial reporting systems.</li><li>For contracts covered by the Agreement on Trade Continuity between Canada and the United  Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (TCA), departments are to  report using the new data value associated with the Canada-United Kingdom Trade  Continuity Agreement. Alternatively, departments may continue to report using  the data value associated with the Canada-European Union Comprehensive Economic  and Trade Agreement (CETA), until such time that the new data value associated  with the Canada-United Kingdom Trade Continuity Agreement is added to  departments’ procurement or financial reporting system.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>String  text, comma separated. It is recommended that this field be populated with one or  more of the following alphabetic characters. Report the alphabetic characters only. All text after the alphabetic characters, including the colon, is for information purposes only. For example, a procurement covered by  the Canadian Free Trade Agreement and the Canada-European Union Comprehensive  Economic and Trade Agreement is reported as CA, EU.
				
					<ul><li>XX: None</li><li>NA: North  American Free Trade Agreement (archived for  historical information)     </li><li>GP: World Trade Organization –  Agreement on Government Procurement </li><li>CL: Canada-Chile Free Trade  Agreement</li><li>PE: Canada-Peru Free Trade Agreement</li><li>CO: Canada-Colombia Free Trade  Agreement</li><li>PA: Canada-Panama Free Trade Agreement</li><li>HN: Canada-Honduras Free Trade  Agreement</li><li>KR: Canada-Korea Free Trade Agreement</li><li>CA: Canadian Free Trade Agreement</li><li>EU: Canada-European Union Comprehensive  Economic and Trade Agreement</li><li>TP: Comprehensive and Progressive  Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership</li><li>UA: Canada-Ukraine Free Trade Agreement</li><li>UK: Canada-United Kingdom Trade  Continuity Agreement</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those entered  into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>21. Comprehensive Land Claims Agreement / Entente sur  les revendications territoriales globales</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this field indicate whether the procurement is for goods,  services or construction services to be delivered to an area that is within one  or more of the Comprehensive Land Claims Agreements. </dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>String  text, comma separated. It is recommended that  this  field be populated with one or more of the following alphabetic characters. Report the alphabetic characters only. All text after the alphabetic characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only: 
				
					<ul><li>NA:  Not Applicable</li><li>JN:  James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement</li><li>NQ:  Northeastern Quebec Agreement</li><li>NI:  Nunavik Inuit Land Claims Agreement</li><li>EM:  Eeyou Marine Region Land Claims Agreement</li><li>LI:  Labrador Inuit Land Claim Agreement</li><li>NU: Nunavut  Agreement (Agreement between the Inuit of the Nunavut Settlement Area and Her  Majesty the Queen in right of Canada)</li><li>IF:  Inuvialuit Final Agreement</li><li>GW: Gwich’in  Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement</li><li>SD:  Sahtu Dene and Metis Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement</li><li>TA:  Tlicho Agreement</li><li>CH:  Champagne and Aishihik First Nations Final Agreement</li><li>FN:  First Nation of Nacho Nyak Dun Final Agreement</li><li>TT:  Teslin Tlingit Council Final Agreement</li><li>VG:  Vuntut Gwitchin First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>SF:  Selkirk First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>LS:  Little Salmon/Carmacks First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>TH: Tr’ondëk  Hwëch’in Final Agreement</li><li>TK: Ta’an  Kwach’an Council Final Agreement</li><li>KF:  Kluane First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>KD:  Kwanlin Dun First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>CT:  Carcross/Tagish First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>NF: Nisga’a  Final Agreement</li><li>TF:  Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement</li><li>MF:  Maa-nulth First Nations Final Agreement</li><li>TL: Tla’amin  Final Agreement</li><li>YA:  Yale First Nations Final Agreement</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>22. Commodity Type / Type de produit</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that the commodity type be populated with the one of the three  commodity types (Good, Service or Construction). When a contract involves more  than one commodity type, the commodity type associated with the largest dollar  value should be used. A department may use a different approach if this is the  standard practice in the department.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>For  all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value (excluding acquisition  card procurements from −$10,000 to $10,000), this element must be populated with  one of the following values (single  letter only; everything after the single letter, including the colon, is for information purposes  only): 
				
					<ul><li>G: Good</li><li>S: Service</li><li>C: Construction</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>23. Commodity Code / Code de produit</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that the commodity  code be populated with the generic product descriptions used by the federal  government for procurement activities.</li><li>When using the Goods and Services  Identification Number (GSIN), only those GSINs published by PSPC may be used.  The commodity code for goods must use a minimum of four numeric characters. The  commodity code for services must use either a minimum of one alphabetic  character and three numeric characters or, two alphabetic characters and two  numeric characters. The commodity code for construction must use a minimum of “51”  and one or two numeric characters.</li><li>When a contract involves more than one  commodity code, the commodity code associated with the largest dollar value  should be used. A department may use a different approach if this is the  standard practice in the department.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>24. Country of Vendor / Pays du fournisseur (formerly Country  of Origin / Pays d’origine)</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that this data field  be populated with the country of the vendor’s address identified in the  contract.</li><li>Alternatively, the country of the  vendor may be the country of the vendor’s address identified in the procurement  or financial system if this is the standard practice in the department. </li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphabetic characters listed in the <a href="http://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes/iso_3166_code_lists/country_names_and_code_elements.htm">International Organization for  Standardization (ISO) 3166 Country Codes</a>.  </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>25. Solicitation Procedure / Méthode d’invitation à  soumissionner</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that  this  field be populated with one of the five solicitation procedures listed below:
				<ul><li>AC: Advance Contract Award Notice (ACAN) refers to  a contract awarded to a supplier identified under an ACAN process where it was  determined that there were no other statements of capabilities that could  successfully meet the government’s requirements.</li><li>OB: Competitive – Open Bidding (Government  Electronic Tendering System (GETS)) refers to a competitive contract where bids  were solicited via GETS.</li><li>TC: Competitive – Traditional refers to a competitive  contract where bids were not solicited via GETS, but through another medium,  such as soliciting bids directly from suppliers by email or phone.</li><li>ST: Competitive – Selective Tendering refers to a  solicitation procedure permitted under Canada’s trade agreements where  qualified suppliers are selected from a source list (including single-use or  multi-use lists) under the selective tendering procedural rules in Canada’s  trade agreements.</li><li>TN: Non-competitive refers to a contract awarded to  a supplier without soliciting bids.</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that  this  field be populated with one of the following alphabetic codes. Report the  two alphabetic characters only. All text after the two alphabetic  characters,  including the colon, is  for information purposes only:  
				<ul><li>OB: Competitive – Open Bidding (GETS)</li><li>ST: Competitive – Selective Tendering </li><li>TC: Competitive – Traditional </li><li>AC: Advance Contract Award Notice</li><li>TN: Non-Competitive</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>26. Limited Tendering Reason /  Raisons justifiant le recours à l’appel d’offres limité</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It  is recommended that this field be populated with one or more of the limited  tendering reasons listed below. For reference, CUFTA stands for Canada-Ukraine  Free Trade Agreement. </dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>String  text, comma separated. It is recommended that  this  field be populated with one or more of the following numeric characters. Report numeric characters only. All text after the numeric characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only: 
				<ul><li>0:  None</li><li>5: No  response to bid solicitation</li><li>20:  Goods purchased on a commodity market</li><li>21:  Purchases made under exceptionally  advantageous conditions</li><li>22:  Winner of an architectural design contest</li><li>71:  Exclusive rights</li><li>72:  Prototype purchase</li><li>74: Additional  deliveries  (formerly interchangeable parts)</li><li>81:  Extreme urgency</li><li>23:  Consulting services regarding matters of a confidential nature (for contracts not covered by  CETA, TCA, WTO-GPA, CPTPP, CKFTA and CUFTA)</li><li>30:  Work on a property by a contractor according to a warranty or guarantee (for contracts  that are only covered by the CFTA)</li><li>31:  Work on a leased building or related property performed only by the lessor (for  contracts that are only covered by the CFTA)</li><li>32:  Subscriptions to newspapers, magazines, or other periodicals (for contracts  that are only covered by the CFTA)</li><li>33:  Goods regarding matters of a confidential or privileged nature (for contracts  that are only covered by the CFTA)</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>27. Trade Agreement Exceptions and Exclusions / Exceptions  et exclusions applicables aux accords commerciaux</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this field be populated with one or more of the exceptions or exclusions  listed below. Trade agreement exception and exclusion data values that are  identified as “archived” are to be used until such time that the new data  values can be used.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>String  text, comma separated. It is recommended that  this  field be populated with one or more of the following numeric characters. Report numeric characters only. All text after the numeric characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only: 
<ul><li>00: None</li><li>01: Shipbuilding  and repair (applies to all agreements except the CFTA)</li><li>02: Urban rail and  urban transportation equipment systems, components and materials (applies to  all agreements except CFTA, CETA, TCA and CPTPP)</li><li>03: Contracts  respecting Federal Supply Classification (FSC) 58 (communications, detection  and coherent radiation equipment) (applies to all agreements except CFTA, CETA,  TCA and CPTPP)</li><li>04: Set-asides for  small and minority businesses (archived for historical purpose)</li><li>05: Agricultural products made in furtherance of  agricultural support programs or human feeding programs (applies  to all agreements except CFTA)</li><li>06: The Depts. of  Transport, Communications and Fisheries &amp; Oceans respecting FSC 70, 74, 36 (applies to all agreements except CFTA, CKFTA,  WTO-AGP, CUFTA, CETA, TCA and CPTPP)</li><li>07:  Any measures for Indigenous peoples and businesses, including set asides for  Indigenous businesses (applies to all agreements)</li><li>08: Set-asides for small businesses, other than Indigenous  businesses (applies to all agreements except CETA and TCA) </li><li>09: Measures necessary to protect public  morals, order or safety (applies to all agreements)</li><li>10:  Measures necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health (applies to  all agreements) </li><li>11:  Measures necessary to protect intellectual property (applies to all agreements) </li><li>12:  Measures relating to goods or services of persons with disabilities,  philanthropic institutions or prison labour (applies to all agreements)</li><li>13: Services procured in support of military forces located  overseas (applies to all agreements) </li><li>14:  Research and development services (applies to all trade agreements except for CFTA)</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>28. Procurement Strategy for Indigenous Business (PSIB)  / Stratégie d’approvisionnement auprès des entreprises autochtones (SAEA)</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is recommended  that this field indicate whether the Procurement Strategy for Indigenous Business  mandatory or voluntary set-aside applies to the procurement transaction.  Departments may contact Indigenous Services Canada (ISC) by email at <a href="mailto:indigenousprocurement@sac-isc.gc.ca">indigenousprocurement@sac-isc.gc.ca</a> or by  phone at 1‑800‑400‑7677 for more information on the Procurement Strategy for Indigenous  Business.
	</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this  field be populated with one of the following alphabetic codes. Report the alphabetic characters only. All text after the alphabetic characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only: 
<ul><li>NA:  None</li><li>MS:  Mandatory Set-Aside</li><li>VS: Voluntary  Set-Aside</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>29. Indigenous Business excluding PSIB Set-Aside / Entreprises  autochtones excluant le marché réservé en vertu de la SAEA</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that this field  indicate whether a contract was awarded to an Indigenous business. Requirements  for verifying Indigenous businesses for the purposes of this data field are  available in the <a href="https://www.sac-isc.gc.ca/eng/1100100033057/1610797769658">Indigenous  Business Directory</a>, in accordance with subsection E.2.2.2.4 of Appendix E  of the <em>Directive on the Management of  Procurement</em>. </li><li>Any contract awarded to an Indigenous  business where the procurement is subject to a mandatory or voluntary set-aside  under the Procurement Strategy for Indigenous Business should be reported as  “No” under this data field as such contracts are already reported under the  Procurement Strategy for Indigenous Business data field.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Boolean  (including valid formats such as Yes or No, Y or N, T or F, Yes/Oui, or  No/Non).</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>30. Intellectual Property Indicator / Indicateur de  propriété intellectuelle </h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is recommended that this field  identify whether there are terms and conditions in the contract related to  intellectual property (IP) and whether those terms would result in Crown or  contractor ownership of the rights to the intellectual property. Refer to Appendix A  of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=13697"><em>Policy on Title to  Intellectual Property Arising Under Crown Procurement Contracts</em></a> for more information on the Crown exceptions to  Contractor ownership of intellectual property. </dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is recommended that this field be  populated with one of the following alphanumeric values. Report the alphanumeric characters  only. All text after the alphanumeric characters, including the colon, is for  information purposes only:
<ul><li>A2:  Crown owned – exception 2, contractor ownership is precluded by prior  obligations</li><li>A3:  Crown owned – exception 3, contractor has no interest in owning Foreground  IP</li><li>A41:  Crown owned – exception 4.1, generate knowledge for public dissemination</li><li>A42:  Crown owned – exception 4.2, augment existing body of Crown background</li><li>A43:  Crown owned – exception 4.3, deliver a not-yet fully developed component  or subsystem</li><li>A5:  Crown owned – exception 5, foreground IP consists of material subject to  copyright </li><li>A8:  Crown owned – exemption 8 (note: must have received approval from the  Treasury Board via a Treasury Board submission)</li><li>B:  Contractor owned</li><li>C: No  IP terms in contract </li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for all contracts and amendments regardless of  dollar value, excluding those entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or  less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>31. Potential for Commercial Exploitation / Potentiel d’exploitation  commerciale</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this field identify whether intellectual property generated  under the contract has the potential for commercial exploitation.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Boolean  (including valid formats such as Yes or No, Y or N, T or F, Yes/Oui, or  No/Non).</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments where Intellectual Property is generated under  the contract, regardless of dollar value, excluding those entered into via  acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>32. Former Public Servant in receipt  of a PSSA pension / Ancien fonctionnaire recevant une pension en vertu de la LPFP</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It  is recommended that this field identify whether the contractor is a former  public servant<sup id="fn2-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn2"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>2</a></sup> in receipt of a pension under the <em>Public  Service Superannuation Act</em> (PSSA).</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Boolean  (including valid formats such as Yes or No, Y or N, T or F, Yes/Oui, or  No/Non). </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>33. Contracting Entity (formerly Call-up or Contract  against a Standing Offer or Supply Arrangement Agreement) / Entité contractante  (anciennement Commande subséquente à une offer à commandes ou à un arrangement  en matière d’approvisionnement)</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that this field  identify whether the procurement is a contract awarded by the client  department, Public Services and Procurement Canada, Shared Services Canada or  another departmental entity or a call-up contract against a standing offer  agreement or supply arrangement agreement established by PSPC, SSC or the  department.</li><li>If PSPC awards a contract against a  PSPC SOSA on behalf of a client department, it is recommended that the contract  be reported as “PWC” for this field.</li><li>If SSC awards a contract against a SSC  SOSA on behalf of a client department, it is recommended that the contract be  reported as “SSCC” for this field.</li><li>If a department awards a contract  against a PSPC or SSC SOSA, it is recommended that the contract be reported as  “PWSOSA” or “SSCSOSA” as applicable.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this  field be populated with one of the following alphabetic characters. Report the alphabetic characters only. All text after the alphabetic characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only:
<ul><li>PWC:  Contract or Call-up awarded by PSPC on behalf of the client department.</li><li>SSCC:  Contract or Call-up awarded by SSC on behalf of the client department.</li><li>OGDC:  Contract awarded by another department on behalf of the client department.</li><li>DC:  Contract awarded by the department.</li><li>PWSOSA:  Call-up or Contract awarded by client department against a Standing Offer or  Supply Arrangement Agreement established by PSPC.</li><li>SSCSOSA:  Call-up or Contract awarded by client department against a Standing Offer or  Supply Arrangement Agreement established by SSC.</li><li>DSOSA:  Call-up or Contract against a Standing Offer or Supply Arrangement Agreement established  by the department.</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>34. Standing Offer or Supply Arrangement Number /  Numéro de l’offre à commandes ou de l’arrangement en matière  d’approvisionnement</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is recommended that this field be populated with the Standing Offer or Supply  Arrangement Number applicable to this contract. This field should be left blank  if there is no standing offer or supply arrangement established by PSPC or SSC  associated with this contract.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Alphanumeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>35. Instrument Type / Type d’instrument</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>It is recommended that the instrument  type identify whether the transaction being reported is a contract, contract  amendment, or a standing offer or supply arrangement agreement.</li><li>The instrument type for:
<ul><li>A contract is “C”; </li><li>An amendment is“A”;</li><li>A standing offer agreement or supply  arrangement agreement is “SOSA”;</li><li>Issuing a call-up against a standing  offer or supply arrangement is “C”; and</li><li>An amendment to a call-up is “A” for  this field.</li></ul></li><li>When a contract is entered into and  subsequently amended in the same fiscal quarter, the two transactions should be  reported separately. Entry into the contract should be reported as one entry  and should be identified as a contract by entering “C” for this field. The  contract amendment should be reported as a separate entry and be identified as  an amendment by entering “A” for this field.</li><li>When a standing offer or supply  arrangement agreement is amended, it should continue to be identified as an “SOSA”  for this field.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this  field be populated with one of the following alphabetic characters. Report the alphabetic character only. All text after the alphabetic character, including the colon, is  for information purposes only:
<ul><li>C:  Contract</li><li>A:  Amendment</li><li>SOSA:  Standing Offer Agreement / Supply  Arrangement Agreement</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>36. Ministers’ Office Contracts / Marchés des cabinets  des ministres</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this  field indicate whether the transaction is for the Minister’s office. Ministers’  offices contracts are any contracts for  goods and services entered into by a minister or their exempt staff. In  accordance with the <em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em>, such contracts should be charged to either a Minister’s  other operating budget or to the Parliamentary Secretary’s Assistant/Advisor  operating budget. Please refer to the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html"><em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em></a> for  more information on the Minister’s office budgets. This data field should be  entered for contracts and amendments awarded effective June 21, 2019, or, alternatively, for the contracts and amendments awarded  within the month of this effective date.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd> Boolean  (including valid formats such as Yes or No, Y or N, T or F, Yes/Oui, or  No/Non).</dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>37. Number of Bids / Nombre de soumissions</h3></header><p>Departments  and agencies listed in Appendix E are to report on this additional data  field in accordance with subsection 4.4.9 of this guide.</p><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this field be populated with the total number of compliant and  non-compliant bids received in the procurement.
<ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>For a competitive contract, it is  recommended for this field to be the number of bids received pursuant to a bid  solicitation.</li><li>For a call-up contract against a  standing offer agreement established under a competitive process, it is  recommended that a value of “0” be entered for this field. In this instance,  the value of “0” represents not applicable.</li><li>For a contract with task  authorizations, the number of bids of the contract may be reported if this  value is known when the task authorization is issued. If the number of bids is  unknown, the department may input a value of 0 to indicate it is not  applicable.</li><li>If the contract was awarded using an  Advance Contract Award Notice (ACAN) and it was determined that there were no  statements of capabilities that met the ACAN requirements, it is recommended  that a value of “1” be entered for this field. </li><li>For non-competitive contract, it is  recommended that a value of “1” be entered for this field.</li><li>For the establishment of a standing  offer or supply arrangement agreement, it is recommended for this field to be  the number of standing offer or supply arrangement bids received. If the  standing offer was established under a non-competitive or an ACAN procurement  process where it was determined that there were no statements of capabilities  that meet the ACAN requirements, it is recommended that a value of “1” be  entered for this field for subsequent contracts awarded under the standing  offer.</li><li>For a competitive contract awarded by  PSPC, SSC or another department on behalf of the client department, a value of  “0” may be entered if the information is not available within the reporting  period for which the contract was awarded. Once the information is available,  the contract record is to be updated at the next subsequent reporting period,  or as soon as practicable.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric. </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>38. Section 6 <em>Government Contracts Regulations</em> Exceptions / Article 6 – Exceptions au Règlement sur les marchés de l’État</h3></header><p>Departments  and agencies listed in Appendix E are to report on this additional data  field in accordance with subsection 4.4.9 of this guide.</p><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd><ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>The <em>Government  Contracts Regulations</em> requires the solicitation of bids unless one of the section 6  exceptions to the <em>Government Contracts  Regulations</em> applies to the contract. </li><li>It is recommended that this field be  populated with one of the section 6 exceptions to solicit bids if bids have  not been solicited for the contract.</li><li>It is recommended that this field be  populated with one of the section 6 exceptions to solicit bids if the  contract was awarded using an Advance Contract Award Notice (ACAN) and it was  determined that there were no statements of capabilities that met the ACAN  requirements. </li><li>For contracts whereby bids have been  solicited or if the procurement is not a contract subject to the <em>Government Contracts Regulations</em>, the  value of “0” should be entered. For this data value, the value of “0”  represents not applicable.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this  field be populated with one of the following numeric characters. Report numeric characters only. All text after the numeric characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only:
<ul><li>0: Not  applicable </li><li>1:  Pressing emergency in which delay would be injurious to the public interest</li><li>2:  Does not exceed s.6 (b) <em>Government Contracts Regulation</em>s  prescribed dollar limits. </li><li>3: Not  in the public interest to solicit bids </li><li>4:  Only one person is capable of performing the contract</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>39. Award Criteria / Critères d’attribution</h3></header><p>Departments  and agencies listed in Appendix E are to report on this additional data  field in accordance with subsection 4.4.9 of this guide.</p><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It  is recommended that this field be populated with one of the bid evaluation  methodologies below if bids have been solicited for the contract:
<ol class="lst-lwr-rmn"><li>If bids have not been solicited, the  value of “0” is to be selected. </li><li>For ACANs whereby it was determined  that there were no statements of capabilities that met the ACAN requirements,  the value of “0” should be entered. </li><li>For amendments, select the value of “0”  of this field.</li><li>For a competitive contract awarded by  PSPC, SSC or another department on behalf of the client department, a value of  “0” may be entered if the information is not available within the reporting  period for which the contract was awarded. Once information is available, the  contract record is to be updated at the next subsequent reporting period, or as  soon as practicable.</li></ol></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended that this  field be populated with one of the following numeric characters. Report numeric characters only. All text after the numeric characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only:
<ul><li>0: Not  applicable</li><li>1:  Lowest price</li><li>2:  Lowest cost-per-point</li><li>3:  Highest combined rating of technical merit and price </li><li>4:  Highest technical merit  within a stipulated maximum budget</li><li>5:  Variations or combinations of the above methods</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts entered into and positive and negative amendments over  $10,000.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>40. Socio-Economic  Indicator / Indicateur socioéconomique</h3></header><p>Departments  and agencies listed in Appendix E are to report on this additional data  field in accordance with subsection 4.4.9 of this guide.</p><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is recommended  that this field indicate whether the procurement is subject to one or more of  the applicable Socio-economic indicators.
<table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><tr><th class="text-left" scope="col">Indicator</th><th class="text-left" scope="col">Description</th></tr><tr><td>Federal Contractors Program for Employment Equity</td><td>This indicator should be selected if the contract is subject to the Federal Contractors Program for Employment Equity. For additional information or enquiries on the program, please contact Employment and Social Development Canada (ESDC) at <a href="mailto:ee-eme@hrsdc-rhdcc.gc.ca">ee-eme@hrsdc-rhdcc.gc.ca</a>.</td></tr></table></dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>String  text, comma separated. It is recommended that  this  field be populated with one or more of the following alphabetic characters. Report the alphabetic characters only. All text after the alphabetic characters, including the colon, is  for information purposes only:
<ul><li>NA:  None</li><li>FP:  Federal Contractors Program for Employment Equity</li><li>Reserved  for future use</li><li>Reserved  for future use</li><li>Reserved  for future use</li></ul></dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement </strong></dt><dd>Required  for all contracts and amendments, regardless of dollar value, excluding those  entered into via acquisition card at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>41. Reporting Period / Periode de déclaration</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is recommended that this field be  populated in the standard format described below. For example, if a contract is  being amended on May 3, 2017, and reported in the first fiscal quarter of  2017–2018, the entry should be 2017–2018–‑Q1.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>When reporting quarterly, one of the following values  where YYYY is the fiscal year the data was reported:
<ul><li>YYYY-YYYY-Q1</li><li>YYYY-YYYY-Q2</li><li>YYYY-YYYY-Q3</li><li>YYYY-YYYY-Q4</li></ul><p>When providing information to Public Services  and Procurement Canada, include the calendar year with the format YYYY. </p></dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required for all contracts and amendments  regardless of dollar value, excluding those entered into via acquisition card  at $10,000 or less.</dd></dl></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appB">Appendix B – data elements for annual reporting and publication</h2><div class="pol-content"><section><header><h3>1. Calendar Year Reporting Period</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated in the standard format described  below. For example, if the template is being reported for the 2017 calendar  year, the entry will be populated as 2017.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>YYYY </dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>2. Number of Goods Contracts $10K and under</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the total number of goods  contracts entered into with a value of $10,000 and under. This includes goods  contracts entered into and subsequently amended in the same calendar year to an  amended contract value of $10,000 and under.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding spaces and commas. Formulas are not to be used to populate this  data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>3. Goods Contracts $10K and under - Original Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the value of all goods  contracts with a value of $10,000 and under, at the time of contract entry.  This value should be in Canadian currency and include all applicable taxes.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23.  Formulas are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting  requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>4. Goods Contracts Amendments from −$10K to $10K - Net Amendment Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the value of all net amendments  to goods contracts (that is, all positive and negative amendments) with a value  from −$10,000 to $10,000. This value should be in Canadian currency and include  all applicable taxes. An amendment should be reported either quarterly or  annually. Reporting an amendment both quarterly and annually would result in  double counting of the amendment’s value when calculating the total contracting  activity of an organization.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas  are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>5. Number of Service Contracts $10K and under</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the total number of services  contracts entered into with a value of $10,000 and under. This includes  services contracts entered into and subsequently amended in the same calendar  year to an amended contract value of $10,000 and under.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding spaces and commas. Formulas are not to be used to populate this  data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>6. Service Contracts $10K and under - Original Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It  is recommended for this field to be populated with the value of all service  contracts with a value $10,000 and under, at the time of contract entry. This  value should be in Canadian currency and include all applicable taxes.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas  are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>7. Service Contracts from −$10K to $10K - Net Amendment Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It  is recommended for this field to be populated with the value of all net  amendments to service contracts (that is, all positive and negative amendments)  with a value from −$10,000 to $10,000. This value should be in Canadian  currency and include all applicable taxes. An amendment should be reported  either quarterly or annually. Reporting an amendment both quarterly and  annually would result in double counting of the amendment’s value when  calculating the total contracting activity of an organization.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas  are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>8. Number of Construction Contracts $10K and under</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the total number of construction  contracts entered into with a value of $10,000 and under. This includes construction  contracts entered into and subsequently amended in the same calendar year to an  amended contract value of $10,000 and under.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding spaces and commas. Formulas are not to be used to populate this  data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>9. Construction Contracts $10K and under - Original Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the value of all construction  contracts with a value $10,000 and under, at the time of contract entry. This  value should be in Canadian currency and include all applicable taxes.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas  are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>10. Construction Contracts Amendments from −$10K to $10K - Net Amendment Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the value of all net amendments  to construction contracts (that is, all positive and negative amendments) with  a value from −$10,000 to $10,000. This value should be in Canadian currency and  include all applicable taxes. An amendment should be reported either quarterly  or annually. Reporting an amendment both quarterly and annually would result in  double counting of the amendment’s value when calculating the total contracting  activity of an organization.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas  are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>11. Number of Acquisition Card Transactions for All Dollar Values</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the total number of all  acquisition card transactions for all dollar values.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding spaces and commas. Formulas are not to be used to populate this  data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required. </dd></dl></section><section><header><h3>12. Acquisition Card Transactions for All Dollar Values - Total Value</h3></header><dl><dt><strong>Description</strong></dt><dd>It is  recommended for this field to be populated with the sum of all dollar values  for all acquisition card transactions. This value should be in Canadian  currency and include all applicable taxes.</dd><dt><strong>Data format</strong></dt><dd>Numeric  and excluding dollar signs, spaces and commas. For example, 23000.23. Formulas  are not to be used to populate this data field.</dd><dt><strong>Reporting requirement</strong></dt><dd>Required.</dd></dl></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appC">Appendix C – table of standardized comments</h2><div class="pol-content"><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr class="active"><th scope="col">The “comments” data element is to identify when the contract contains the following characteristic</th><th scope="col">Standardized comment</th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="2"><p><strong>Note:</strong> Departments are encouraged to develop additional standardized comments that meet their unique operational requirements.</p></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><th scope="row">Contract involving more than one department</th><td>This is part of multi-departmental contract #: [insert contract #].</td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Contract restatement</th><td>This is a notice of the restatement of Contract [reference number] dated [contract period/delivery date]. The contract was misstated for [misstated contract information] and has been corrected. </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Contract previously not reported</th><td><p>This contract was omitted from a previous proactive publication. </p><p>Note: Departments may continue to use the following text until such time as their reporting processes have been updated with the new standardized comment:</p><p>This contract was omitted from a previous proactive disclosure.</p></td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Contract with task authorizations</th><td><p>For a contract with task authorizations, the realized amount of the contract is contingent on the number of task authorizations issued and may be less than the amount proactively published, dependent on the operational requirements of the department.</p><p>Note: Departments may continue to use the following text until such time as their reporting processes have been updated with the new standardized comment:</p><p>For a contract with task authorizations, the realized amount of the contract is contingent on the number of task authorizations issued and may be less than the amount proactively disclosed, dependent on the operational requirements of the department.</p></td></tr><tr><th scope="row">Contract update with additional information on number of bids and/or award criteria.</th><td>The contract was updated with additional information for the number of bids and/or award criteria.</td></tr></tbody></table></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appD">Appendix D – economic  object codes warranting a further contract description</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>D.1 Contracts and amendments awarded on  or after October 1, 2023, that include the following economic object codes are subject  to additional reporting requirements as specified in section D.2 of this appendix.</p><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Economic object code</th><th scope="col">Objects of expenditure</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row">0351</th><td>Communications professional services not elsewhere specified </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0859</th><td>Other business services not elsewhere specified </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0401</th><td>Accounting and audit services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0402</th><td>Human resources management services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0403</th><td>Financial management services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0404</th><td>Communications services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0405</th><td>Real property services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0406</th><td>Material services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0407</th><td>Acquisition services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0420</th><td>Engineering services not elsewhere specified </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0422</th><td>Engineering consultants – construction </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0423</th><td>Engineering consultants – other </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0431</th><td>Scientific consultants </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0446</th><td>Training consultants </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0451</th><td>Other health services not elsewhere specified </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0473</th><td>Information technology and telecommunications consultants </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0491</th><td>Management consulting </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0813</th><td>Temporary help services </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0499</th><td>Other professional services not elsewhere specified </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0819</th><td>Non-professional personal service contracts not elsewhere specified </td></tr><tr><th scope="row">0891</th><td>Personal services </td></tr></tbody></table><p>D.2 Contracts for services with the economic  object codes specified in section D.1 of this appendix are to include the  following in the comments data field or, if additional capacity is required, in  the additional comments data field: </p><p>D.2.1 Include the standardized text as  indicated in the following table in plain language when a contract has: </p><ul><li>A value over $10,000; </li><li>Positive or negative amendments  with a value over $10,000; or</li><li>Positive amendments  that modify the initial contract value to over $10,000.</li></ul><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr><th class="text-left" scope="col">Type of information</th><th class="text-left" scope="col">Standardized text</th><th class="text-left" scope="col">Guidance note</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="row">Contract Description</th><td>Contract Description: [Insert a brief description of the contract]</td><td>Departments are to provide a brief description of the contract so that the public may benefit from additional context.</td></tr></tbody></table><p><strong>Example</strong></p><p>If a department reports a $50,000 contract  for engineering consulting services to conduct a feasibility study to retrofit  a building to improve accessibility, the type of standardized text to be provided  in the comments or additional comments data field may include: </p><p>Contract  Description: Engineering consulting services to conduct a feasibility study of accessibility  retrofits at 90 Elgin.</p><p>D.2.2 Include the standardized text as  indicated in the following table in plain language when a contract has:</p><ul><li>A value over $1,000,000;</li><li>Positive amendments  that modify such initial contracts to a value over $1,000,000; or</li><li>Subsequent amendments to such contracts that require  proactive publication onto the Open Government Portal on a quarterly basis.</li></ul><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr><th class="text-left" scope="col">Type of information</th><th class="text-left" scope="col">Standardized text format</th><th class="text-left" scope="col">Guidance note</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><th scope="col">Contract Description</th><td>Contract Description: [Insert a detailed description of the contract.]</td><td><p>Departments are to provide a detailed description of the contract.</p><p>Where the contract was the result of an open competitive process, departments should consider using the publicly available description of the work, such as    procurement description information in a tender on the Government Electronic    Tendering System or contract information on a public website.</p><p>If there is no publicly available information, departments should provide a description of the contract similar to what a department would normally provide in a tender or contract award notice or a summary of the statement of work. </p><p>If readily available, provide the categories of resources required.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><p><strong>Example</strong></p><p>If a department  is proactively publishing information on a $10 million contract for  professional services for the provision of specialized informatics professional  services to support the ongoing operation of their financial management system,  the type of standardized text to be provided in the comments or additional comments  data field may include: </p><p>Contract Description: The department  has a requirement for the provision of specialized technical support services  for the department’s financial management system. The contractor will provide  technical support 24 hours a day and 7 days a week to the department’s  information technology service team to troubleshoot issues, develop software  patches and provide system updates to ensure that there are no service  interruptions to the system. This contract supports the department’s delivery  of its core mandate and contributes to the department’s data modernization  strategy.</p><p>D.2.3 When  reporting on amendments, departments are to include the contract description  for the original contract. Departments are to provide additional information if  there is a significant amendment to the contract and this information is in the  public interest. </p><p>D.2.4 Consistent  with subsections 4.2.1, 4.2.2, 4.2.3, and 4.2.4 of this guide, departments  are to determine to what extent the contract description information, in whole  or in part, would properly be withheld in response to a request under Part 1  of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, pursuant to section 80 and section 90  of the Act.</p><p>D.2.5 Business  owners should assist departments by providing information related to the  contract description to ensure the timely publication of contract information.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="appE">Appendix E – reporting of additional contract data  fields in Appendix A</h2><div class="pol-content"><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed"><thead><tr><th class="text-left" scope="col">Departments and agencies</th><th class="text-left" scope="col">Reporting date</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Departments and agencies onboarding to the Government of Canada    Financial and Materiel Management (GCFM) Solution</td><td>No later than <time datetime="2022-05-30" class="nowrap">May 30, 2022</time> for contracts awarded starting <time datetime="2022-01-01" class="nowrap">January 1, 2022</time> or on the date that a department onboards to GCFM. </td></tr><tr><td>Departments and agencies that are members of the following:
					   <ul><li>Integrated Financial and Materiel System (IFMS) group</li><li>GX group</li></ul><p>The following departments:</p><ul><li>Transport Canada</li><li>Correctional Services Canada</li></ul></td><td>No later than <time datetime="2022-05-30">May 30, 2022</time> for contracts awarded starting <time datetime="2022-01-01" class="nowrap">January 1, 2022</time>. </td></tr><tr><td>Public Services and Procurement Canada</td><td><time datetime="2023-10-30" class="nowrap">October 30, 2023</time> for contracts awarded starting <time datetime="2023-07-01" class="nowrap">July 1, 2023</time> or when this information is available within departmental procurement or financial systems </td></tr><tr><td>All other departments and agencies</td><td>Departments and agencies are to consider these data elements when onboarding to new financial or procurement systems and to report within the applicable reporting timelines. For example, if an entity onboards to a new system on <time datetime="2022-04-01" class="nowrap">April 1, 2022</time>, then the reporting requirement will be for <time datetime="2022-07-30" class="nowrap">July 30, 2022</time>. </td></tr></tbody></table><p>The reporting date listed above identifies  the date for which the Appendix E departments are to report on the  following Appendix A data fields: </p><ul><li>Number of Bids</li><li>Section 6 Government Contracts Regulations Exceptions</li><li>Award Criteria</li><li>Socio-Economic Indicator</li></ul><p>Note: Departments and agencies listed in this Appendix E may proactively publish information on the additional contract data earlier than the listed reporting date, if such information is available in their departmental procurement or financial systems.</p></div></section></div><aside class="wb-fnote" role="note"><h2 id="fn">Footnotes</h2><dl><dt>Footnote fn1</dt><dd id="fn1"><p><p>A task authorization  (TA) is a structured administrative process that enables the client to  authorize work by a contractor on an as-and-when-requested basis in accordance  with the terms and conditions of an existing contract. Contracts that provide  for the use of TAs (TA contracts) are used in contracting situations when a  definite need for a category of service exists, but the precise nature and  timing of the need cannot be established in advance.</p></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#fn1-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>1<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote fn2</dt><dd id="fn2"><p><p> For the purpose of this guideline, ’former public servant’ means, any former member of a department as defined in the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>, in receipt of a pension under the <em>Public Service Superannuation Act</em>.</p></p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#fn2-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>2<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd></dl></aside><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small">© His Majesty the King in right of Canada, represented by the President of the Treasury Board, 2025, <br/>ISBN:                  </p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>