<!DOCTYPE html><!--[if lt IE 9]><html class="no-js lt-ie9" lang="en" dir="ltr"><![endif]--><!--[if gt IE 8]><!--><html class="no-js" dir="ltr" lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--<![endif]--><head><meta charset="utf-8"></meta><!-- Web Experience Toolkit (WET) / Boîte à outils de l'expérience Web (BOEW) wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/License-en.html / wet-boew.github.io/wet-boew/Licence-fr.html --><title>Guide to the Proactive Publication of Travel and Hospitality Expenses</title><meta content="width=device-width,initial-scale=1" name="viewport"></meta><meta content="robots" name="noindex,nofollow"></meta><!-- Load stylesheet --><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/cdts-styles.css"></link><!-- Load/activate closure template scripts --><script src="https://www.canada.ca/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/compiled/wet-en.js"></script><noscript><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/refTop.html" --></noscript><script>
          wet.builder.setup({
            cdnEnv: "prod",
            isApplication: false,
            top: {
              breadcrumbs: [{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/index.html", title: "Home"},{ href: "http://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/index.html", title: "How government works"},{ href: "index-eng.aspx", title: "Policies, directives, standards and guidelines"},{ href: "doc-eng.aspx?id=32660", title: "Guide to the Proactive Publication of Travel and Hospitality Expenses"}],
              lngLinks: [{ lang: "en", href: "doc-fra.aspx?id=32660&amp;section=html", text: "Français"}],
              search: false,
              siteMenu: false,
              topSecMenu: false
            },
            preFooter: {
              dateModified: "2025-03-18",
              showFeedback: false,
              showPostContent: false,
              showShare: false
            },
            footer: {
              showFooter: false
            }
          });
        </script><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/pol.css"></link><link rel="stylesheet" href="./css/print.pol.css"></link></head><body vocab="http://schema.org/" typeof="WebPage"><div id="cdts-def-top"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/top-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/top-en.html" --></div><main property="mainContentOfPage" typeof="WebPageElement" class="container"><!-- the main content --><div class="row"><div class="col-md-12"><h1 id="wb-cont" property="name">Guide to the Proactive Publication of Travel and Hospitality Expenses</h1><div class="pol-cha"><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha1">1. Date of publication</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guide takes effect on August 1, 2020, and was updated on March 18, 2025.</p><p>This guide replaces <em>Guidance Document: Proactive Disclosure of Travel and Hospitality Expenses</em>, dated March 31, 2004.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha2">2. Application</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guide supports the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32756"><em>Directive on Proactive Publication under the Access to Information Act</em></a>, which aims to establish consistent practices and procedures for implementing the proactive publication requirements under Part 2 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>.</p><p>This guide focuses on the proactive publication of travel and hospitality expenses that apply to government institutions that are subject to the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>.</p><p>Government institutions should adopt all sections and requirements of this guide, as well as all sections and requirements of the following:</p><ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/index.html"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32756"><em>Directive on Proactive Publication under the Access to Information Act</em></a></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha3">3. Objective</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>This guide will help ensure that information on government travel and hospitality expenses is proactively published in accordance with statutory obligations. Proactive publication provides consistent information that is accessible to the public.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha4">4. Whose travel and hospitality expenses must be proactively published?</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>, travel and hospitality expenses incurred by the following individuals must be proactively published in electronic form:</p><ul><li><strong>ministers</strong> (including the Prime Minister, ministers of state and associate ministers), <strong>ministerial advisers</strong><sup id="fn1-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn1"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>1</a></sup> and <strong>ministerial staff</strong><sup id="fn2-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn2"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>2</a></sup></li><li><strong>senior officers or employees</strong> in any department or ministry of state of the Government of Canada, or in any body or office listed in Schedule I of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, which includes government institutions listed in Schedules I, I.1, and II of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a> (including deputy ministers, deputy heads, associate deputy ministers, assistant deputy ministers, assistant deputy heads, and any individuals who hold positions of an equivalent rank)
				</li><li><strong>senior officers or employees</strong> in any parent Crown corporation, and any wholly owned subsidiary of such a corporation, within the meaning of section 83 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a> (including presidents, vice‑presidents, chief executive officers and members of a board of directors, and any individuals who hold positions of an equivalent rank)
				</li></ul><p>Travel and hospitality expenses incurred by individuals on behalf of any person listed above must also be published.</p><p>It is up to the government institution to determine which positions constitute positions of an equivalent rank.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha5">5. What information needs to be proactively published?</h2><div class="pol-content"><section><h3>5.1 What travel expense information needs to be proactively published?</h3><p>Government institutions must publish the information in Table 1 for each trip taken by any individual listed in section 4 of this guide.</p><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed table-hover small"><caption class="text-left">Table 1: information fields for travel expenses</caption><thead><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Information field</th><th scope="col">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><p>Reference number</p></td><td><p>A unique reference number given to the published expense report for each trip. Having a unique identifier for each trip helps users find a specific item if they need to change or delete it.</p><p><strong>Example:</strong> T-20YY-P1-00001</p><ul><li>T: for travel</li><li>20YY: for the fiscal year ending on March 31, 20YY</li><li>P: for the reporting period in which the expenses were reimbursed (see Table 3)</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> The 5-digit number at the end of the reference number is generated in sequence for each trip, for example:</p><ul><li>T-20YY-P1-00002</li><li>T-20YY-P1-00003</li><li>T-20YY-P1-00004</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Disclosure group</p></td><td><p>The group to which the individual belongs. Choose one of the following:</p><ul><li>Minister / ministerial adviser / ministerial staff / parliamentary secretary / exempt staff</li><li>Senior officer or employee</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Title</p></td><td><p>Position title of the person who travelled.</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li>Vice‑Chairperson</li><li>Deputy Minister</li><li>Parliamentary Secretary</li><li>Assistant Deputy Minister, Programs Branch</li><li>Commander, Royal Canadian Air Force</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Name</p></td><td><p>Name of the person who travelled.</p><p>Name should be formatted as [first name] [last name].</p><p><strong>Example: </strong>John Smith</p><p>For name of ministers, do not include “Honourable” in the name field.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Organization</p></td><td><p>Name of the government institution.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Purpose of travel</p></td><td><p>A short description of the reason for the trip.</p><p>The description should be no more than one line, if possible, and acronyms should be avoided.</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li>Attend North American Free Trade Agreement trade mission</li><li>Give presentation at the Ontario Chamber of Commerce</li><li>Attend Government of Canada Leadership Conference</li><li>Team Canada trade mission meetings</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Dates of travel</p></td><td><p>Start and end dates for the full period of the trip.</p><p>Dates should be formatted as yyyy-mm-dd.</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Start date:</strong> 20YY-06-22</li><li><strong>End date:</strong> 20YY-06-23</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Places visited</p></td><td><p>All places visited during the trip.</p><p>Destinations in Canada and the United States should be formatted as [city], [province or state], [country].</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li>Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</li><li>New York City, New York, United States</li></ul><p>International destinations should be formatted as [city], [country].</p><p><strong>Example:</strong> Kyoto,  Japan</p><p><strong>Multiple destinations</strong></p><p>Refer to the Open Government Registry Proactive Publication – Travel Expenses Reference tab / Data Dictionary for technical guidance on data entry.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Airfare</p></td><td><p>Total cost of airline tickets.</p><p><strong>Aircraft owned or operated by Government of Canada</strong><br />
If the individual travelled on an aircraft that is owned or operated by the Government of Canada, charges may not be levied in some cases. Use of such aircraft, however, should still be indicated. If charges were levied for the use of such aircraft, however, those charges should be indicated. See subsection 6.3 of the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html"><em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em></a> for details.</p><p>Fees for seat selection and luggage should be included in the total cost of airfare. These fees should be explained in the “Additional comments” field.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Other transportation</p></td><td><p>Total cost of any other forms of transportation (for example, train, bus, vehicle rental, private vehicle, taxis, parking).</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Lodging</p></td><td><p>Total cost of accommodation.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Meals and incidentals</p></td><td><p>Total cost of meals and incidental expenses.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Other expenses</p></td><td><p>Total cost of all other items that are not covered by the above fields (for example, a special passport, visas, associated photos, calls to the office or home, dependant care, where applicable).</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Total amount</p></td><td><p>The total of the amounts listed above.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Additional comments</p></td><td><p>Additional explanatory comments (as required). In this field, explain any corrections or adjustments made to the proactive publication or any other information, such as:</p><ul><li>the individuals accompanying the travellers (for example, a minister’s spouse or dependant or a member of Parliament)</li><li>the cancellation of a trip</li><li>the application of credits to the cost of the trip (for example, using credit from a cancelled trip to reduce the airfare of another trip)</li><li>use of a government owned vehicle or aircraft</li></ul><p>Refer to the notes in subsections 5.1.1 and 5.3 below for more information.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><section><header class="panel-heading"><h4>5.1.1 Additional information on publication of travel expenses</h4></header><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li><strong>Companion travel:</strong> Companion travel expenses must be included in the travel expense disclosure of the individual subject to proactive publication. For example, when the spouse of a minister accompanies that minister on official government business, in accordance with the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html"><em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em></a>, the travel expenses incurred by the spouse must be included in the minister’s travel expense claims and must be published. In such situations, the spouse’s presence on the trip is to be indicated in the “Purpose of travel” field (for example, “Attend state funeral: Accompanied by spouse”). Additional information could be added in the “Additional comments” field.</li><li><strong>Dependant travel:</strong> Travel expenses for dependants can be claimed under very specific circumstances, which are set out in the National Joint Council <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d10/en"><em>Travel Directive</em></a>. If dependant travel expenses are allowed, they should be included in the official’s travel claims and should be published. For example, the “Purpose of travel” field could be populated with “Weekend travel: Dependant” and additional information could be added in the “Additional comments” field.</li><li><strong>Member of Parliament (MP) travel: </strong>Under the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html"><em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em></a> and the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/travel-relocation/special-travel-authorities.html"><em>Special Travel Authorities</em></a>, MPs may, in some circumstances, accompany a minister as a guest or travel on a minister’s behalf. If the travel expenses incurred by an MP in such circumstances are charged to the minister’s budget, they should be published and would be indicated in the “Purpose of travel” field. Example: “Infrastructure Canada announcement: Accompanied by Joe Smith, MP” or “Infrastructure Canada announcement: Joe Smith, MP, on behalf of Minister Jones.”</li><li><strong>Relocation:</strong> Travel expenses incurred for the purposes of relocation under the National Joint Council <a href="http://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d6/en"><em>Relocation Directive</em></a> are not subject to proactive publication.</li><li><strong>Cancelled trips: </strong>If a trip is cancelled, the expenses incurred should still be published and additional information provided in the “Additional comments” field. For example, in the case of a cancelled trip for which an airline ticket was purchased, if the airline has issued or will be issuing travel credits or refunds to offset the cost of the ticket, the total cost of the ticket (including all associated fees) should be published and information on the cancelled trip and cost offset should be provided in the “Additional comments” field.</li><li><strong>Use of travel credits: </strong>When travel credits are applied to the cost of an airline ticket, thereby reducing its cost, the total cost of the airline ticket that would have been charged should be published and additional information on the travel credit used should be provided in the “Additional comments” field.</li><li><strong>Local travel: </strong>Travel expenses to be published include local travel within the normal office location and surrounding working area (for example, taxi and parking expenses).</li></ol></section><section class="panel panel-primary"><header class="panel-heading"><h4 class="mrgn-tp-0">Example 1: proactive publication of travel expenses</h4></header><div class="panel-body"><p><strong>Reference number:</strong> T-20YY-P10-00013</p><p><strong>Disclosure group:</strong> Minister / ministerial adviser / ministerial staff / parliamentary secretary / exempt staff</p><p><strong>Title:</strong> Minister of Veterans Affairs Canada</p><p><strong>Name:</strong> John Smith</p><p><strong>Organization:</strong> Veterans Affairs Canada</p><p><strong>Purpose of travel:</strong> Attend a wreath‑laying ceremony to commemorate the Battle of Verdun</p><p><strong>Travel start date:</strong> 20YY-06-22</p><p><strong>Travel end date:</strong> 20YY-06-23</p><p><strong>Places visited:</strong> Verdun, France</p><p><strong>Airfare:</strong> $2,000.00</p><p><strong>Other transportation:</strong> $50.00</p><p><strong>Lodging:</strong> $300.00</p><p><strong>Meals and incidentals:</strong> $150.00</p><p><strong>Other expenses:</strong> $0.00</p><p><strong>Total amount:</strong> $2,500.00</p></div></section></section><section><h3>5.2 What hospitality expense information needs to be proactively published?</h3><p>Government institutions must publish the information in Table 2 for hospitality expenses incurred by any individual listed in section 4 of this guide.</p><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed table-hover small"><caption class="text-left">Table 2: information fields for hospitality expenses</caption><thead><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Information field</th><th scope="col">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><p>Reference number</p></td><td><p>A unique reference number given to each proactive publication of a hospitality activity. Having a unique identifier for each hospitality activity helps users find a specific item if they need to change or delete it.</p><p><strong>Example:</strong> H-20YY-P1-00001</p><ul><li>H: for hospitality</li><li>20YY: for the fiscal year ending on March 31, 20YY</li><li>P: for the reporting period in which the expenses were reimbursed (see Table 3)</li></ul><p><strong>Note:</strong> The 5-digit number at the end of the reference number is generated in sequence for each hospitality activity, for example:</p><ul><li>H-20YY-P1-00002</li><li>H-20YY-P1-00003</li><li>H-20YY-P1-00004</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Disclosure group</p></td><td><p>The group to which the individual belongs.</p><p>Choose 1 of the following:</p><ul><li>Minister / ministerial adviser / ministerial staff / parliamentary secretary / exempt staff</li><li>Senior officer or employee</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Title</p></td><td><p>Position title of the individual who incurred the hospitality expenses. The hospitality expenses were charged to their responsibility centre or were incurred on behalf of that individual.</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li>Vice‑Chairperson</li><li>Deputy Minister</li><li>Parliamentary Secretary</li><li>Assistant Deputy Minister, Programs Branch</li><li>Commander, Royal Canadian Air Force</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Name</p></td><td><p>Name of the individual who incurred the hospitality expenses. The hospitality expenses were charged to their responsibility centre or were incurred on behalf of that individual.</p><p>For name of ministers, do not include “Honourable” in the name field.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Organization</p></td><td><p>Name of the government institution.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Purpose of hospitality activity</p></td><td><p>Indicate both the form (for  example, breakfast, refreshments, lunch, reception, dinner and other forms of  hospitality) and the circumstances of the hospitality.</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li>Refreshments and lunch: Information Management and Policies Committee meeting</li><li>Reception: Maltese delegation</li><li>Dinner: Trade discussions with United States and Mexican officials</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Date of hospitality activity</p></td><td><p>Start and end dates for the period in which the hospitality was provided.</p><p>Dates should be formatted as yyyy-mm-dd.</p><p><strong>Examples:</strong></p><ul><li>Start date: 20YY-05-25</li><li>End date: 20YY-05-25</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Municipality where the hospitality activity took place</p></td><td><p>Municipality where the hospitality was provided.</p><p>The information should be formatted as [city], [province/state], [country].</p><p><strong>Example:</strong> Montréal, Quebec, Canada</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Name of the commercial establishment or vendor involved in the hospitality activity</p></td><td><p>The name of the commercial establishment that provided the hospitality (for example, restaurant, hotel or other location) and the name of the vendor (for example, a caterer), if it is different.</p><p>When hospitality expenses are from more than one vendor, list all vendors. Separate them with semicolons.</p><p><strong>Example:</strong></p><ul><li>Vendor A; Vendor B; Vendor C</li></ul><p>Note the following:</p><ul><li>Another government department is not a vendor for the purposes of this requirement. A Crown corporation is a vendor for the purposes of this requirement only if it is a non-agent Crown corporation (for example, one of the museums established under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/M-13.4/index.html"><em>Museums Act</em></a>). If the name is not required, enter “nil” in this field.</li><li>Proactive publication of the name of the venue is required if a room is rented for the purpose of providing the hospitality activity and if the venue is a commercial establishment. It is not required if the venue is a government venue unless the venue is operated by a non-agent Crown corporation.</li><li>Proactive publication of the name of the venue is required if a room is rented for the sole purpose of providing hospitality.</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Number of persons who attended the hospitality activity</p></td><td><p>The number of Government of Canada officials: for example, public servants, federal ministers and ministerial staff, persons on contracts with the Government of Canada.</p><p>The number of guests: for example, foreign delegates, provincial or municipal representatives, private sector representatives.</p><p>The names of the attendees are not required.</p><p><strong>Example:</strong></p><ul><li>Attendees (Government of Canada officials): 7</li><li>Attendees (guests): 5</li></ul></td></tr><tr><td><p>Total amount of the expenses for the hospitality activity</p></td><td><p>The total cost of the hospitality activity.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p>Additional comments</p></td><td><p>Additional explanatory comments (as required).</p><p>Refer to the notes in subsections 5.2.1 and 5.3 below for more  information.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><section><header class="panel-heading"><h4>5.2.1 Additional information on publication of hospitality expenses</h4></header><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>All hospitality expenses that were charged to the responsibility centre of an individual subject to proactive publication or that were incurred on their behalf should be proactively published, even if the individual did not attend the hospitality activity.</li><li>In a situation where hospitality expenses have been charged, for example, to a branch cost centre but organized on behalf of an individual subject to proactive publication, the hospitality expenses should be published. If the expenses were not charged to the individual’s cost centre and were not incurred by them or on their behalf, although the individual attended the hospitality activity, there is no requirement to publish the expenses. However, in the interest of greater openness and transparency this information could still be proactively published.</li></ol></section><section class="panel panel-primary"><header class="panel-heading"><h4 class="mrgn-tp-0">Example 2: proactive publication of hospitality activity expenses</h4></header><div class="panel-body"><p><strong>Reference number:</strong> H-20YY-P4-00006</p><p><strong>Disclosure group:</strong> Senior officer or employee</p><p><strong>Title:</strong> Chief Financial Officer</p><p><strong>Name:</strong> John Smith</p><p><strong>Organization:</strong> Fisheries and Oceans Canada</p><p><strong>Purpose of hospitality activity:</strong> Refreshments and lunch: Aspiring Leaders Symposium</p><p><strong>Start date:</strong> 20YY-05-25</p><p><strong>End date:</strong> 20YY-05-25</p><p><strong>Municipality where the hospitality activity took place:</strong> Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</p><p><strong>Name of any commercial establishment or vendor involved in the hospitality activity:</strong> Rogers Centre Ottawa</p><p><strong>Attendees (Government of Canada officials):</strong> 150</p><p><strong>Attendees (guests):</strong> 4</p><p><strong>Total</strong><strong>amount of the expenses for the hospitality activity</strong>: $7,710.55</p></div></section></section><section><header class="panel-heading"><h3>5.3 Additional information on publication of travel and  hospitality expenses</h3></header><ol class="lst-lwr-alph"><li>Amounts must be reported in Canadian dollars and  include taxes.</li><li>Travel and hospitality expenses should be listed in  chronological order according to the date(s) on which the expenses were reimbursed,  so that the most recent expenses appear first.</li><li>Government institutions that have no travel or hospitality  expenses to report in a period (in other words, no one in the institution  incurred any travel or hospitality expenses) must submit a report that states  “nothing to report.” This report is known as a “nil report.” Institutions are  not to publish nil reports for each individual who has no travel or hospitality  expenses for a publication period.</li><li>Who reimbursed the expenses?
    <ol><li>A third party: If travel or hospitality expenses are  reimbursed by a third party (for example, a provincial body), the government  institution should post a zero-dollar transaction and provide additional  information in the “Additional comments” field.</li><li>A federal government institution: If travel or  hospitality expenses are reimbursed by another federal institution, the  institution that initially paid the expenses should proactively publish them  and provide additional information in the “Additional comments” field,  including the name of the institution that provided the reimbursement. The institution  that reimbursed the expenses does not have to publish the expense, but it may  choose to do so in the interests of transparency.</li></ol></li></ol></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha6">6. When do travel and hospitality expenses need to be proactively published?</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>, any travel and hospitality expenses incurred by individuals listed in section 4 of this guide must be published within 30 days after the end of the month in which these expenses were reimbursed. The publication deadlines are listed in Table 3.</p><p>Information published on the Open Government Portal must be uploaded to the Open Government Registry the day before the deadline for proactive publication so that the information can be published overnight to meet the legislated timeline for publication.</p><table class="table table-bordered table-condensed table-hover small"><caption class="text-left">Table 3: deadlines for publishing travel and hospitality expenses</caption><thead><tr class="active"><th scope="col">Reporting period in which expenses were reimbursed</th><th scope="col">Publication deadline<sup id="table3-fn1-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#table3-fn1"><span class="wb-inv">table 3 note </span>*</a></sup></th></tr></thead><tfoot><tr><td colspan="2"><section class="wb-fnote"><h3 id="table3-fn" class="wb-inv">Table 3 Notes</h3><dl><dt>Table 3 Note *</dt><dd id="table3-fn1"><p>When the deadline falls on a weekend or statutory holiday, the information must be published in electronic form by the last business day before that weekend or holiday.</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#table3-fn1-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to table 3 note </span>*<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd></dl></section></td></tr></tfoot><tbody><tr><td><p><strong>Period 1:</strong> April 1 to April 30</p></td><td><p>May 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 2:</strong> May 1 to May 31</p></td><td><p>June 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 3:</strong> June 1 to June 30</p></td><td><p>July 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 4:</strong> July 1 to July 31</p></td><td><p>August 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 5:</strong> August 1 to August 31</p></td><td><p>September 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 6:</strong> September 1 to September 30</p></td><td><p>October 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 7:</strong> October 1 to October 31</p></td><td><p>November 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 8:</strong> November 1 to November 30</p></td><td><p>December 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 9:</strong> December 1 to December 31</p></td><td><p>January 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 10:</strong> January 1 to January 31</p></td><td><p>March 2 (March 1 in a leap year)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 11:</strong> February 1 to February 28</p></td><td><p>March 30</p></td></tr><tr><td><p><strong>Period 12:</strong> March 1 to March 31</p></td><td><p>April 30</p></td></tr></tbody></table><section><h3>Corrections and adjustments</h3><p>Proactive publication should occur when the travel and hospitality expenses have been reimbursed (see the reimbursement criteria listed in section 7 of this guide).</p><p>The publication should not be delayed in anticipation of an adjustment to the information (such as a non-material cost that is charged long after the trip occurred or the hospitality was provided).</p><p>In the event of an error or adjustment in published information (for example, an additional unexpected processing fee is charged after the travel expenses have been proactively published), government institutions must correct or adjust the published information as soon as possible.</p></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha7">7. What does reimbursement of travel and hospitality expenses mean?</h2><div class="pol-content"><section><h3>7.1 When are travel expenses considered reimbursed?</h3><p>Under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>, any travel expenses incurred by an individual listed in section 4 of this guide must be proactively published within 30 days after the end of the month in which the travel expenses were reimbursed.</p><p>The reimbursement of travel expenses in the Government of Canada is complex for several reasons, including:</p><ul><li>Travel expenses can take different forms, for example:
						<ul><li>reimbursement of out‑of‑pocket expenses paid by an individual</li><li>prepaid expenses, such as airfare and hotel</li><li>allowances</li><li>advances</li></ul></li><li>Travel expenses can be incurred at different times, for example:
						<ul><li>before a trip (airfare and accommodations)</li><li>during a trip (meals and transportation)</li></ul></li><li>Travel expenses can be paid in different ways, for example:
						<ul><li>paid directly by the government institution</li><li>paid out of pocket by the individual and reimbursed later by the government institution</li></ul></li></ul><p>Because of these complexities, travel expenses are considered to have been reimbursed once <strong>all</strong> of the following have occurred:</p><ul><li>the travel expense claim for the trip has been approved</li><li>all of the expenses related to the travel have been granted certification authority and payment authority (sections 34 and 33 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>) by the appropriate individuals with delegated authority<sup id="fn3a-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn3"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>3</a></sup></li><li>all of the travel expenses are recorded in the government institution’s financial management system</li></ul><p>Note that all related travel expenses must be published together once all of the expenses are reimbursed as described above.</p><p>Figure 1 is an example of how to determine when a travel expense must be published. The example:</p><ul><li>is a timeline of the publication of travel expenses incurred by a senior officer or employee in a department</li><li>shows how the reimbursement of travel expenses triggers the deadline for proactive publication</li></ul><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 1: example of a timeline for the proactive publication of travel expenses</strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol-cont/32660-01-eng.png" alt="Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary>Figure 1 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 1 is an example of a timeline for the proactive  publication of travel expenses and the example is as follows: </p><ul><li>On September 6, a decision is made that  there is a need to travel</li><li>On September 15, the travel request is approved  by the appropriate delegated departmental manager, according to the  departmental delegation chart (expenditure initiation)</li><li>On September 20, the hotel and airline  tickets are booked</li><li>From October 22 to 23, the  employee travels and incurs out-of-pocket expenses for meals and transportation </li><li>On October 28, the employee returns to  work and the travel expense claim is prepared with the supporting receipts</li><li>On November 10, the travel expense  claim is approved, including supporting documentation and receipts (section 34  of the <em>Financial Administration  Act</em>)</li><li>On November 14, a requisition for  payment is made (section 33 of the <a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>), the employee is reimbursed and the expenses  are recorded in the departmental financial management system</li><li>On December 30, the travel expenses are  proactively published (30 days after the end of November)</li></ul></details></figure></section><section><h3>7.2 When are hospitality expenses considered reimbursed?</h3><p>Under the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>, any hospitality expenses incurred by an individual listed in section 4 of this guide must be proactively published within 30 days after the end of the month in which the hospitality expenses were reimbursed.</p><p>The reimbursement of hospitality expenses in the Government of Canada is complex because these expenses can result from various payment methods (for example, invoices, acquisition cards and reimbursements of out‑of‑pocket expenses), which means that some expenses are paid directly by the government institution and some are reimbursed to individuals. In addition, a hospitality activity may include several hospitality expenses, for example expenses related to providing refreshments, lunch and dinner.</p><p>As a result, the detailed total cost of the hospitality activity must be published 30 days after the end of the month once <strong>both</strong> of the following actions have occurred:</p><ul><li>all of the hospitality expenses related to the hospitality activity have been granted certification authority and payment authority (sections 34 and 33 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a>) from the appropriate individuals with delegated authority<sup id="fn3b-rf"><a class="fn-lnk" href="#fn3"><span class="wb-inv">Footnote </span>3</a></sup></li><li>all of the hospitality expenses related to the hospitality activity are recorded in the senior officer’s budget or the employee’s budget (responsibility centre) as a hospitality expense in the government institution’s financial management system</li></ul><p>Figure 2 is an example of how to determine when a hospitality expense must be published. The example:</p><ul><li>is a timeline of the publication of hospitality expenses incurred by a senior officer or employee in a department</li><li>shows how the reimbursement of hospitality expenses triggers the proactive publication deadline</li></ul><figure><figcaption class="text-center"><strong>Figure 2: example of a timeline for the proactive publication of hospitality expenses</strong></figcaption><img src="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol-cont/32660-02-eng.png" alt="Text version below:" class="img-responsive center-block" /><details class="brdr-tp brdr-rght brdr-bttm brdr-lft"><summary>Figure 2 - Text version</summary><p>Figure 2 is an example of a timeline for the proactive  publication of hospitality expenses and the example is as follows: </p><ul><li>On May 4, a decision is made that there  is a need to provide hospitality</li><li>On May 17, the hospitality request is approved  by the appropriate delegated departmental manager</li><li>On May 25, the hospitality activity  occurs</li><li>On June 20, the hospitality expense is  approved, including supporting documentation and receipts (section 34 of  the <em>Financial Administration Act</em>)</li><li>On June 26, a requisition for payment  is made (section 33 of the <em>Financial  Administration Act</em>); the expense  is recorded in the departmental financial management system, and is charged to the  responsibility centre of the senior official or employee</li><li>On July 30, the hospitality expenses  are proactively published (30 days after the end of June)</li></ul></details></figure></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha8">8. Where must travel and hospitality expenses be proactively published?</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>The <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a>:</p><ul><li>requires that travel and hospitality expenses be published in electronic form</li><li>provides that the President of the Treasury Board, as designated Minister, may specify the form of the publication</li></ul><p>As set out in the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32756"><em>Directive on Proactive Publication under the Access to Information Act</em></a>, information that is to be proactively published under Part 2 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em> must be published on the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat’s Open Government Portal.</p><p>Contact <a href="mailto:open-ouvert@tbs-sct.gc.ca">open-ouvert@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> for information about the Open Government Portal.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha9">9. Protecting what is not required or not permitted to be proactively published</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Pursuant to sections 80 and 90 of the <em>Access to Information Act</em>, when proactively publishing travel and hospitality expenses, an institution is required to not publish any information that would be required to be withheld if it were being disclosed in response to an access to information request. As well, an institution is not required to publish information that the institution could refuse to disclose in response to an access to information request. For example, the publication of travel and hospitality expenses is not required if the information would compromise national security, public safety or ongoing criminal investigations.</p><p>Government institutions should consult with their access to information and privacy coordinators for advice on whether specific information relating to government travel and hospitality expenses should be disclosed.</p></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha10">10. How is proactive publication monitored?</h2><div class="pol-content"><p>Government institutions are responsible for ensuring that:</p><ul><li>information about travel and hospitality expenses is accurate and up to date</li><li>the information is posted in accordance with this guide and with the following:

					<ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/index.html"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18310"><em>Directive on Access to Information Requests</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32756"><em>Directive on Proactive Publication under the Access to Information Act</em></a></li></ul></li></ul></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha11">11. References</h2><div class="pol-content"><section><h3>11.1 Legislation</h3><ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Ac</em>t</a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li></ul></section><section><h3>11.2 Other relevant documents</h3><ul><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18310"><em>Directive on Access to Information Requests</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32756"><em>Directive on Proactive Publication under the Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27228"><em>Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures</em></a></li><li>National Joint Council <a href="https://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d10/v238/en?print"><em>Travel Directive</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/travel-relocation/special-travel-authorities.html"><em>Special Travel Authorities</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html"><em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em></a></li></ul></section></div></section><section class="pol-sec"><h2 id="cha12">12. Enquiries</h2><div class="pol-content"><section><h3>12.1 Enquiries from the public</h3><p>Members of the public who have questions about this guide may contact the Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat Public Enquiries at <a href="mailto:questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca">questions@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a>.</p></section><section><h3>12.2 Enquiries from government institutions about access to information</h3><p>Individuals from government institutions should contact:</p><ul><li><a href="mailto:open-ouvert@tbs-sct.gc.ca">open-ouvert@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> for information and technical questions related to the Open Government Portal
					</li><li>their <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/ap/atip-aiprp/coord-eng.asp">access to information and privacy coordinator</a> for guidance related to their institution’s internal processes for the proactive publication of travel and hospitality expenses, including any questions related to removing personal information from travel and hospitality receipts</li></ul><p>Individuals from information and privacy groups may contact the Information and Privacy Policy Division of Treasury Board of Canada Secretariat at <a href="mailto:ippd-dpiprp@tbs-sct.gc.ca">ippd-dpiprp@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> for guidance on the following:</p><ul><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/A-1/"><em>Access to Information Act</em></a></li><li><a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/P-21/index.html"><em>Privacy Act</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12510"><em>Policy on Privacy Protection</em></a></li><li><a href="http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=12453"><em>Policy on Access to Information</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=18310"><em>Directive on Access to Information Requests</em></a></li><li><a href="https://www.tbs-sct.canada.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32756"><em>Directive on Proactive Publication under the Access to Information Act</em></a></li></ul></section><section><h3>12.3 Enquiries from government institutions about financial management</h3><p>Individuals from government institutions should contact:</p><ul><li>their financial policy group for guidance on the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27228"><em>Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures</em></a></li><li>their <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/psm-fpfm/pay-remuneration/travel-deplacements/dtc-cmv-eng.asp">designated travel coordinator</a> for guidance on the National Joint Council <a href="https://www.njc-cnm.gc.ca/directive/d10/v238/en?print"><em>Travel Directive</em></a> and the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/travel-relocation/special-travel-authorities.html"><em>Special Travel Authorities</em></a></li><li><a href="mailto:mino-cabmin@tbs-sct.gc.ca">mino-cabmin@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> for any guidance on the <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/treasury-board-secretariat/services/policies-ministers-offices-january-2011.html"><em>Policies for Ministers’ Offices</em></a></li></ul><p>Designated travel coordinators may contact <a href="mailto:ZZVOYAGE@tbs-sct.gc.ca">ZZVOYAGE@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a>.</p><p>Individuals from a departmental or agency financial policy group may contact <a href="mailto:fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca">fin-www@tbs-sct.gc.ca</a> for any questions on this guide and interpretation of the <a href="https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=27228"><em>Directive on Travel, Hospitality, Conference and Event Expenditures</em></a>.</p></section><section><h3>12.4 Enquiries from Crown corporations</h3><p>Individuals from Crown corporations or wholly owned subsidiaries should contact the internal financial management services or portfolio department at their parent Crown corporation if they have questions about this guide.</p></section></div></section></div><aside class="wb-fnote" role="note"><h2 id="fn">Footnotes</h2><dl><dt>Footnote fn1</dt><dd id="fn1"><p>
			According to the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-36.65/"><em>Conflict of Interest Act</em></a>, a ministerial adviser “means a person, other than a public servant, who occupies a position in the office of a minister of the Crown or a minister of state and who provides policy, program or financial advice to that person on issues relating to his or her powers, duties and functions as a minister of the Crown or a minister of state, whether or not the advice is provided on a full-time or part-time basis and whether or not the person is entitled to any remuneration or other compensation for the advice.”
		</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#fn1-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>1<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote fn2</dt><dd id="fn2"><p>
			According to the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-36.65/"><em>Conflict of Interest Act</em></a>, ministerial staff “means those persons, other than public servants, who work on behalf of a minister of the Crown or a minister of state.”       
		</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#fn2-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>2<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd><dt>Footnote fn3</dt><dd id="fn3"><p>
			Government institutions that are not subject to sections 33 and 34 of the <a href="http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/F-11/"><em>Financial Administration Act</em></a> are expected to have expenses approved in accordance with their internal travel approval process.      
		</p><p class="fn-rtn"><a href="#fn3a-rf"><span class="wb-inv">Return to footnote </span>3<span class="wb-inv"> referrer</span></a></p></dd></dl></aside><p class="mrgn-tp-lg text-center small"></p></div></div><!-- end main content --><div id="cdts-def-preFooter"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/preFooter-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/preFooter-en.html" --></div></main><div id="cdts-def-footer"><!-- Write closure fall-back static file --><!-- /ROOT/etc/designs/canada/cdts/gcweb/v5_0_2/cdts/static/footer-en.html --><!--#include virtual="/pol/GoC.WebTemplate/StaticFallbackFiles/gcweb/footer-en.html" --></div></body></html>